<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY imgroot "images/references/ref.json/">
<!ENTITY tp "ugr.ref.json.">
<!ENTITY % uimaents SYSTEM "../../target/docbook-shared/entities.ent" >  
%uimaents;
]>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->
<chapter id="ugr.ref.json">
  <title>JSON Serialization of CASs and UIMA Description objects</title>
  <titleabbrev>JSON support</titleabbrev>

  <section id="ugr.ref.json.overview">
    <title>JSON serialization support overview</title>
     
    <para>Applications are moving to the "cloud", and new applications are being rapidly developed that are hooking
    things up using various mashup techniques.  New standards and conventions are emerging to support this kind
    of application development, such as REST services.  
    JSON is now a popular way for services to communicate; 
    its popularity is rising (in 2014) while XML is falling.</para>
    
    <para>Starting with version 2.7.0, JSON style serialization (but not (yet) deserialization) 
    for CASs and UIMA descriptions is supported. 
    The exact format of the serialization is configurable in several aspects.  
    The implementation is built on top of the Jackson JSON generation library.   
    </para>
    
    <para>The next section discusses serialization for CASes, while a later section describes serialization
    of description objects, such as type system descriptions.</para>
  </section>
     
  <section id="ug.ref.json.cas">
    <title>JSON CAS Serialization</title>
    
    <para>CASs primarily consist of collections of Feature Structures (FSs). Similar to XMI serialization, JSON
    serialization skips serializing unreachable FSs, outputting only those FSs that are found in the indexes (these are called
    <emphasis>roots</emphasis>), plus all of  
    the FSs that are referenced via some chain of references, from the roots.  
    </para>
    
    <para>To support the kinds of things users do with FSs, 
    the serialized form may be augmented to include additional information beyond the FSs.</para>
    <para>For traditional UIMA implementations, the serialized formats mostly assumed that the receivers had access to
    a type system description, which specified details of the types of each feature value.  For JSON serialization,
    some of this information can be including directly in the serialization.</para>
        
    <para>This abbreviated type system information is one kind of additional information that can be included; 
    here's a summary list of the various kinds of additional information you can add to the serialization:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>having a way to identify which fields in a FS should be treated as references to other FSs, or
        as representing serialized binary data from UIMA byte arrays.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>something like XML namespaces to allow the use of short type names in the serialization while handling name
        collisions</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>enough of the UIMA type hierarchy to allow the common operation of iterating over a type together 
        with all of its subtypes</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para>A way to identify which FSs were "added-to-the-indexes" (separately, per CAS View) 
      and therefore serve as roots when 
      iterating over types.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para>An identification of the associated type system definition</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <para>Simple JSON serialization does not have a convention for supporting these, but many extensions do.
    We borrow some of the concepts in the JSON-LD (linked data) standard in providing this 
    additional information.</para>
    
    <section id="ug.ref.json.cas.bigpic">
      <title>The Big Picture</title>

	    <para>CAS JSON serialization consists of several parts: an optional _context, the set of Feature Structures,
	    and (if doing a delta serialization) information about changes to what was indexed.</para>
	    
	    <figure id="ug.ref.json.fig.bigpic">
	      <title>The major sections of JSON serialization</title>
		    <mediaobject>
	        <imageobject>
	          <imagedata width="3.5in" format="PNG" fileref="&imgroot;big_picture2.png"/>
	        </imageobject>
	        <textobject><phrase>The big picture showing the parts of serialization, with the _context optional.</phrase>
	        </textobject>
	      </mediaobject>
      </figure>
	       
    <para>The serializer can be configured to omit
    the _context or parts of the _context for cases where that information isn't needed.  The index changes
    information is only included if Delta CAS serialization is specified.  Note that Delta CAS support
    is incomplete; so this information is just for planning purposes.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="ug.ref.json.cas.context">
      <title>The _context section</title>
          <para>The _context section has entries for each used type as well as some special additional entries. 
          Each entry for a type has multiple sub-entries, identified
          by a key-name.  Each sub-entry can be selectively omitted if not needed.
          
          
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">_type_system</emphasis> - a URI of the type system information</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">_types</emphasis> - information about each used type
              <itemizedlist>
		            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">_id</emphasis> - the type's fully qualified UIMA type name</para></listitem>
		            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">_feature_types</emphasis> - a map from features of this type to 
		                                information about the type of the value of the feature</para></listitem>
		            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">_subtypes</emphasis> - an array of used subtype short-names</para></listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </para></listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          </para>
          
			    
			    <para>Here's an example:</para>
			    <informalexample>  <!-- does a keep-together -->
			    <?dbfo keep-together="always" ?>
          <programlisting>"_context" : {
  "_type_system" : "URI to the type system information",
  "_types : {
    "A_Typical_User_or_built_in_Type" : {
      "_id" : "org.apache.uima.test.A_Typical_User_or_built_in_Type", 
      "_feature_types" : [
           "sofa"         : "_ref", 
           "aFS"          : "_ref", 
           "an_array"     : "_array",
           "a_byte_array" : "_byte_array"],
      "_subtypes" : [ "subtype1", "subtype2", ... ] }, 
    "Sofa" : {
      "_id" : "uima.cas.Sofa", 
      "_feature_types" : {"sofaArray" : "_ref"} }
  }
}</programlisting></informalexample>

      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">_type_system</emphasis> is an optional URI that references a UIMA type system description that
      defines the types for the CAS being serialized.</para>
      
      <para>In the <emphasis role="bold">_types</emphasis> section, the key (e.g. "Sofa" or "A_Typical_User_or_built_in_Type") is the "short" name 
      for the type used in the serialization.  
      It is either just
      the last segment of the full type name (e.g. for the type x.y.z.TypeName, it's TypeName), or, 
      if name would collide with another type name if just the last segment
      was used (example:  some.package.cname.Foo,  and some.other.package.cname.Foo), then the key is made up of
      the next-to-last segment, with an optional suffixed incrementing integer in case of collisions on that name,
      a colon (:) and then the last name.</para>
      
      <blockquote><para>In this example, since the next to last segment of both names is
      "cname", one namespace name would be "cname", and the other would be "cname1".  The keys in this case would be
      cname:Foo and cname1:Foo.</para></blockquote>
      
      <para>The value of the _id is the fully qualified name of the type.</para>
      
      <para>The <emphasis role="bold">_feature_types</emphasis> values of _ref, _array, and _byte_array indicate the corresponding values 
      of the named features need special handling 
      when deserailized.
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">_ref</emphasis> - used when features are deserialized as numbers, but they are to be
      interpreted as references to other FSs whose <code>id</code> is the number.  UIMA lists and arrays of 
      FSs are marked with _ref; if the value is a JSON array, the elements of the array will be either
      numbers (to be interpreted as references), or embedded serializations of FSs.</para></listitem>
      
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">_array</emphasis> - used when features are serialized as JSON 
        arrays containing embedded values, 
      unless the corresponding UIMA object has
      multiple references, in which case it is serialized as a FS reference which looks like a single number.
      If a feature is marked with _array, then a non-array, single number should be interpreted as the
      <code>id</code> of the feature structure that is the array or the first element of the list of items.
      This designation is used for both UIMA arrays and lists.</para>
      
      <para>This designation is for arrays and lists of primitive values, except for byte arrays.  
      In the case of FS arrays and lists, the _ref designation is used instead of this to indicate that the 
      resulting values in a JSON array that look like numbers should be interpreted as references.</para></listitem>
      
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">_byte_array</emphasis> - _byte_array features are serialized numbers (if they are a 
      reference to a separate object, or as strings (if embedded).  The strings are to be decoded into
      binary byte arrays using the Base64 encoding (the standard one used by Jackson to serialize binary data).</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>  
      </para>
      
      <para>
      Note that single element arrays are <emphasis>not</emphasis> unwrapped, as in some other JSON serializations, to enable distinguishing
      references to arrays from embedded arrays.
      </para>

      <para><emphasis role="bold">_subtypes</emphasis> are a list of the type's used subtypes.  A type is <emphasis>used</emphasis>
       if it is the type of a Feature Structure
      being serialized,
      or if it is in the supertype chain of some Feature Structure which is serialized.  If a type has no
      used subtypes, this element is omitted.
      The names are represented as the "short" name.  Users typically use this information
      to construct support for iterators over a type which includes all of its subtypes.</para>

     
      
      <!-- 
      <para>_supertypes are a list of the type's supertypes, in the natural nearest to farthest order.
      The list is truncated as soon as a type is mentioned which already (in a previous _supertypes)
      has had its supertypes enumerated.</para> -->
      
      <section id="ug.ref.json.cas.context.omit">
          <title>Omitting parts of the _context section</title>
          <para>It is possible to selectively omit some of the 
          _context sections (or the entire _context), via configuration.  
          Here's an example:</para>

          <informalexample>  <!-- does a keep-together -->
          
          <programlisting>// make a new instance to hold the serialization configuration           
JsonCasSerializer jcs = new JsonCasSerializer();  
// Omit the expanded type names information
jcs.setJsonContext(JsonContextFormat.omitExpandedTypeNames);</programlisting></informalexample>
         
          <para>See the Javadocs for <code>JsonContextFormat</code> for how to specify the parts.</para>
      </section>
      
    </section>  <!-- of context -->
    
    <section id="ug.ref.json.cas.featurestructures">
      <title>Serializing Feature Structures</title>
      
    <para>Feature Structures themselves are represented as JSON objects consisting of field - value pairs, where the 
    fields correspond to UIMA Features, and the values are the values of the features. 
    </para>
    
    <para>The various kinds of values for a UIMA feature are represented by their natural JSON counterpart.
    UIMA primitive boolean values are represented by JSON true and false literals. UIMA Strings are 
    represented as JSON strings.  Numbers are represented by JSON numbers. 
    Byte Arrays are represented by the Jackson standard binary encoding (base64 encoding), written as JSON strings. 
    References to other Feature Structures are also represented as JSON integer numbers, the values of which are 
    interpreted as ids of the referred-to
    FSs.  These ids are treated in the same manner as the xmi:ids of XMI Serialization.  Arrays and Lists when
    embedded (see following section) are represented as JSON arrays using the [] notation.</para>
    
    <para>Besides the feature values defined for a Feature Structure, an additional special feature
    may be serialized:  _type.  
    The _type is the type name, written using the short format.  This is automatically included when the type cannot 
    easily be
    inferred from other contextual information. 
    </para>
    
    <para>Here's an example, with some comments which, since JSON doesn't support comments, are just here for explanation:</para>
              <informalexample>  <!-- does a keep-together -->
    <programlisting>{ "_type" : "Annotation", // _type may be omitted
  "feat1" : true,   // boolean value represented as true or false
  "feat2" : 123,    // could be a number or a reference to FS with id 123
  "feat3" : "b3axgh"//could be a string or a base64 encoded byte array
}</programlisting></informalexample>    
        
    
    <section id="ug.ref.json.cas.featurestructures.embedding">
      <title>Embedding normally referenced values</title>
      
      <para>Consider a FS which has a feature that refers to another FS.  This can be serialized in one of two ways:</para>
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem><para>the value of the feature can be coded as an <code>id</code> (a number), where the number is the <code>id</code> of the
        referred-to FS.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>The value of the feature can be coded as the serialization of the referred-to FS.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      
      <para>
      This second way of encoding is often done by JSON style serializations, and is called "embedding".  Referred-to 
      FSs may be embedded if there are no other references to the embedded FS.  Multiple references may arise due to
      having a FS referenced as a "root" in some CAS View, or being used as a value in a FS feature.</para>
      
      <para>Following the XMI conventions, UIMA arrays and lists which are 
      identified as singly referenced by either the static or dynamic method (see below) are embedded
      directly as the value of a feature.  In this case, the JSON serialization writes out the value of the feature
      as a JSON array.  Otherwise, the value is written out as a FS reference, and a separate serialization occurs of 
      the list elements or the array.</para>
      
      <para>In addition to arrays and lists, FSs which are identifed as singly referenced from another FS are
      serialized as the embedded value of the referring feature.  
      This is also done (when using the dynamic method) for singly referenced rooted instances.
      </para>
      <para>  
      If a FS is multiply referenced, the serialization in these
      cases is just the numeric value of the <code>id</code> of the FS.</para>
      </section>
      
      <section id="ug.ref.json.cas.featurestructures.dynamicstatic">
        <title>Dynamic vs Static multiple-references and embedding</title>
      
      <para>There are two methods of determining if a particular FS or list or array can be embedded.
      
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">dynamic</emphasis> - calculates at serilization time whether or not there
        are multiple references to a given FS.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">static</emphasis> - looks in the type system definition to see if 
        the feature is marked with &lt;multipleReferencesAllowed&gt;.  
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem><para><code>multipleReferencesAllowed</code> false &rarr; use the embedded style</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><code>multipleReferencesAllowed</code> true &rarr; use separate objects</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        Note that since this flag is not available for 
        references to FSs from View indexes, any FS that is indexed in any view is considered (if using static mode)
        to be multipleReferencesAllowed. 
        </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      </para>
       
      <para>Delta serialization only supports the static method; this mode is forced on if delta serialization
      is specified.</para>
       
      <para>Dynamic embedding is enabled by default for JSON, but may be disabled via configuration.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="ug.ref.json.cas.featurestructures.embeddedArraysLists">
      <title>Embedded Arrays and Lists</title>
    
    <para>When static embedding is being used, a case can arise where some feature is marked to have only 
    singly referenced FS values, but that value may actually be multiply referenced.  This is detected during 
    serialization, and an message is issued if an error handler has been specified to the serializer.
    The serialization continues, however.  In the case of an Array, the value of the array is embedded
    in the serialization and the fact that these were referring to the same object is lost.
    In the case of a list, if any element in the list
    has multiple references (for example,  if the list has back-references, loops, etc.), 
    the serialization of the list is truncated at the point where the multiple reference
    occurs.</para>
    
    <blockquote><para>Note that you can correctly serialize arbitrarily linked complex list structures created 
    using the built-in list types only if you use dynamic embedding, or 
    specify <code>multipleReferencesAllowed</code> = true.</para></blockquote> 
    
    
    <para>Embedded list or array values are both serialized using the JSON array notation; as a result, these
    alternative representations are not distinguised in the JSON serialization.</para>
    </section>  <!-- end of embedded Arraylists-->
    
    <section id="ug.ref.json.cas.featurestructures.null">
      <title>Omitting null values</title>
    
      <para>Following the conventions established in XMI serialization, features with <code>null</code> values have their
      key-value pairs omitted from the FS serialization when the type of the feature value is:
      </para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>a Feature Structure Reference</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>a String ( whose value is <code>null</code>, not "" (a 0-length String))</para>
      </listitem>
            <listitem>
        <para>an embedded Array or List (where the entire array and/or list is <code>null</code>)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <note><para>Inside arrays or lists of FSs, references which are being serialized
    as references have a <code>null</code> reference coded as the number 0; references which are embedded are serialized as 
    <code>null</code>.</para></note>
    
    <para>Configuring the serializer with <code>setOmit0Values(true)</code> causes
    additional primitive features (byte/short/int/long/float/double) to be omitted, when their values are 0 or 0.0</para>
        
    </section>
        
    </section>
    
    </section>
        
    <section id="ug.ref.json.cas.featurestructures.organization">
      <title>Organizing the Feature Structures</title>
    
    <para>The set of all FSs being serialized is divided into two parts.  The first part represents
    all FSs that are root FSs, in that they were in one or more indexes at the time of serialization.  The second part
    represents feature structures that are multiply referenced, or are referenced via a chain of references from the
    root FSs.  The same feature structure can appear in both lists.  The elements in the second part are actual 
    serialized FSs, whereas, the elements in the first part are either references to the corresponding FSs in the
    second part, if they exist, or the actual embedded serialized FSs.  Actual embedded serialized FSs only
    exist once in the two parts.</para>
    
              <informalexample>  <!-- does a keep-together -->
    <programlisting>"_views" : {
  "_InitialView" : {
     "theFirstType" : [  { ... fs1 ...}, 123, 456, { ... fsn ...} ]
     "anotherType"  : [  { ... fs1 ...}, ... { ... fsn ...} ]
      ...     // more types which have roots in view "12"
         },
  "AnotherView" : {
     "theFirstType" : [  { ... fsv1 ...}, 123, { ... fsvn ...} ]
     "anotherType"  : [  { ... fsv1 ...}, ... { ... fsvn ...} ]
      ...     // more types which have roots in view "25"
         },
   ...        // more views         
}, 

"_referenced_fss" : {
  "12" : {"_type" : "Sofa",  "sofaNum" : 1,  "sofaID" : "_InitialView" },
  "25" : {"_type" : "Sofa",  "sofaNum" : 2,  "sofaID" : "AnotherView" },
  
  "123" : { ... fs-123 ... },
  "456" : { ... fs-456 ... },
  ...
}</programlisting></informalexample>
    
    <para>The first part map is made up of multiple maps, one for each separate CAS View.
    The outer map is keyed by the <code>id</code> of the corresponding SofaFS (or 0, if there is no corresponding SofaFS).
    For each view, the value is a map whose key is a used Type, and the values are an array of instances
    of FSs of that type which were found in some index; these are the "root" FSs.  Only root instances
    of a particular type are included in this array.  
    </para>
    
        
    <para>The second part map has keys which are the <code>id</code> value of the FSs, and values which are 
    a map of key-value pairs corresponding to the feature-values of that FS.
    In this case, the _type extra feature is added to record the type.</para>
    
    <!--       
    <para>
    FSs can be referenced either from being the value of some Feature in an FS, or 
    by being in one or more indexes at the time of serialization. 
    If there are more than 1 of these kinds of references, then the FS is
    multiply referenced.  All FSs that are multiply referenced are not "embedded" at their reference points;
    instead each reference point has a value which is the <code>id</code> of that FS, and which can be used as the "key"
    in the _referenced_fss map to obtain the actual serialized form of the FS.</para>
     -->
    
    <para>The _views map, keyed by view and type name, has all the FSs (as an JSON array) for that type that were in
    one or more indexes in any View.  If a FS in this array is not multiply referenced (using dynamic mode), 
    then it is embedded here. Otherwise, only the reference (a simple number representing the <code>id</code> of that FS) is serialized for that FS.</para>
    
    <!-- 
    <para>Here's a picture of what the _types map would look like with two views, with Sofa ids of 22 and 99.</para>
    
    <figure>
      <title>Feature Structure Organization</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="2.5in" format="PNG" fileref="&imgroot;multi.view.png"/>
          </imageobject>
          <textobject><phrase>Multi-view serialized Feature Structures</phrase></textobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </figure>   
          -->
               
    </section>  <!-- of representing the collection of FSs -->

    <!--  
    <section id="ug.ref.json.cas.casviews">
      <title>CAS Views</title>
      <para>The last section in a JSON CAS serialization is the _cas_views.  
      This contains for each view, an array of IDs of FSs that the serializing application added to its indexes.  
        These arrays are stored in a map, with the key being the <code>id</code> for the Sofa FS associated with the view, or
        "0" for the edge case where no Sofa has (yet) been created for the initial view (this is an edge case that
        normally will not occur). For
        delta-cas serialization (where only changes are being serialized), this array is replaced with a map 
        of 3 keys:  "added-members", "deleted-members", and "reindexed-members", 
        the values of which are arrays of IDs of FSs which were added, removed, or reindexed by the application
        doing the serializing.</para>
        
      <para>In some cases, the receiving application may only want to index FSs 
      that the serializing application had indexed, but otherwise, this information is not of much use 
      to that application, as that application would likely have its own indexing needs.  .</para>
    
    </section> <!- - end of cas views - ->
     -->
    <!--  
    <section id="ug.ref.json.cas.xmidiff">
      <title>Differences with XMI serialization</title>
      
      <para>JSON serialization shares the same implementation core with XMI serialization,
      except of course for serializing in JSON formats vs XMI/XML formats.
      One area where it differs is in the treatment of so-called out-of-type-system data.</para>
      
      <para>XMI deserialization can be specified with a "lenient" flag, which allows the incoming data to 
    include types and features which are not present in the type system being deserialized into. These 
    data are called "out-of-type-system" data (oots).  The XMI serialization merges the oots data back into the
    the output serialization (if not doing a delta-cas serialization), thus preserving types and features in the
    serialization it doesn't have definitions for.</para>
    
    <para>
    JSON serialization doesn't support this, mainly because there's no type information available for the 
    oots data, and the JSON _context information for these types can't be generated.</para>
     -->      
        

     
    <section id="ug.ref.json.cas.features">
      <title>Additional JSON CAS Serialization features</title>

    <para>JSON serialization also supports several additional features, including:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <!-- 
      <listitem>
        <para>)Delta CAS: only serializes changes since the mark was set</para>
      </listitem>
       -->
      <listitem>
        <para>Type and feature filtering: only types and features that exist in a specified type system description 
        are serialized.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>An ErrorHandler; this will be called in various error situations, including when 
        serializing in static mode an array or list value for a feature marked <code>multipleReferencesAllowed = false</code>
        is found to have multiple references.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>A switch to control omitting of numeric features that have 0 values (default is to include these).
        See the <code>setOmit0Values(true_or_false)</code> method in JsonCasSerializer.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>a pretty printing flag (default is not to do pretty-printing)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>See the Javadocs for JsonCasSerializer for details.</para>
    
    <section id="ugr.ref.json.delta">
      <title>Delta CAS</title>
      
      <note><para>Delta CAS support is incomplete, and is not supported as of release 2.7.0, but may
      be supported in later releases.  The information here is just for planning purposes.</para></note>
      
      <para><emphasis role="bold">_delta_cas</emphasis> is present only when a delta CAS serialization is being performed.  
      This serializes just the 
      changes in the CAS since a Mark was set; so for cases where a large CAS is deserialized into a service, which
      then does a relatively small amount of additions and modifications, only those changes are serialized.
      The values of the keys are arrays of the ids of FSs that were added to the indexes, 
      removed from the indexes, or reindexed.</para>
      
      <para>This mode requires the static embeddability mode.  When specified, a <code>_delta_cas</code> key-value 
      is added to the serialization at the end, 
      which lists the FSs (by <code>id</code>) that were added, removed, or reindexed, since the mark was set.  
      Additional extra information, created when the CAS was previously deserialized and the mark set, 
      must be passed to the serializer, in the form of an instance of <code>XmiSerializationSharedData</code>,
      or JsonSerializationSharedData (not yet defined as of release 2.7.0).</para>
      
      <para>Here's what the last part of the serialization looks like, when Delta CAS is specified:
                <informalexample>  <!-- does a keep-together -->
      <programlisting>"_delta_cas" : {
  "added_members" : [  123, ... ],
  "deleted_members" : [  456, ... ],
  "reindexed_members" : [] }</programlisting></informalexample>
      </para>
      
      
    </section>
  </section>

  
  <section id="ugr.ref.json.usage">
    <title>Using JSON CAS serialization</title>
    
    <para>The support is built on top the Jackson JSON serialization
    package.  We follow Jackson conventions for configuring.</para>
    
    <para>The serialization APIs are in the JsonCasSerializer class.</para>
    
    <para>Although there are some static short-cut methods for common use cases, the basic operations needed
    to serialize a CAS as JSON are:</para>
    
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Make an instance of the <code>JsonCasSerializer</code> class.  This will serve to collect configuration information.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Do any additional configuration needed.  See the Javadocs for details.  
        The following objects can be configured:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The <code>JsonCasSerializer</code> object: here you can specify the kind of JSON formatting, what to serialize,
            whether or not delta serialization is wanted, prettyprinting, and more.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The underlying <code>JsonFactory</code> object from Jackson.  Normally, you won't need to configure this.
            If you do, you can create your own instance of this object and configure it and use it in the
            serialization.</para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>The underlying <code>JsonGenerator</code> from Jackson. Normally, you won't need to configure this.
            If you do, you can get the instance the serializer will be using and configure that.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Once all the configuration is done, the serialize(...) call is done in this class, 
        which will create a one-time-use
        inner class where the actual serialization is done.  The serialize(...) method is thread-safe, in that the same 
        JsonCasSerializer instance (after it has been configured) can kick off multiple 
        (identically configured) serializations 
        on different threads at the same time.</para>
        <para>The serialize call follows the Jackson conventions, taking one of 3 specifications of where to serialize to:
        a Writer, an OutputStream, or a File.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <para>Here's an example:</para>
              <informalexample>  <!-- does a keep-together -->
    <programlisting>JsonCasSerializer jcs = new JsonCasSerializer();
jcs.setPrettyPrint(true); // do some configuration
StringWriter sw = new StringWriter();                          
jcs.serialize(cas, sw); // serialize into sw</programlisting></informalexample>
    
    <para>The JsonCasSerializer class also has some static convenience methods for JSON serialization, for the
    most common configuration cases; please see the Javadocs for details. These are named jsonSerialize, to 
    distinguish them from the non-static serialize methods.</para>

    <para>Many of the common configuration methods generally return the instance, so they can be chained together.
    For example, if <code>jcs</code> is an instance of the JsonCasSerializer, you can write
    <code>jcs.setPrettyPrint(true).setOmit0values(true);</code> to configure both of these.</para>

   <!--  of configuring  -->

  </section> <!--  of JSON Cas Serialization -->
  
  <section id="ugr.ref.json.descriptionserialization">
    <title>JSON serialization for UIMA descriptors</title>
    
    <para>UIMA descriptors are things like analysis engine descriptors, type system descriptors, etc. 
    UIMA has an internal form for these, typically named UIMA <emphasis>description</emphasis>s; 
    these can be serialized out as XML using a <code>toXML</code> method.  
    JSON support adds the ability to serialize these a JSON objects, as well.  It may be of use, for example,
    to have the full type system description for a UIMA pipeline available in JSON notation.
    </para>
    
    <para>The class JsonMetaDataSerializer defines a set of static methods that serialize UIMA description objects
    using a toJson method that takes as an argument the description object to be serialized, and the standard
    set of serialiization targets that Jackson supports (File, Writer, or OutputStream).  There is also
    an optional prettyprint flag (default is no prettyprinting).</para>
    
    <para>The resulting JSON serialization is just a straight-forward serialization of the description object,
    having the same fields as the XML serialization of it.</para>
    
    <para>Here's what a small TypeSystem description looks like, serialized:</para>
    
              <informalexample>  <!-- does a keep-together -->
    <programlisting>{"typeSystemDescription" : 
  {"name" : "casTestCaseTypesystem",  
   "description" : "Type system description for CAS test cases.",  
   "version" : "1.0",  
   "vendor" : "Apache Software Foundation",  
   "types" : [
     {"typeDescription" : 
       {"name" : "Token",  
        "description" : "",  
         "supertypeName" : "uima.tcas.Annotation",  
         "features" : [
           {"featureDescription" : 
             {"name" : "type",  
              "description" : "",  
              "rangeTypeName" : 
              "TokenType" } }, 
           {"featureDescription" : 
             {"name" : "tokenFloatFeat",  
              "description" : "",  
              "rangeTypeName" : "uima.cas.Float" } } ] } }, 
     {"typeDescription" : 
       {"name" : "TokenType",  
        "description" : "",  
        "supertypeName" : "uima.cas.TOP" } } ] } }</programlisting></informalexample>
        
    <para>Here's a sample of code to serialize a UIMA description object held in the variable <code>tsd</code>, with 
    and without pretty printing:</para>
    
 
          <informalexample>  <!-- does a keep-together -->
    <programlisting>StringWriter sw = new StringWriter();                               
JsonMetaDataSerializer.toJSON(tsd, sw); // no prettyprinting

sw = new StringWriter();             
JsonMetaDataSerializer.toJSON(tsd, sw, true); // prettyprinting</programlisting></informalexample>
  </section>
  
</chapter>