<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY imgroot "../images/tools/tools.cpe/" >
<!ENTITY % uimaents SYSTEM "../entities.ent" >  
%uimaents;
]>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->
<chapter id="ugr.tools.cpe">
  <title>Collection Processing Engine Configurator User&apos;s Guide</title>
  <titleabbrev>CPE Configurator User&apos;s Guide</titleabbrev>
  
  <para>A <emphasis>Collection Processing Engine (CPE)</emphasis> processes
    collections of artifacts (documents) through the combination of the following
    components: a Collection Reader, Analysis Engines, and CAS Consumers.
    <footnote><para>Earlier versions of UIMA supported another component, the CAS
    Initializer, but this component is now deprecated in UIMA Version 2.</para></footnote>
    </para>
  
  <para>The <emphasis>Collection Processing Engine Configurator(CPE
    Configurator)</emphasis> is a graphical tool that allows you to assemble and run
    CPEs.</para>
  
  <para>For an introduction to Collection Processing Engine concepts, including
    developing the components that make up a CPE, read <olink
      targetdoc="&uima_docs_tutorial_guides;" targetptr="ugr.tug.cpe"/>. This
    chapter is a user&apos;s guide for using the CPE Configurator tool, and does not describe
    UIMA&apos;s Collection Processing Architecture itself.</para>
  
  <section id="ugr.tools.cpe.limitations">
    <title>Limitations of the CPE Configurator</title>
    
    <para>The CPE Configurator only supports basic CPE configurations.</para>
    
    <para>It only supports <quote>Integrated</quote> deployments (although it will
      connect to remotes if particular CAS Processors are specified with remote service
      descriptors). It doesn&apos;t support configuration of the error handling. It
      doesn&apos;t support Sofa Mappings; it assumes all Single-View components are
      operating with the _InitialView Sofa. Multi-View components will not have their names
      mapped. It sets up a fixed-sized CAS Pool.</para>
    
    <para>To set these additional options, you must edit the CPE Descriptor XML file
      directly.  See <olink
      targetdoc="&uima_docs_ref;" targetptr="ugr.ref.xml.cpe_descriptor"/> for the syntax.
      You may then open the CPE Descriptor in the CPE Configurator and run it.  The changes
      you applied to the CPE Descriptor <emphasis>will</emphasis> be respected, although you
      will not be able to see them or edit them from the GUI.
    </para>   
  </section>
  
  <section id="ugr.tools.cpe.starting">
    <title>Starting the CPE Configurator</title>
    
    <para>The CPE Configurator tool can be run using the <literal>cpeGui</literal> shell
      script, which is located in the <literal>bin</literal> directory of the UIMA SDK. If
      you&apos;ve installed the example Eclipse project (see <olink
        targetdoc="&uima_docs_overview;"
        targetptr="ugr.ovv.eclipse_setup.example_code"/>, you can also run it using the
      <quote>UIMA CPE GUI</quote> run configuration provided in that project.</para>
    <note><para>If you are planning to build a CPE using components other than the examples
    included in the UIMA SDK, you will first need to update your CLASSPATH environment
    variable to include the classes needed by these components.</para></note>
    
    <para>When you first start the CPE Configurator, you will see the main window shown here:
      
      
      <screenshot>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata width="5.8in" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;image002.jpg"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject><phrase>CPE Configurator main GUI window</phrase> 
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot></para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="ugr.tools.cpe.selecting_component_descriptors">
    <title>Selecting Component Descriptors</title>
    
    <para>The CPE Configurator&apos;s main window is divided into three sections, one each for the Collection
      Reader, Analysis Engines, and CAS Consumers.<footnote>
      <para>There is also a fourth pane, for the CAS Initializer, but it is hidden by default. To enable it click the
        <literal>View &rarr; CAS Initializer Panel</literal> menu item.</para></footnote></para>
    
    <para>In each section of the CPE Configurator, you can select the component(s) you want to use by browsing to (or
      typing the location of) their XML descriptors. You must select a Collection Reader, and at least one Analysis
      Engine or CAS Consumer.</para>
    
    <para>When you select a descriptor, the configuration parameters that are defined in that descriptor will then
      be displayed in the GUI; these can be modified to override the values present in the descriptor.</para>
    
    <para>For example, the screen shot below shows the CPE Configurator after the following components have been
      chosen:
      
      
      <programlisting>examples/descriptors/collectionReader/FileSystemCollectionReader.xml
examples/descriptors/analysis_engine/NamesAndPersonTitles_TAE.xml
examples/descriptors/cas_consumer/XmiWriterCasConsumer.xml</programlisting></para>
    
    
    <screenshot>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata width="5.8in" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;image004.jpg"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject><phrase>CPE Configurator after components chosen</phrase> 
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
    
  </section>
  
  <section id="ugr.tools.cpe.running">
    <title>Running a Collection Processing Engine</title>
    
    <para>After selecting each of the components and providing configuration settings,
      click the play (forward arrow) button at the bottom of the screen to begin processing. A
      progress bar should be displayed in the lower left corner. (Note that the progress bar
      will not begin to move until all components have completed their initialization, which
      may take several seconds.) Once processing has begun, the pause and stop buttons become
      enabled.</para>
    
    <para>If an error occurs, you will be informed by an error dialog. If processing completes
      successfully, you will be presented with a performance report.</para>
    
  </section>
  
  <section id="ugr.tools.cpe.file_menu">
    <title>The File Menu</title>
    
    <para>The CPE Configurator&apos;s File Menu has the following options:</para>
    
    <itemizedlist><listitem><para>Open CPE Descriptor</para></listitem>
      
      <listitem><para>Save CPE Descriptor</para></listitem>

      <listitem><para>Save Options (submenu)</para></listitem>
      
      <listitem><para>Refresh Descriptors from File System</para></listitem>
      
      <listitem><para>Clear All</para></listitem>
      
      <listitem><para>Exit </para></listitem></itemizedlist>
    
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Open CPE Descriptor</emphasis> will allow you to select a
      CPE Descriptor file from disk, and will read in that CPE Descriptor and configure the GUI
      appropriately.</para>
    
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Save CPE Descriptor</emphasis> will create a CPE
      Descriptor file that defines the CPE you have constructed. This CPE Descriptor will
      identify the components that constitute the CPE, as well as the configuration settings
      you have specified for each of these components. Later, you can use <quote>Open CPE
      Descriptor</quote> to restore the CPE Configurator to the state. Also, CPE
      Descriptors can be used to easily run a CPE from a Java program &ndash; see <olink
        targetdoc="&uima_docs_tutorial_guides;"
        targetptr="ugr.tug.application.running_a_cpe_from_a_descriptor"/>
      .</para>
    
    <para>CPE Descriptors also allow specifying operational parameters, such as error
      handling options that are not currently available for configuration through the CPE
      Configurator. For more information on manually creating a CPE Descriptor, see <olink
        targetdoc="&uima_docs_ref;" targetptr="ugr.ref.xml.cpe_descriptor"/>
      .</para>
    
    <para>The <emphasis role="bold">Save Options</emphasis> submenu has one item,
      "Use &lt;import>".  If this item is checked (the default), saved CPE descriptors
      will use the <literal>&lt;import></literal> syntax to refer to their component 
      descriptors.  If unchecked, the older <literal>&lt;include></literal> syntax will
      be used for new components that you add to your CPE using the GUI.  (However, if you  
      open a CPE descriptor that used &lt;import>, these imports will not be replaced.)    
    </para>
    
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Refresh Descriptors from File System</emphasis> will
      reload all descriptors from disk. This is useful if you have made a change to the
      descriptor outside of the CPE Configurator, and want to refresh the display.</para>
    
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Clear All</emphasis> will reset the CPE Configurator to
      its initial state, with no components selected.</para>
    
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Exit</emphasis> will close the CPE Configurator. If you
      have unsaved changes, you will be prompted as to whether you would like to save them to a
      CPE Descriptor file. If you do not save them, they will be lost.</para>
    
    <para>When you restart the CPE Configurator, it will automatically reload the last CPE
      descriptor file that you were working with.</para>
    
  </section>
  
  <section id="ugr.tools.cpe.help_menu">
    <title>The Help Menu</title>
    
    <para>The CPE Configurator&apos;s Help menu provides <quote>About</quote>
      information and some very simple instructions on how to use the tool.</para>
    
  </section>
</chapter>