<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY imgroot "../images/tools/tools.cvd/" >
<!ENTITY % uimaents SYSTEM "../entities.ent" >  
%uimaents;
]>
<!--
 Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
 or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
 distributed with this work for additional information
 regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
 "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
 with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at
 
 http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 
 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
 software distributed under the License is distributed on an
 "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
 KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
 specific language governing permissions and limitations
 under the License.
-->
<chapter id="ugr.tools.cvd">
 <title>CAS Visual Debugger</title>
 <section id="ugr.tools.cvd.introduction">
 <title>Introduction</title>
 <para>
  The CAS Visual Debugger is a tool to run text analysis engines in UIMA
  and view the results. The tool is implemented as a stand-alone GUI 
  tool using Java's Swing library.
 </para>
 <para>
  This is a developer's tool.  It is intended to support you in writing
  text analysis annotators for UIMA (Unstructured Information Management
  Architecture).  As a development tool, the emphasis is not so much on
  pretty pictures, but rather on navigability.  It is intended to show
  you all the information you need, and show it to you quickly (at least
  on a fast machine ;-).
 </para>
 <para>
  The main purpose of this application is to let you browse all the data
  that was created when you ran an analysis engine over some text.  The
  display mimics the access methods you have in the CAS API in terms of
  indexes, types, feature structures and feature values.
 </para>
 <para>
  As in the CAS, there is special support for annotations.  Clicking on
  an annotation will select the corresponding text, and conversely, you
  can display all annotations that cover a given position in the text.
  This will be explained in more detail in the section on the main
  display area.
 </para>
 <para>
  As usual, the graphics in this manual are for illustrative purposes
  and may not look 100% like the actual version of CVD you are running.
  This depends on your operating system, your version of Java, and a
  variety of other factors.
 </para>
 <section id="ugr.cvd.introduction.running">
 <title>Running CVD</title>
 <para>
  You will usually want to start CVD from the command line, or from Eclipse.  To start CVD from the
  command line, you minimally need the uima-core and uima-tools jars.  Below is a sample command
  line for sh and its offspring.
  <programlisting>java -cp ${UIMA_HOME}/lib/uima-core.jar:${UIMA_HOME}/lib/uima-tools.jar 
    org.apache.uima.tools.cvd.CVD</programlisting>
  However, there is no need to type this.  The ${UIMA_HOME}/bin directory contains a cvd.sh and
  cvd.bat file for Windows and *nix operating systems.
 </para>
 <para>
   In Eclipse, you have a ready to use launch configuration available when you have installed the
   UIMA sample project (see <olink targetdoc="&uima_docs_overview;" 
   targetptr="ugr.ovv.eclipse_setup.example_code"/>).  Below is a screenshot of the the Eclipse Run 
   dialog with the CVD
   run configuration selected.
   <screenshot>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata scale="100" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;eclipse-cvd-launch.jpg"/>
     </imageobject>
     <textobject>
      <phrase>Sample error dialog</phrase>
     </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </screenshot>
 </para>
 </section>
 </section>
 <section id="cvd.errorHandling">
  <title>Error Handling</title>
  <para>
   On encountering
   an error, CVD will pop up an error dialog with a short,
   usually incomprehensible message.  Often, the error message will
   claim that there is more information available in the log file, and
   sometimes, this is actually true; so do go and check the log.  You
   can view the log file by selecting the appropriate item in the
   &quot;Tools&quot; menu.

   <screenshot>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata scale="100" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;ErrorExample.jpg"/>
     </imageobject>
     <textobject>
      <phrase>Sample error dialog</phrase>
     </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </screenshot>

  </para>
 </section>

 <section id="cvd.preferencesFile">
  <title>Preferences File</title>
  <para>
   The program will attempt to read on startup and save on exit a file
   called annotViewer.pref in your home directory.  This file contains
   information about choices you made while running the program:
   directories (such as where your data files are) and window sizes. 
   These settings will be used the next time you use the program. There
   is no user control over this process, but the file format is
   reasonably transparent, in case you feel like changing it.  Note,
   however, that the file will be overwritten every time you exit the
   program.
  </para>
 </section>

 <section id="cvd.theMenus">
  <title>The Menus</title>
  <para>
   We give a brief description of the various menus. All menu items come
   with mnemonics (e.g., Alt-F X will exit the program). In addition,
   some menu items have their own keyboard accelerators that you can use
   anywhere in the program. For example, Ctrl-S will save the text
   you've been editing.
  </para>
  <section id="cvd.fileMenu">
   <title>The File Menu</title>
   <para>
    The File menu lets you load, create and save text, load and save
    color settings, and import and export the XCAS format. Here's a
    screenshot.

   <screenshot> 
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
       <imagedata scale="100" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;FileMenu.jpg"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
       <phrase>The File menu</phrase>
      </textobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>
   </para>

   <itemizedlist>
    <para>
     Below is a list of the menu items, together with an explanation.
    </para>

    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>New Text...</title>
      <para>
       Clears the text area. Text you type is written to an anonymous
       buffer. You can use &quot;Save Text As...&quot; to save the text
       you typed to a file. Note: whenever you modify the text, be it
       through typing, loading a file or using the &quot;New
       Text...&quot; menu item, previous analysis results will be lost.
       Since the previous analysis is specific to the text, modifying
       the text invalidates the analysis.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Open Text File</title>
      <para>
       Loads a new text file into the viewer.  The next time you run an
       analysis engine, it will run the text you loaded last.  Depending
       on the annotator you're using, the program may run slow with very
       large text files, so you may want to experiment.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Save Text File</title>
      <para>
       Saves the currently open text file. If no file is currently
       loaded (either because you haven't loaded a file, or you've used
       the &quot;New Text...&quot; menu item), this menu item is
       disabled (and Ctrl-S will do nothing).
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Save Text As...</title>
      <para>
       Save the text to a file of your choosing. This can be an existing
       file, which is then overwritten, or it can be a new file that
       you're creating.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Change Code Page</title>
      <para>
       Allows you to change the code page that is used to load and save
       text files. If you're sure the text you're loading is in ASCII or
       one of the 8-bit extensions such as ISO-8859-1 (ISO Latin1),
       there is probably nothing you need to do. Just load the text and
       look at the display. If you see no funny characters or square
       boxes, chances are your selected code page is compatible with
       your text file.

       Note that the code page setting is also in effect when you save
       files. You can observe the effects with a hex editor or by just
       looking at the file size. For example, if you save the default
       text
       <computeroutput>This is where the text goes.</computeroutput>
       to a file on Windows using the default code page, the size of the
       file will be 28 bytes. If you now change the code page to UTF-16
       and save the file again, the file size will be 58 bytes: two
       bytes for each character, plus two bytes for the byte-order mark.
       Now switch the code page back to the default Windows code page
       and reload the UTF-16 file to see the difference in the editor.

       By default, the code page options include all code pages that any
       Java implementation must support: US-ASCII, ISO-8859-1, UTF-8,
       UTF-16BE (big-endian), UTF-16LE (little endian) and UTF-16 (with
       magic marker). Also included is the system code page, if it is
       not among the built-in ones. Prior to Java 1.4, there is no
       programmatic way to determine what the complete list of supported
       code pages is. Therefore, you can add your own code page in the
       corresponding submenu. All this amounts to is adding a string.
       The new code page is automatically selected as the current code
       page. The way to find out if the code page you entered is
       supported in your Java implementation is to try and load a text
       file. If you see an error ``Unsupported text encoding'', the code
       page is not supported.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Load Color Settings</title>
      <para>
       Load previously saved color settings from a file (see
       Tools/Customize Annotation Display).  It is highly recommended
       that you only load automatically generated files.  Strange things
       may happen if you try to load the wrong file format. On startup,
       the program attempts to load the last color settings file that
       you loaded or saved during a previous session. If you intend to
       use the same color settings as the last time you ran the program,
       there is therefore no need to manually load a color settings
       file.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Save Color Settings</title>
      <para>
       Save your customized color settings (see Tools/Customize
       Annotation Display).  The file is a Java properties file, and as
       such, reasonably transparent.  What is not transparent is the
       encoding of the colors (integer encoding of 24-bit RGB values),
       so changing the file by hand is not really recommended.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Read Type System File</title>
      <para>
       Load a type system file. This allows you to load an XCAS file
       without having to have access to the corresponding annotator.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Write Type System File</title>
      <para>
       Create a type system file from the currently loaded type
       definitions. In addition, you can save the current CAS as a XCAS
       file (see below). This allows you to later load the type system
       and XCAS to view the CAS without having to rerun the annotator.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Read XMI CAS File</title>
      <para>
       Read an XMI CAS file. Important: XMI CAS is a serialization format that
       serializes a CAS without type system and index information. It is
       therefore impossible to read in a stand-alone XMI CAS file. XMI CAS
       files can only be interpreted in the context of an existing type
       system. Consequently, you need to load the TAE that was used to
       create the XCAS file to be able to load it.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Write XMI CAS File</title>
      <para>
       Writes the current analysis out as an XMI CAS file.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>


    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Read XCAS File</title>
      <para>
       Read an XCAS file. Important: XCAS is a serialization format that
       serializes a CAS without type system and index information. It is
       therefore impossible to read in a stand-alone XCAS file. XCAS
       files can only be interpreted in the context of an existing type
       system. Consequently, you need to load the TAE that was used to
       create the XCAS file to be able to load it. Loading a XCAS file
       without loading the TAE may produce strange errors. You may get
       syntax errors on loading the XCAS file, or worse, everything may
       appear to go smoothly but in reality your CAS may be corrupted.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Write XCAS File</title>
      <para>
       Writes the current analysis out as an XCAS file.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Exit</title>
      <para>Exits the program. Your preferences will be saved.</para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>

   </itemizedlist>

  </section>

  <section id="cvd.editMenu">
   <title>The Edit Menu</title>
   <para>

   <screenshot>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>  <!-- was 2.15in -->
       <imagedata scale="100" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;EditMenu.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
       <phrase>The Edit menu</phrase>
      </textobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </screenshot>

    The &quot;Edit&quot; menu provides a standard text editing menu with
    Cut, Copy and Paste, as well as unlimited Undo.
   </para>
   <para>
    Note that standard keyboard accelerators Ctrl-X, Ctrl-C, Ctrl-V and
    Ctrl-Z can be used for Cut, Copy, Paste and Undo, respectively. The
    text area supports other standard keyboard operations such as
    navigation HOME, Ctrl-HOME etc., as well as marking text with Shift-
    &lt;ArrowKey&gt;.
   </para>
  </section>

  <section id="cvd.runMenu">
   <title>The Run Menu</title>
   <para>

    <screenshot>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject> <!-- was width="2.225in" -->
       <imagedata scale="100" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;RunMenu.jpg" />
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
       <phrase>The Run menu</phrase>
      </textobject>
     </mediaobject>
     </screenshot>

     In the Run menu, you can load and run text analysis engines.
   </para>

   <itemizedlist>

    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Load AE</title>
      <para>
       Loads and initializes a text analysis engine. Choosing this menu
       item will display a file open dialog where you should choose an
       XML descriptor of a Text Analysis Engine to process the current
       text.  Even if the analysis engine runs fast, this will take a
       while, since there is a lot of setup work to do when a new TAE is
       created.  So be patient.

       When you develop a new annotator, you will often need to
       recompile your code. Gladis will not reload your annotator code.
       When you recompile your code, you need to terminate the GUI and
       restart it. If you only make changes to the XML descriptor, you
       don't need to restart the GUI. Simply reload the XML file.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Run AE</title>
      <para>
       Before you have (successfully) loaded a TAE, this menu item will
       be disabled. After you have loaded a TAE, it will be enabled, and
       the name changes according to the name of the TAE you have
       loaded. For example, if you've loaded &quot;The World's Fastest
       Parser&quot;, you will have a menu item called &quot;Run The
       World's Fastest Parser&quot;. When you choose the item, the TAE
       is run on whatever text you have currently loaded.

       After a TAE has run successfully, the index window in the upper
       left-hand corner of the screen should be updated and show the
       indexes that were created by this run.  We will have more to say
       about indexes and what to do with them later.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Run AE on CAS</title>
      <para>
       This allows you to run an analysis engine on the current CAS.
       This is useful if you have loaded a CAS from an XCAS file, and
       would like to run further analysis on it.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Performance Report</title>
      <para>
       After you've run your analysis, you can view a performance report.  It will show
       you where the time went: which component used how much of the processing time.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Recently used</title>
      <para>
       Collects a list of recently used analysis engines as a short-cut
       for loading.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <formalpara>
      <title>Language</title>
      <para>
       Some annotators do language specific processing. For example, if
       you run lexical analysis, the results may be quite different
       depending on what the analysis engine thinks the language of the
       document is. With this menu item, you can manually set the
       document language. Alternatively, you can use an automatic
       language identification annotator. If the analysis engines you're
       working with are language agnostic, there is no need to set the
       language.
      </para>
     </formalpara>
    </listitem>

   </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section id="cvd.toolsMenu">
   <title>The tools menu</title>
   <para>
    The tools menu contains some assorted utilities, such as the log
    file viewer. Here you can also set the log level for UIMA.  
    A more detailed description of some of the menu items
    follows below.
   </para>
   <section id="cvd.viewTypeSystem">
    <title>View Type System</title>
    <para>

     <screenshot>
       <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>  
         <imagedata scale="100" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;TypeSystemViewer.jpg" />
        </imageobject>
       </mediaobject>
      </screenshot>

     Brings up a new window that displays the type system. This menu
     item is disabled until the first time you have run an analysis
     engine, since there is no type system to display until then. An
     example is shown above.
    </para>
    <para>
     You can view the inheritance tree on the left by expanding and
     collapsing nodes.  When you select a type, the features defined on
     that type are displayed in the table on the right.  The feature
     table has three columns.  The first gives the name of the feature,
     the second one the type of the feature (i.e., what values it
     takes), and the third column displays the highest type this feature
     is defined on.  In this example, the features &quot;begin&quot; and
     &quot;end&quot; are inherited from the built-in annotation type.
    </para>
    <para>
     In the options menu, you can configure if you want to see inherited
     features or not (not yet implemented).
    </para>
   </section>

   <section id="cvd.showSelectedAnnotations">
    <title>Show Selected Annotations</title>
    <para>
     <figure id="AnnotationViewerFigure">
      <title>
       Annotations produced by a statistical named entity tagger
      </title>
      <mediaobject>
       <imageobject> <!-- was width="5.82in" -->
        <imagedata scale="100" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;AnnotationViewer.jpg" />
       </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
     </figure>
    </para>

    <para>
     To enable this menu, you must have run an analysis engine and
     selected the ``AnnotationIndex'' or one of its subnodes in the
     upper left hand corncer of the screen.  It will bring up a new text
     window with all selected annotations marked up in the text. 
    </para>
    <para>
     <xref linkend="AnnotationViewerFigure" />
     shows the results of applying a statistical named entity tagger to
     a newspaper article.  Some annotation colors have been customized:
     countries are in reverse video, organizations have a turquois
     background, person names are green, and occupations have a maroon
     background.  The default background color is yellow.  This color is
     also used if there is more than one annotation spanning a certain
     text.  Clearly, this display is only useful if you don't have any
     overlapping annotations, or at least not too many.
    </para>
    <para>
     This menu item is also available as a context menu in the Index
     Tree area of the main window. To use it, select the annotation
     index or one of its subnodes, right-click to bring up a popup menu,
     and select the only item in the popup menu. The popup menu is
     actually a better way to invoke the annotation display, since it
     changes according to the selection in the Index Tree area, and will
     tell you if what you've selected can be displayed or not.
    </para>


   </section>

  </section>

 </section>

 <section id="cvd.mainDisplayArea">
  <title>The Main Display Area</title>
  <para>
   The main display area has three sub-areas.  In the upper left-hand
   corner is the
   <emphasis role="bold">index display</emphasis>, which shows the indexes that were defined in the 
   AE, as well as
   the types of the indexes and their subtypes.  In the lower left-hand
   corner, the content of indexes and sub-indexes is displayed 
   (<emphasis role="bold">FS display</emphasis>).  Clicking on any node in the index display will 
   show the
   corresponding feature structures in the FS display.  You can explore
   those structures by expanding the tree nodes.  When you click on a
   node that represents an annotation, clicking on it will cause the
   corresponding text span to marked in the
   <emphasis role="bold">text display</emphasis>.
  </para>
  <para>
   <figure id="Main1Figure">
    <title>State of GUI after running an analysis engine</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata scale="100" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;Main1.jpg" />
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
  </para>
  <para>
   <xref linkend="Main1Figure"></xref>
   shows the state after running the UIMA_Analysis_Example.xml aggregate from the
   uimaj-examples project.  There are two indexes in the index display, and the
   annotation index has been selected.  Note that the number of
   structures in an index is displayed in square brackets after the
   index name.
  </para>
  <para>
   Since displaying thousands of sister nodes is both confusing and
   slow, nodes are grouped in powers of 10.  As soon as there are no
   more than 100 sister nodes, they are displayed next to each other.
  </para>
  <para>
   In our example, a name annotation has been selected, and the
   corresponding token text is highlighted in the text area.  We have
   also expanded the token node to display its structure (not much to see in this simple example).
  </para>
  <para>
   In <xref linkend="Main1Figure"/>, we selected an annotation in the FS display to find the
   corresponding text.  We can also do the reverse and find out what
   annotations cover a certain point in the text.  Let's go back to the
   name recognizer for an example.
  </para>
  <para>
   <figure id="Main2Figure">
    <title>
     Finding annotations for a specific location in the text
    </title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject>  <!-- next width was 6.39in -->
      <imagedata scale="100" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;Main2.jpg" />
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
  </para>
  <para>
   We would like to know if the Michael Baessler has been
   recognized as a name.  So we position the cursor in the corresponding
   text span somewhere, then right-click to bring up the context menu
   telling us which annotations exist at this point. An example is shown
   in
   <xref linkend="Main2Figure" />.
  </para>
  <para>
   <figure id="Main3Figure">
    <title>
     Selecting an annotation from the context menu will highlight that
     annotation in the FS display
    </title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject> <!-- width was 6.39in -->
      <imagedata scale="100" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;Main3.jpg" />
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
  </para>

  <para>
   At this point (<xref linkend="Main2Figure" />), 
   we only know that somewhere around the text cursor position (not
   visible in the picture), we discovered a name.  When we select the corresponding entry in the
   context menu, the name annotation is selected in the FS display, and its covered text is
   highlighted.
   <xref linkend="Main3Figure" /> shows the display after 
   the name node has been selected in
   the popup menu.
  </para>
  <para>
   We're glad to see that, indeed, Michael Baessler is
   considered to be a name.  Note that in the FS display, the
   corresponding annotation node has been selected, and the tree has
   been expanded to make the node visible.
  </para>
  <para>
   NB that the annotations displayed in the popup menu come from the
   annotations currently displayed in the FS display.  If you didn't
   select the annotation index or one of its sub-nodes, no annotations
   can be displayed and the popup menu will be empty.
  </para>

  <section id="cvd.statusBar">
   <title>The Status Bar</title>
   <para>
    At the bottom of the screen, some useful information is displayed in
    the
    <emphasis role="bold">status bar</emphasis>. The left-most area shows the most recent major event, with the
    time when the event terminated in square brackets. The next area
    shows the file name of the currently loaded XML descriptor. This
    area supports a tool tip that will show the full path to the file.
    The right-most area shows the current cursor position, or the extent
    of the selection, if a portion of the text has been selected. The
    numbers correspond to the character offsets that are used for
    annotations.
   </para>
  </section>

  <section id="cvd.keyboardNavigation">
   <title>Keyboard Navigation and Shortcuts</title>
   <para>
    The GUI can be completely navigated and operated through the
    keyboard. All menus and menu items support keyboard mnemonics, and
    some common operations are accessible through keyboard accelerators.
   </para>
   <para>
    You can move the focus between the three main areas using
    <computeroutput>Tab</computeroutput>
    (clockwise) and
    <computeroutput>Shift-Tab</computeroutput>
    (counterclockwise). When the focus is on the text area, the
    <computeroutput>Tab</computeroutput>
    key will insert the corresponding character into the text, so you
    will need to use
    <computeroutput>Ctrl-Tab</computeroutput>
    and
    <computeroutput>Ctrl-Shift-Tab</computeroutput>
    instead. Alternatively, you can use the following key bindings to
    jump directly to one of the areas:
    <computeroutput>Ctrl-T</computeroutput>
    to focus the text area,
    <computeroutput>Ctrl-I</computeroutput>
    for the index repository frame and
    <computeroutput>Ctrl-F</computeroutput>
    for the feature structure area.
   </para>
   <para>
    Some additional keyboard shortcuts are available only in the text
    area, such as
    <computeroutput>Ctrl-X</computeroutput>
    for Cut,
    <computeroutput>Ctrl-C</computeroutput>
    for Copy,
    <computeroutput>Ctrl-V</computeroutput>
    for Paste and
    <computeroutput>Ctrl-Z</computeroutput>
    for Undo. The context menu in the text area can be evoke through the
    <computeroutput>Alt-Enter</computeroutput>
    shortcut. Text can be selected using the arrow keys while holding
    the
    <computeroutput>Shift</computeroutput>
    key.
   </para>
   <para>
    The following table shows the supported keyboard shortcuts.
   </para>
   <table frame="none" id="cvd.table.keyboardShortcuts">
    <title>Keyboard shortcuts</title>
    <tgroup cols="3">
     <thead>
      <row>
       <entry>Shortcut</entry>
       <entry>Action</entry>
       <entry>Scope</entry>
      </row>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <computeroutput>Ctrl-O</computeroutput>
       </entry>
       <entry>Open text file</entry>
       <entry>Global</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <computeroutput>Ctrl-S</computeroutput>
       </entry>
       <entry>Save text file</entry>
       <entry>Global</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <computeroutput>Ctrl-L</computeroutput>
       </entry>
       <entry>Load AE descriptor</entry>
       <entry>Global</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <computeroutput>Ctrl-R</computeroutput>
       </entry>
       <entry>Run current AE</entry>
       <entry>Global</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <computeroutput>Ctrl-I</computeroutput>
       </entry>
       <entry>Switch focus to index repository</entry>
       <entry>Global</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <computeroutput>Ctrl-T</computeroutput>
       </entry>
       <entry>Switch focus to text area</entry>
       <entry>Global</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <computeroutput>Ctrl-F</computeroutput>
       </entry>
       <entry>Switch focus to FS area</entry>
       <entry>Global</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <computeroutput>Ctrl-X</computeroutput>
       </entry>
       <entry>Cut selection</entry>
       <entry>Text</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <computeroutput>Ctrl-C</computeroutput>
       </entry>
       <entry>Copy selection</entry>
       <entry>Text</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <computeroutput>Ctrl-V</computeroutput>
       </entry>
       <entry>Paste selection</entry>
       <entry>Text</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <computeroutput>Ctrl-Z</computeroutput>
       </entry>
       <entry>Undo</entry>
       <entry>Text</entry>
      </row>
      <row>
       <entry>
        <computeroutput>Alt-Enter</computeroutput>
       </entry>
       <entry>Show context menu</entry>
       <entry>Text</entry>
      </row>
     </tbody>
    </tgroup>
   </table>
  </section>

 </section>
</chapter>