<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY imgroot "../images/tools/tools.pear.installer/" >
<!ENTITY % uimaents SYSTEM "../entities.ent" >  
%uimaents;
]>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->
<chapter id="ugr.tools.pear.installer">
  <title>PEAR Installer User&apos;s Guide</title>
  
  <para>PEAR (Processing Engine ARchive) is a new standard for packaging UIMA compliant
    components. This standard defines several service elements that should be included in
    the archive package to enable automated installation of the encapsulated UIMA
    component. The major PEAR service element is an XML Installation Descriptor that
    specifies installation platform, component attributes, custom installation
    procedures and environment variables. </para>
  
  <para>The installation of a UIMA compliant component includes 2 steps: (1) installation of
    the component code and resources in a local file system, and (2) verification of the
    serviceability of the installed component. Installation of the component code and
    resources involves extracting component files from the archive (PEAR) package in a
    designated directory and localizing file references in component descriptors and other
    configuration files. Verification of the component serviceability is accomplished
    with the help of standard UIMA mechanisms for instantiating analysis engines.
    
    
    <screenshot>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata width="5.8in" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;image002.jpg"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject><phrase>PEAR Installer GUI</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot></para>
  
  <para>PEAR Installer is a simple GUI based Java application that helps installing UIMA
    compliant components (analysis engines) from PEAR packages in a local file system. To
    install a desired UIMA component the user needs to select the appropriate PEAR file in a
    local file system and specify the installation directory (optional). If no installation
    directory is specified, the PEAR file is installed to the current working directory. 
	By default the PEAR packages are not installed directly to the specified installation directory. 
	For each PEAR a subdirectory with the name of the PEAR's ID is created where the PEAR package is 
	installed to. If the PEAR installation directory already exists, the old content is automatically 
	deleted before the new content is installed. During the
    component installation the user can read messages printed by the installation program in
    the message area of the application window. If the installation fails, appropriate error
    message is printed to help identifying and fixing the problem.</para>
  
  <para>After the desired UIMA component is successfully installed, the PEAR Installer
    allows testing this component in the CAS Visual Debugger (CVD) application, which is
    provided with the UIMA package. The CVD application will load your UIMA component using
    its XML descriptor file. If the component is loaded successfully, you&apos;ll be able to
    run it either with sample documents provided in the
    <literal>&lt;UIMA_HOME&gt;/examples/data</literal> directory, or with any other
    sample documents. See <olink targetdoc="&uima_docs_tools;"
      targetptr="ugr.tools.cvd"/> for more information about the CVD application.
    Running your component in the CVD application helps to make sure the component will run in
    other UIMA applications. If the CVD application fails to load or run your component, or
    throws an exception, you can find more information about the problem in the uima.log file
    in the current working directory. The log file can be viewed with the CVD.</para>
  
  <para>PEAR Installer creates a file named <literal>setenv.txt</literal> in the
    <literal>&lt;component_root&gt;/metadata</literal> directory. This file contains
    environment variables required to run your component in any UIMA application. 
    It also creates a PEAR descriptor (see also <olink targetdoc="&uima_docs_ref;"
      targetptr="ugr.ref.pear.specifier"/>)
    file named <literal>&lt;componentID&gt;_pear.xml</literal> 
    in the <literal>&lt;component_root&gt;</literal> directory that can be used to directly run
    the installed pear file in your application.
    </para>
  
</chapter>