<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % uimaents SYSTEM "entities.ent" >  
%uimaents;
]>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->
<chapter id="ugr.faqs">
  <title>UIMA Frequently Asked Questions (FAQs)</title>
  
  <qandaset>
    <title></title>
    
    <qandadiv>
      <title>Basic definitions</title>
    
      <qandaentry>
        <question><para>What is UIMA?</para></question>
        <answer><para>
          UIMA stands for Unstructured Information Management
          Architecture. It is component software architecture for the development,
          discovery, composition and deployment of multi-modal analytics for the analysis
          of unstructured information and its integration with search and knowledge
          management technologies.</para>
          <para>
            UIMA processing occurs through a series of modules called analysis
            engines. The result of analysis is an assignment of semantics 
            to the elements of
            unstructured data, for example, the indication that the phrase
            <quote>Washington</quote> refers to a person&apos;s  name or that 
            it refers to a place.           
            </para>
          <para>UIMA supports the rendering of these results in conventional structures,
            for example, relational databases or search engine indices, where the content
            of the original unstructured information may be efficiently accessed
            according to its inferred semantics. </para>
          
          <para>UIMA is specifically designed to support the developer in creating,
            integrating, and deploying components across platforms and among disperse
            teams working to develop unstructured information management
            applications.
      
            </para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>

      <qandaentry>
        <question><para>How do you pronounce UIMA?</para></question>
        <answer><para>You &ndash; eee &ndash; muh</para></answer>
      </qandaentry>

      <qandaentry>
        <question><para>What&apos;s the difference between UIMA and the UIMA SDK?</para>
        </question>
        <answer><para>UIMA is an architecture which specifies component interfaces,
          design patterns, data representations and development roles.</para>
          <para>The UIMA Software Development Kit (SDK) is a software system which includes
            a run-time framework, APIs and tools for implementing, composing, packaging
            and deploying UIMA components. It interfaces with a semantic search engine
            component (available from <ulink
              url="www.alphaworks.ibm.com/tech/uima"/> for indexing and querying over
            the results of analysis. Over time, we hope that additional search engines will
            add support for semantic searching.</para>
          
          <para>The UIMA run-time framework allows developers to plug-in their components
            and applications and run them on different platforms and according to different
            deployment options that range from tightly-coupled (running in the same
            process space) to loosely-coupled (distributed across different processes or
            machines for greater scale, flexibility and recoverability).</para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>

      <qandaentry>
        <question><para>What is an Annotation?</para></question>
        <answer><para>An annotation is metadata that is associated with a region of a
          document. It often is a label, typically represented as string of characters. The
          region may be the whole document. </para>
          
          <para>An example is the label <quote>Person</quote> associated with the span of
            text <quote>George Washington</quote>. We say that <quote>Person</quote>
            annotates <quote>George Washington</quote> in the sentence <quote>George
            Washington was the first president of the United States</quote>. The
            association of the label
            <quote>Person</quote> with a particular span of text is an annotation. Another
            example may have an annotation represent a topic, like <quote>American
            Presidents</quote> and be used to label an entire document.</para>
          
          <para>Annotations are not limited to regions of texts. An annotation may annotate
            a region of an image or a segment of audio. The same concepts apply.</para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
     
    </qandadiv>
     
  </qandaset>
</chapter>
