<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY imgroot "../images/overview_and_setup/eclipse_setup_files/" >
<!ENTITY % uimaents SYSTEM "../entities.ent" >  
%uimaents;
]>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->
<chapter id="ugr.ovv.eclipse_setup">
  <title>Setting up the Eclipse IDE to work with UIMA</title>
  <titleabbrev>Eclipse IDE setup for UIMA</titleabbrev>
  
  <para>This chapter describes how to set up the UIMA SDK to work with Eclipse. Eclipse (<ulink
      url="&url_eclipse;"/>) is a popular open-source Integrated Development
    Environment for many things, including Java. The UIMA SDK does not require that you use
    Eclipse. However, we recommend that you do use Eclipse because some useful UIMA SDK tools
    run as plug-ins to the Eclipse platform and because the UIMA SDK examples are provided in a
    form that's easy to import into your Eclipse environment.</para>
  
  <para>If you are not planning on using the UIMA SDK with Eclipse, you may skip this chapter and
    read <olink targetdoc="&uima_docs_tutorial_guides;" targetptr="ugr.tug.aae"/>
    next.</para>
  
  <para>This chapter provides instructions for
    
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact"><listitem><para>installing Eclipse, </para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem><para>installing the UIMA SDK's Eclipse plugins into your Eclipse
        environment, and </para></listitem>
      
      <listitem><para>importing the example UIMA code into an Eclipse project. </para>
        </listitem></itemizedlist></para>
  
  <para>The UIMA Eclipse plugins are designed to be used with Eclipse version 3.1 or
    later.
  </para>
  
  <note><para>You will need to run Eclipse using a Java at the 1.5 or later level, in order
  to use the UIMA Eclipse plugins.</para></note>
  
  <section id="ugr.ovv.eclipse_setup.installation">
    <title>Installation</title>
    <section id="ugr.ovv.eclipse_setup.install_eclipse">
      <title>Install Eclipse</title>
      
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact"><listitem><para>Go to <ulink
          url="&url_eclipse;"/> and follow the instructions there to download Eclipse.
        </para></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>We recommend using the latest release level (not an
          <quote>Integration level</quote>). Navigate to the Eclipse Release version you
          want and download the archive for your platform.</para></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>Unzip the archive to install Eclipse somewhere, e.g., c:\</para>
          </listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>Eclipse has a bit of a learning curve. If you plan to make
          significant use of Eclipse, check out the tutorial under the help menu. It is well
          worth the effort. There are also books you can get that describe Eclipse and its
        use.</para></listitem></itemizedlist>
      
      <para>The first time Eclipse starts up it will take a bit longer as it completes its
        installation. A <quote>welcome</quote> page will come up. After you are through
        reading the welcome information, click on the arrow to exit the welcome page and get to
        the main Eclipse screens.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="ugr.ovv.eclipse_setup.install_uima_eclipse_plugins">
      <title>Installing the UIMA Eclipse Plugins</title>
      
      <para>The best way to do this is to use the Eclipse Update mechanism, because that will 
        insure that all needed prerequisites are also installed.  See below for an alternative,
        manual approach.</para>
      
        <note><para>If your computer is on an internet connection which uses a proxy server, you can
        configure Eclipse to know about that. Put your proxy settings into Eclipse using the
        Eclipse preferences by accessing the menus: Window &rarr; Preferences... &rarr;
        Install/Update, and Enable HTTP proxy connection under the Proxy Settings with the
        information about your proxy. </para></note>

      
      <para>To use the Eclipse Update mechanism, start Eclipse, and then pick the menu 
        <command>Help &rarr; Software Updates &rarr; Find and Install...</command>.
      On the next page, select the option to Search for new features to install, and press the
        <command>Next</command> button.  On the next panel, update sites to visit, press the "Add a new
        remote site" button and enter the URL 
        http://www.apache.org/dist/incubator/uima/eclipse-update-site, and press OK.  On the previous
        page will now appear this new Site, and it should be checked.</para>
      
      <para>Also check the Europa (or Callisto) 
        Discovery Site, which is where the EMF core plugins are (EMF stands for Eclipse Modeling Framework; 
        it is an add-on to Eclipse, and is used
        by some of the UIMA Eclipse tooling).</para>
      <para>Now click finish, and follow the 
        remaining panels to install the UIMA plugins.  If
        you do not have a compatible level of EMF installed, when you select the UIMA plugins, you will get a
        message saying it needs EMF.  To add EMF to the list of plugins to be downloaded, just expand the
        Discovery Site entry by clicking it's little "plus" sign and then push the "Select Required" button on the right
        of the panel.  This will select the part of EMF that is needed.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="ugr.ovv.eclipse_setup.install_emf">
      <title>Manual Install additional Eclipse component: EMF</title>
      <para>You can skip this section if you installed EMF using the above process.</para>
      
      <warning><para>EMF comes in many versions; <emphasis role="bold">you must install
      the version that corresponds to the level of Eclipse that you are running.</emphasis>
      This is automatically done for you if you install it using the Eclipse update mechanism,
      described below. If you separately download an EMF package, you will need to verify it is
      the version that corresponds to the level of Eclipse you are running, before installing
      it.</para></warning>
      
      <para>Before installing EMF using these instructions, please go to <ulink
          url="&url_emf;"/> and read the installation instructions, and then click on the
        "Update Manager" link to see what url to use in the next step, where you use the built-in
        facilities in Eclipse to find and install new features. </para>
      
      <para> The exact way to install EMF changes from time to time. In the next few paragraphs,
        we try to give instructions that should work for most versions. Please see the end of
        this section for shortcut instructions for the current version of Eclipse at the time
        of this writing, Eclipse 3.3. </para>
      
      <para>Activate the software feature finding by using the menu: Help &rarr; Software
        Updates &rarr; Find and Install. Select <quote>Search for new features to
        install</quote>, push <quote>Next</quote>. Specify the update sites to use to
        search for EMF, making sure the <quote>Ignore features not applicable to this
        environment</quote> box is checked (at the bottom of the dialog), and push
        <quote>Finish</quote>. A good site to use is one of the Discovery Sites (e.g. Callisto or Europa) - which has a
        collection of Eclipse components including EMF. </para>
            
      <para>This will launch a search for updates to Eclipse; it may show a list of update site
        mirrors &ndash; click OK. When it finishes, it shows a list of possible updates in an
        expandable tree. Expand the tree nodes to find EMF SDK. The specific level may vary
        from the level shown below as newer versions are released.</para>
      
      <informalfigure>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata width="4in" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;image002.jpg"/>
          </imageobject>
          <textobject><phrase>Screenshot showing search results for EMF</phrase>
          </textobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </informalfigure>
      
      <para>Click <quote>Next</quote>. Then pick Eclipse Modeling Framework (EMF), and
        push <quote>Next</quote>, accept any licensing agreements, etc., until it
        finishes the installation. It may say it's an <quote>unsigned feature</quote>;
        proceed by clicking <quote>Install</quote>. If it recommends restarting, you may
        do that.</para>
      
      <para>This will install EMF, without any extras. (If you want the whole EMF system,
        including source and documentation, you can pick the <quote>EMF SDK</quote> and the
        <quote>Examples for Eclipse Modeling Framework</quote>.)</para>
      
      <section id="ugr.ovv.eclipse_setup.install_emf_shortcut">
        <title>EMF Installation Shortcut for Eclipse 3.2</title>
        <para>Since Eclipse 3.2, all major Eclipse sub-projects coordinate their
          release timeframes and publish the consolidated releases. The code name
          for 3.2 was Callisto, the one for 3.3 is Europa.  You can
          easily install EMF via the release discovery site as follows.
          <orderedlist>
            <listitem><para> From the Eclipse menu, select Help/Software Updates/Find
              and Install.../Search for new features to install. </para></listitem>
            <listitem><para> Check the "[release name] discovery site", push "Next". </para>
              </listitem>
            <listitem><para> Select a convenient mirror site. </para></listitem>
            <listitem><para> Check the EMF box under "Models and model development"
              </para></listitem>
            <listitem><para> Follow the instructions for the rest of the install. </para>
              </listitem>
          </orderedlist> </para>
      </section>
      
    </section>
    
    <section id="ugr.ovv.eclipse_setup.install_uima_sdk">
      <title>Install the UIMA SDK</title>
      <para>If you haven't already done so, please download and install the UIMA SDK from
          <ulink url="&url_apache_uima_download;"/>.  Be sure to set the environmental variable
          UIMA_HOME pointing to the root of the installed UIMA SDK and run the
          <literal>adjustExamplePaths.bat</literal> or <literal>adjustExamplePaths.sh</literal>
          script, as explained in the README.</para>

      <para>The environmental parameter UIMA_HOME is used by the command-line scripts in the
          %UIMA_HOME%/bin directory as well as by eclipse run configurations in the uimaj-examples
          sample project.</para>

    </section>
    
    <section id="ugr.ovv.eclipse_setup.install_uima_eclipse_plugins_manually">
      <title>Installing the UIMA Eclipse Plugins, manually</title>
      
      <para>If you installed the UIMA plugins using the update mechanism above, please skip this section.</para>
      
      <para>If you are unable to use the Eclipse Update mechanism to install the UIMA plugins, you 
        can do this manually.  In the directory %UIMA_HOME%/eclipsePlugins (The environment variable
        %UIMA_HOME% is where you installed the UIMA SDK), you will see a set of folders. Copy these
        to your %ECLIPSE_HOME%/eclipse/plugins directory (%ECLIPSE_HOME% is where you
        installed Eclipse).</para>
      
    </section>
    
    <section id="ugr.ovv.eclipse_setup.start_eclipse">
      <title>Start Eclipse</title>
      <para>If you have Eclipse running, restart it (shut it down, and start it again) using
        the
        <code>-clean</code> option; you can do this by running the command
        <command>eclipse -clean</command> (see explanation in the next section) in the
        directory where you installed Eclipse. You may want to set up a desktop shortcut at
        this point for Eclipse.</para>
      
      <section id="ugr.ovv.eclipse_setup.special_startup_parameter_clean">
        <title>Special startup parameter for Eclipse: -clean</title>
        <para>If you have modified the plugin structure (by copying or files directly in the
          file system) in Eclipse 3.x after you started it for the first time, please include
          the <quote>-clean</quote> parameter in the startup arguments to Eclipse,
          <emphasis>one time</emphasis> (after any plugin modifications were done). This
          is needed because Eclipse may not notice the changes you made, otherwise. This
          parameter forces Eclipse to reexamine all of its plugins at startup and recompute
          any cached information about them.</para>
      </section>
      
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="ugr.ovv.eclipse_setup.example_code">
    <title>Setting up Eclipse to view Example Code</title>
    <para>Later chapters refer to example code. You can create a special project in Eclipse to
      hold the examples. Here's how:</para>
    
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact"><listitem><para>In Eclipse, if the Java
      perspective is not already open, switch to it by going to Window &rarr; Open Perspective
      &rarr; Java.</para></listitem>
      
      <listitem><para>Set up a class path variable named UIMA_HOME, whose value is the
        directory where you installed the UIMA SDK. This is done as follows:
        
        <itemizedlist><listitem><para>Go to Window &rarr; Preferences &rarr; Java
          &rarr; Build Path &rarr; Classpath Variables.</para></listitem>
          
          <listitem><para>Click <quote>New</quote></para></listitem>
          
          <listitem><para>Enter UIMA_HOME (all capitals, exactly as written) in the
            <quote>Name</quote> field.</para></listitem>
          
          <listitem><para>Enter your installation directory (e.g. <literal>C:/Program
            Files/apache-uima</literal>) in the <quote>Path</quote> field</para>
            </listitem>
          
          <listitem><para>Click <quote>OK</quote> in the <quote>New Variable
            Entry</quote> dialog</para></listitem>
          
          <listitem><para>Click <quote>OK</quote> in the <quote>Preferences</quote>
            dialog</para></listitem>
          
          <listitem><para>If it asks you if you want to do a full build, click
            <quote>Yes</quote> </para></listitem></itemizedlist></para>
        </listitem>
      
      <listitem><para>Select the File &rarr; Import menu option</para></listitem>
      
      <listitem><para>Select <quote>General/Existing Project into Workspace</quote> and click
        the <quote>Next</quote> button.</para></listitem>
      
      <listitem><para>Click <quote>Browse</quote> and browse to the
        %UIMA_HOME%/ directory</para></listitem>
      
      <listitem><para>Click <quote>Finish.</quote> This will create a new project called
        <quote>uimaj-examples</quote> in your Eclipse workspace. There should be no
        compilation errors. </para></listitem></itemizedlist>
    
    <para>To verify that you have set up the project correctly, check that there are no error
      messages in the <quote>Problems</quote> view.</para>
    
  </section>
   
  <section id="ugr.ovv.eclipse_setup.adding_source">
    <title>Adding the UIMA source code to the jar files</title>
    
    <para>If you would like to be able to jump to the UIMA source code in Eclipse or to step
    through it with the debugger, you can add the UIMA source code to the jar files.  This is
    done via a shell script that comes with the source distribution.  To add the source code
    to the jars, you need to:
    </para>
    
    <itemizedlist>
    
    <listitem>
    <para>
    Download and unpack the UIMA source distribution.
    </para>
    </listitem>
    
    <listitem>
    <para>
    Download and install the UIMA binary distribution (the UIMA_HOME environment variable needs
    to be set to point to where you installed the UIMA binary distribution).    
    </para>
    </listitem>
    
    <listitem>
    <para>
    Execute the <command>addSourceToJars</command> script in the root directory of the 
    source distribution.
    </para>
    </listitem>
    
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <para>
    This adds the source code to the jar files, and it will then be automatically available
    from Eclipse.  There is no further Eclipse setup required.
    </para>
  
  </section>
  
  
  <section id="ugr.ovv.eclipse_setup.linking_uima_javadocs">
     <title>Attaching UIMA Javadocs</title>
     
     <para>The binary distribution also includes the UIMA Javadocs.  They are
       attached to the UIMA library Jar files in the uima-examples project described
       above.  You can attach the Javadocs to your own project as well.  
     </para>
    
     <note><para>If you attached the source as described in the previous section, you 
     don't need to attach the Javadocs because the source includes the Javadoc comments.</para></note>
     
     <para>Attaching the Javadocs enables Javadoc help for UIMA APIs.  After they are 
       attached, if you hover your mouse
     over a certain UIMA api element, the corresponding Javadoc will appear.  
       You can then press <quote>F2</quote> to make the hover "stick", or 
       <quote>Shift-F2</quote> to open the default 
       web-browser on your system to let you browse the entire Javadoc information 
       for that element.
     </para>
     <para>If this pop-up behavior is something you don't want, you can turn it off
     in the Eclipse preferences, in the menu Window &rarr; Preferences &rarr;
       Java &rarr; Editors &rarr; hovers.
     </para>
    
     <para>Eclipse also has a Javadoc "view" which you can show, using the Window &rarr;
     Show View &rarr; Javadoc.</para>
   
     <para>See <olink targetdoc="&uima_docs_ref;" targetptr="ugr.ref.javadocs.libraries"/>
     for information on how to set up a UIMA "library" with the Javadocs attached, which
     can be reused for other projects in your Eclipse workspace.</para>
                
     <para>You can attach the Javadocs to each UIMA library jar you think you might be 
       interested in.  It makes most sense
       for the uima-core.jar, you'll probably use the core APIs most of all.
     </para>
     
     <para>Here's a screenshot of what you should see when you hover your mouse pointer over the
     class name <quote>CAS</quote> in the source code.
     </para>

       <informalfigure>
         <mediaobject>
           <imageobject>
             <imagedata width="5.7in" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;image004.jpg"/>
           </imageobject>
           <textobject><phrase>Screenshot of mouse-over for UIMA APIs</phrase>
           </textobject>
         </mediaobject>
       </informalfigure>
       
   </section>
   
  <section id="ugr.ovv.eclipse_setup.running_external_tools_from_eclipse">
    <title>Running external tools from Eclipse</title>
    
    <para>You can run many tools without using Eclipse at all, by using the shell scripts in the
      UIMA SDK's bin directory. In addition, many tools can be run from inside Eclipse;
      examples are the Document Analyzer, CPE Configurator, CAS Visual Debugger, 
      and JCasGen. The uimaj-examples project provides Eclipse launch
      configurations that make this easy to do.</para>
    
    <para>To run these tools from Eclipse:</para>
    
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact"><listitem><para>If the Java perspective is not
      already open, switch to it by going to Window &rarr; Open Perspective &rarr;
      Java.</para></listitem>
      
      <listitem><para>Go to Run &rarr; Run... </para></listitem>
      
      <listitem><para>In the window that appears, select <quote>UIMA CPE GUI</quote>,
        <quote>UIMA CAS Visual Debugger</quote>, <quote>UIMA JCasGen</quote>, or 
        <quote>UIMA Document Analyzer</quote>
        from the list of run configurations on the left. (If you don't see, these, please
        select the uimaj-examples project and do a Menu &rarr; File
        &rarr; Refresh).</para></listitem>
      
      <listitem><para>Press the <quote>Run</quote> button. The tools should start. Close
        the tools by clicking the <quote>X</quote> in the upper right corner on the GUI.
        </para></listitem></itemizedlist>
    
    <para>For instructions on using the Document Analyzer and CPE Configurator, see <olink
        targetdoc="&uima_docs_tools;" targetptr="ugr.tools.doc_analyzer"/>, and
        <olink targetdoc="&uima_docs_tools;" targetptr="ugr.tools.cpe"/> For
      instructions on using the CAS Visual Debugger and JCasGen, see <olink
        targetdoc="&uima_docs_tools;" targetptr="ugr.tools.cvd"/> and
        <olink targetdoc="&uima_docs_tools;" targetptr="ugr.tools.jcasgen"/></para>
    
  </section>
  
</chapter>
