<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY % uimaents SYSTEM "../entities.ent" >  
%uimaents;
]>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->
<chapter id="ugr.tug.aas">
  <title>Annotations, Artifacts, and Sofas</title>
  <titleabbrev>Annotations, Artifacts &amp; Sofas</titleabbrev>
  
  <para>Up to this point, the documentation has focused on analyzing strings of Unicode text,
    producing subtypes of Annotations which reference offsets in those strings. This
    chapter generalizes this concept and shows how other kinds of artifacts can be handled,
    including non-text things like audio and images, and how you can define your own kinds of
    <quote>annotations</quote> for these.</para>
  
  <section id="ugr.tug.aas.terminology">
    <title>Terminology</title>
    
    <section id="ugr.tug.aas.artifact">
      <title>Artifact</title>
      
      <para>The Artifact is the unstructured thing being analyzed by an annotator. It could
        be an HTML web page, an image, a video stream, a recorded audio conversation, an MPEG-4
        stream, etc. Artifacts are often restructured in the course of processing to
        facilitate particular kinds of analysis. For instance, an HTML page may be converted
        into a <quote>de-tagged</quote> version. Annotators at different places in the
        pipeline may be analyzing different versions of the artifact.</para>
      
    </section>
    
    <section id="ugr.tug.aas.sofa">
      <title>Subject of Analysis &mdash; Sofa</title>
      
      <para>Each representation of an Artifact is called a Subject of Analysis, abbreviated
        using the acronym <quote>Sofa</quote> which stands for <emphasis
          role="underline">S</emphasis>ubject <emphasis role="underline">
        OF</emphasis> <emphasis role="underline">A</emphasis>nalysis. Annotation
        metadata, which have explicit designations of sub-regions of the artifact to which
        they apply, are always associated with a particular Sofa. For instance, an
        annotation over text specifies two features, the begin and end, which represent the
        character offsets into the text string Sofa being analyzed.</para>
      
      <para>Other examples of representations of Artifacts, which could be Sofas include:
        An HTML web page, a detagged web page, the translated text of that document, an audio or
        video stream, closed-caption text from a video stream, etc.</para>
      
      <para>Often, there is one Sofa being analyzed in a CAS. The next chapter will show how
        UIMA facilitates working with multiple representations of an artifact at the same
        time, in the same CAS.</para>
      
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section id="ugr.tug.aas.sofa_data_formats">
    <title>Formats of Sofa Data</title>
    
    <para>Sofa data can be Java Unicode Strings, Feature Structure arrays of primitive
      types, or a URI which references remote data available via a network
      connection.</para>
    
    <para>The arrays of primitive types can be things like byte arrays or float arrays, and are
      intended to be used for artifacts like audio data, image data, etc.</para>
    
    <para>The URI form holds a URI specification String.</para>
    
  </section>
  
  <section id="ugr.tug.aas.setting_accessing_sofa_data">
    <title>Setting and Accessing Sofa Data</title>
    
    <section id="ugr.tug.aas.setting_sofa_data">
      <title>Setting Sofa Data</title>
      
      <para>When a CAS is created, you can set its Sofa Data, just one time; this property
        insures that metadata describing regions of the Sofa remain valid. As a consequence,
        the following methods that set data for a given Sofa can only be called once for a given
        Sofa.</para>
      
      <para>The following methods on the CAS set the Sofa Data to one of the 3 formats. Assume
        that the variable <quote>aCas</quote> holds a reference to a CAS:</para>
      
      
      <programlisting><?db-font-size 80% ?>aCas.<emphasis role="bold">setSofaDataString</emphasis>(document_text_string, mime_type_string);
aCas.<emphasis role="bold">setSofaDataArray</emphasis>(feature_structure_primitive_array, mime_type_string);
aCas.<emphasis role="bold">setSofaDataURI</emphasis>(uri_string, mime_type_string);</programlisting>
      
      <para>In addition, the method
        <literal>aCas.setDocumentText(document_text_string)</literal> may still be
        used, and is equivalent to <literal>setSofaDataString(string,
        "text")</literal>. The mime type is currently not used by the UIMA framework, but may
        be set and retrieved by user code.</para>
      
      <para>Feature Structure primitive arrays are all the UIMA Array types except arrays of
        Feature Structures, Strings, and Booleans. Typically, these are arrays of bytes,
        but can be other types, such as floats, longs, etc.</para>
      
      <para>The URI string should conform to the standard URI format.</para>
      
    </section>
    
    <section id="ugr.tug.aas.accessing_sofa_data">
      <title>Accessing Sofa Data</title>
      
      <para>The analysis algorithms typically work with the Sofa data. The following
        methods on the CAS access the Sofa Data:</para>
      
      
      <programlisting>String           aCas.getDocumentText();
String           aCas.getSofaDataString();
FeatureStructure aCas.getSofaDataArray();
String           aCas.getSofaDataURI();
String           aCas.getSofaMimeType();</programlisting>
      
      <para>The <literal>getDocumentText</literal> and
        <literal>getSofaDataString</literal> return the same text string. The
        <literal>getSofaDataURI</literal> returns the URI itself, not the data the URI is
        pointing to. You can use standard Java I/O capabilities to get the data associated
        with the URI, or use the UIMA Framework Streaming method described next.</para>
      
    </section>
    
    <section id="ugr.tug.aas.accessing_sofa_data_using_java_stream">
      <title>Accessing Sofa Data using a Java Stream</title>
      
      <para>The framework provides a consistent method for accessing the Sofa data,
        independent of it being stored locally, or accessed remotely using the URI. Get a Java
        InputStream instance from the Sofa data using:</para>
      
      
      <programlisting>InputStream inputStream = aCas.getSofaDataStream();</programlisting>
      
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact"><listitem><para>If the data is local, this method
        returns a ByteArrayInputStream. This stream provides bytes.
        
        <itemizedlist><listitem><para>If the Sofa data was set using setDocumentText or
          setSofaDataString, the String is converted to bytes by using the UTF-8
          encoding.</para></listitem>
          
          <listitem><para>If the Sofa data was set as a DataArray, the bytes in the data array
            are serialized, high-byte first. </para></listitem></itemizedlist>
        </para></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>If the Sofa data was specified as a URI, this method returns the
          handle from url.openStream(). Java offers built-in support for several URI
          schemes including <quote>FILE:</quote>, <quote>HTTP:</quote>,
          <quote>FTP:</quote> and has an extensible mechanism,
          <literal>URLStreamHandlerFactory</literal>, for customizing access to an
          arbitrary URI. See more details at <ulink
            url="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/docs/api/java/net/URLStreamHandlerFactory.html"/>
          . </para></listitem></itemizedlist>
      
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section id="ugr.tug.aas.sofa_fs">
    <title>The Sofa Feature Structure</title>
    
    <para>Information about a Sofa is contained in a special built-in Feature Structure of
      type <literal>uima.cas.Sofa</literal>. This feature structure is created and
      managed by the UIMA Framework; users must not create it directly. Although these Sofa
      type instances are implemented as standard feature structures, <emphasis>generic
      CAS APIs can not be used to create Sofas or set their features</emphasis>. Instead,
      Sofas are created implicitly by the creation of new CAS views. Similarly, Sofa features
      are set by CAS methods such as <literal>cas.setDocumentText()</literal>.</para>
    
    <para>Features of the Sofa type include</para>
    
    <itemizedlist><listitem><para>SofaID: Every Sofa in a CAS has a unique SofaID. SofaIDs
      are the primary handle for access. This ID is often the same as the name string given to the
      Sofa by the developer, but it can be mapped to a different name (see <olink
        targetdoc="&uima_docs_tutorial_guides;"
        targetptr="ugr.tug.mvs.sofa_name_mapping"/>.</para></listitem>
      
      <listitem><para>Mime type: This string feature can be used to describe the type of the
        data represented by a Sofa. It is not used by the framework; the framework provides
        APIs to set and get its value.</para></listitem>
      
      <listitem><para>Sofa Data: The Sofa data itself. This data can be resident in the CAS or
        it can be a reference to data outside the CAS. </para></listitem></itemizedlist>
    
  </section>
  
  <section id="ugr.tug.aas.annotations">
    <title>Annotations</title>
    
    <para>Annotators add meta data about a Sofa to the CAS. It is often useful to have this
      metadata denote a region of the Sofa to which it applies. For instance, assuming the Sofa
      is a String, the metadata might describe a particular substring as the name of a person.
      The built-in UIMA type, uima.tcas.Annotation, has two extra features that enable this
      - the begin and end features - which denote a character position offset into the text
      string being analyzed.</para>
    
    <para>The concept of <quote>annotations</quote> can be generalized for non-string
      kinds of Sofas. For instance, an audio stream might have an audio annotation which
      describes sounds regions in terms of floating point time offsets in the Sofa. An image
      annotation might use two pairs of x,y coordinates to define the region the annotation
      applies to.</para>
    
    <section id="ugr.tug.aas.built_in_annotation_types">
      <title>Built-in Annotation types</title>
      
      <para>The built-in CAS type, <literal>uima.tcas.Annotation</literal>, is just one
        kind of definition of an Annotation. It was designed for annotating text strings, and
        has begin and end features which describe which substring of the Sofa being
        annotated.</para>
      
      <para>For applications which have other kinds of Sofas, the UIMA developer will design
        their own kinds of Annotation types, as needed to describe an annotation, by
        declaring new types which are subtypes of
        <literal>uima.cas.AnnotationBase</literal>. For instance, for images, you
        might have the concept of a rectangular region to which the annotation applies. In
        this case, you might describe the region with 2 pairs of x, y coordinates.</para>
      
    </section>
    
    <section id="ugr.tug.aas.annotations_associated_sofa">
      <title>Annotations have an associated Sofa</title>
      
      <para>Annotations are always associated with a particular Sofa. In subsequent
        chapters, you will learn how there can be multiple Sofas associated with an artifact;
        which Sofa an annotation refers to is described by the Annotation feature structure
        itself.</para>
      
      <para>All annotation types extend from the built-in type uima.cas.AnnotationBase.
        This type has one feature, a reference to the Sofa associated with the annotation.
        This value is currently used by the Framework to support the getCoveredText() method
        on the annotation instance - this returns the portion of a text Sofa that the
        annotation spans. It also is used to insure that the Annotation is indexed only in the
        CAS View associated with this Sofa.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section id="ugr.tug.aas.annotationbase">
    <title>AnnotationBase</title>
    
    <para>A built-in type, <literal>uima.cas.AnnotationBase</literal>, is provided by
      UIMA to allow users to extend the Annotation capabilities to different kinds of
      Annotations. The <literal>AnnotationBase</literal> type has one feature, named
      <literal>sofa</literal>, which holds a reference to the
      <literal>Sofa</literal> feature structure with which this annotation is associated. 
      The <literal>sofa</literal> feature is automatically set when creating an annotation 
      (meaning &mdash; any type derived from the built-in 
      <literal>uima.cas.AnnotationBase</literal> type); it should not be set by the user.</para>
    
    <para>There is one method, <literal>getView</literal>(), provided by
      <literal>AnnotationBase</literal> that returns the CAS View for the Sofa the
      annotation is pointing at. Note that this method always returns a CAS, even when applied
      to JCas annotation instances.</para>
    
    <para>The built-in type <literal>uima.tcas.Annotation</literal> extends
      <literal>uima.cas.AnnotationBase</literal> and adds two features, a begin and an
      end feature, which are suitable for identifying a span in a text string that the
      annotation applies to. Users may define other extensions to
      <literal>AnnotationBase</literal> with alternative specifications that can
      denote a particular region within the subject of analysis, as appropriate to their
      application.</para>
    
  </section>
</chapter>