<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
 to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

  http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->
<document>

<properties>
<title>Home</title>
<author email="uima-dev@incubator.apache.org">
 UIMA Documentation Team</author>
</properties>

<body>

<section name="Welcome to Apache UIMA">

<p>
Welcome to Apache UIMA, a project of the 
<a href="http://incubator.apache.org/">Apache incubator</a>.  Our goal is a 
thriving community of users and developers of UIMA frameworks, supporting
  components for analysing unstructured content such as text, 
  audio and video.
</p>

<p>Unstructured Information Management applications are software systems
that analyze large volumes of unstructured information in order to
discover knowledge that is relevant to an end user. UIMA is a
framework and SDK for developing such applications. An example UIM
application might ingest plain text and identify entities, such as
persons, places, organizations; or relations, such as works-for or
located-at. UIMA enables such an application to be decomposed into
components, for example "language identification" -&gt; "language
specific segmentation" -&gt; "sentence boundary detection" -&gt; "entity
detection (person/place names etc.)". Each component must implement
interfaces defined by the framework and must provide self-describing
metadata via XML descriptor files. The framework manages these
components and the data flow between them. Components are written in
Java or C++; the data that flows between components is designed for
efficient mapping between these languages. UIMA additionally provides
capabilities to wrap components as network services, and can scale to
very large volumes by replicating processing pipelines over a cluster
of networked nodes. 
</p>

<p>UIMA is an Apache-licensed open source implementation of the UIMA specification (that specification is, in turn, being
  developed concurrently by a technical committee 
within <a href="http://www.oasis-open.org">OASIS</a>, a standards organization). 
  We invite and encourage you to participate in both the implementation and specification efforts.
  </p>
  <p>UIMA is a component framework for analysing unstructured content such as text, 
  audio and video.  
  It comprises an SDK and tooling for composing and running 
  analytic components written in Java and C++, with some support for Perl, Python and TCL.
</p>
<!--
<p>
The Apache UIMA project is focused on building the UIMA api 
and a robust, high performance, scalable implementation.
</p>
  -->
</section>

<section name="Incubator Notice and Disclaimer">
    <p>
        <i>Note</i> : Apache UIMA is an effort undergoing incubation at the
        Apache Software Foundation (ASF). Incubation is required of all newly
        accepted projects until a further review indicates that the infrastructure,
        communications, and decision making process have stabilized in
        a manner consistent with other successful ASF projects. While
        incubation status is not necessarily a reflection of the completeness
        or stability of the code, it does indicate that the project has yet to be
        fully endorsed by the ASF.
    </p>

</section>  
<!--  
<section name="UIMA News">

<p>
<strong>UIMA has been accepted into the Apache Incubator.</strong>
</p>

</section>
  
<section name="UIMA Community">
<p>
<strong>Users!</strong>
<blockquote>
We'd love to have you involved. Check out the <a href="http://wiki.apache.org/incubator/uima wiki">Wiki</a>.
</blockquote>
</p>

</section>
-->
</body>
</document>





