<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY imgroot "images/tools/tools.eclipse_launcher/" >
<!ENTITY % uimaents SYSTEM "../../target/docbook-shared/entities.ent" >  
%uimaents;
]>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->

<chapter id="ugr.tools.eclipse_launcher">

	<title>Eclipse Analysis Engine Launcher&apos;s Guide</title>
	<titleabbrev>Eclipse Analysis Engine Launcher&apos;s Guide</titleabbrev>
	
	<para>
	The Analysis Engine Launcher is an Eclipse plug-in that provides debug and run support 
	for Analysis Engines directly within eclipse, like a Java program can be debugged.
	It supports most of the descriptor formats except CPE, UIMA AS and
	some remote deployment descriptors.
	</para>
	
	<screenshot>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata width="5in" format="PNG"
					fileref="&imgroot;image01.png" />
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
	</screenshot>
		
	<section id="ugr.tools.eclipse_launcher.create_configuration">
	    <title>Creating an Analysis Engine launch configuration</title>
	    <para>
	    To debug or run an Analysis Engine a launch configuration must be created. To do this
	    select "Run -> Run Configurations" or "Run -> Run Configurations" from the menu bar. A dialog
	    will open where the launch configuration can be created. Select UIMA Analysis Engine and create
	    a new configuration via pressing the New button at the top, or via the New button in the context menu.
	    The newly created configuration will be automatically selected and the Main tab will be displayed.
	    </para>
	    
	    <para>
	    The Main tab defines the Analysis Engine which will be launched. First select the project which
	    contains the descriptor, then choose a descriptor and select the input. The input can either be
	    a folder which contains input files or just a single input file, if the recursively check box
	    is marked the input folder will be scanned recursively for input files.  
	    </para>
	    
	    <para>
	    The input format defines the format of the input files, if it is set to CASes the input resource
	    must be either in the XMI or XCAS format and if it is set to plain text, plain text input files in
	    the specified encoding are expected. The input logic filters out all files which do not have an appropriate
	    file ending, depending on the chosen format the file ending must be one of .xcas, .xmi or .txt, all
	    other files are ignored when the input is a folder, if a single file is selected it will be processed
	    independent of the file ending.
	    </para>
	    
	    <para>
	    The output directory is optional, if set all processed input files will be written to the specified
	    directory in the XMI CAS format, if the clear check box is marked all files inside the output folder will be deleted, usually
	    this option is not needed because existing files will be overwritten without notice.
	    </para>
	    
	    <para>
	    The other tabs in the launch configuration are documented in the eclipse documentation,
	    see the "Java development user guide -> Tasks -> Running and Debugging". 
	    </para>
    </section>
 	
 	<section id="ugr.tools.eclipse_launcher.launching">
	    <title>Launching an Analysis Engine</title>
	    <para>
		To launch an Analysis Engine go to the previously created launch configuration and
		click on "Debug" or "Run" depending on the desired run mode. The Analysis Engine will
		now be launched. The output will be shown in the Console View. To debug an Analysis Engine
		place breakpoints inside the implementation class. If a breakpoint is hit the execution will pause 
		like in a Java program. 
	    </para>
 	</section>
 </chapter>