<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
   Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
   or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
   distributed with this work for additional information
   regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
   to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
   "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
   with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
   software distributed under the License is distributed on an
   "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
   KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
   specific language governing permissions and limitations
   under the License.    
-->
<feature
      id="org.apache.uima.tools"
      label="UIMA tools (includes Runtime)"
      version="${parsedVersion.osgiVersion}"
      provider-name="Apache Software Foundation">

   <description url="http://uima.apache.org">
      This feature contains a debug structure handler plugin, the Component
Descriptor Editor (a forms-based editor for creating and editing
the XML descriptors used by UIMA), the JCas generation capability,
a CAS Editor, the Launcher, and the PEAR packaging capability.
   </description>

   <copyright url="http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0">
      Copyright the Apache Software Foundation and others; see License
and NOTICE files
   </copyright>

   <license>ASF 2.0 and BSD Software Licenses
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the &quot;License&quot;); you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0 Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under the License is distributed on an &quot;AS IS&quot; BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and limitations under the License.

BSD License (for SVG Icons project (http://freecode.com/projects/svg-icons) (Note: this is a generic BSD license; the svg-icons web site didn't have a specific instance)

Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions are met: 

    * Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.
    * Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in the documentation and/or other materials provided with the distribution.
    * Neither the name of the ORGANIZATION nor the names of its contributors may be used to endorse or promote products derived from this software without specific prior written permission.

THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS "AS IS" AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE COPYRIGHT OWNER OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE. 
</license>

   <url>
      <discovery label="UIMA Eclipse Plugins update site" url="http://www.apache.org/dist/uima/eclipse-update-site/"/>
   </url>

   <includes
         id="org.apache.uima.runtime"
         version="${parsedVersion.osgiVersion}"
         name="UIMA Runtime plugin feature"/>

   <requires>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.core.runtime"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.jdt.debug.ui"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.ui"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.core.runtime.compatibility"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.ui.ide"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.jface.text"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.ui.workbench.texteditor"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.ui.editors"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.core.resources"/>
      <import plugin="org.apache.uima.runtime"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.ui.forms"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.jdt.core"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.jdt.ui"/>
      <import plugin="org.apache.uima.jcas.jcasgenp"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.jdt.launching"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.search"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.emf.codegen"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.emf.common"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.ui.views"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.jdt"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.text"/>
      <import plugin="org.eclipse.ui.workbench"/>
   </requires>

   <plugin
         id="org.apache.uima.debug"
         download-size="0"
         install-size="0"
         version="${parsedVersion.osgiVersion}"
         unpack="false"/>

   <plugin
         id="org.apache.uima.desceditor"
         download-size="0"
         install-size="0"
         version="${parsedVersion.osgiVersion}"
         unpack="false"/>

   <plugin
         id="org.apache.uima.jcas.jcasgenp"
         download-size="0"
         install-size="0"
         version="${parsedVersion.osgiVersion}"
         unpack="false"/>

   <plugin
         id="org.apache.uima.pear"
         download-size="0"
         install-size="0"
         version="${parsedVersion.osgiVersion}"
         unpack="false"/>

   <plugin
         id="org.apache.uima.caseditor"
         download-size="0"
         install-size="0"
         version="${parsedVersion.osgiVersion}"
         unpack="false"/>

   <plugin
         id="org.apache.uima.caseditor.ide"
         download-size="0"
         install-size="0"
         version="${parsedVersion.osgiVersion}"
         unpack="false"/>

   <plugin
         id="org.apache.uima.launcher"
         download-size="0"
         install-size="0"
         version="${parsedVersion.osgiVersion}"
         unpack="false"/>
        

</feature>
