<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY imgroot "images/version_3_users_guide/migration/">
<!ENTITY % uimaents SYSTEM "../../target/docbook-shared/entities.ent">  
%uimaents;
]>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->
<chapter id="uv3.migration">
  <title>Migrating JCas classes</title>
  <titleabbrev>Migrating JCas</titleabbrev>
  
  <section id="uv3.migration.big_picture">
    <title>How to migrate an existing UIMA pipeline to V3</title>
    <titleabbrev>How to migrate</titleabbrev>
    
    <para>
      UIMA V3 is designed to be binary compatible with existing UIMA V2 pipelines, so compiled and/or JAR-ed up classes 
      representing a V2 pipeline should run with UIMA v3, with two changes:
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem><para>Java 8 is required. (If you're already using Java 8, nothing need be done.)</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Any defined JCas cover classes must be migrated or regenerated, and used instead.
        (If you do not define any JCas classes or don't use JCas in your pipeline, then nothing need be done.)</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    
    <para>Some Maven projects use the JCasGen maven plugin; these project's JCasGen maven plugin,
     if switched to UIMA V3, automatically generate the V3 versions.
    </para>
    
    <para>You can use any of the methods of invoking JCasGen to generate the new V3 versions.  If you already have
    the source or class files, you can also migrate those using the migration tool described in this section.</para>
     
    <para>For simple testing, after users have migrated or generated any user-supplied JCas classes, 
      users typically will JAR-up these migrated classes,
      and then place that JAR in the class path ahead of the original V2 pipeline's classes so these will replace
      the corresponding classes.
    </para>
    
    <section id="uv3.migration.maven-cookbook">
      <title>Modifying a Maven project to support both v2 &amp; v3</title>
      <titleabbrev>Maven v2/v3 simultaneous support</titleabbrev>
      
      <para>When migrating an existing Maven project to v3, you can of course, just change the dependencies, upgrade
      to Java 8 if needed, and migrate/regenerate any user-defined JCas class definitions.  Nothing special is needed
      for this approach.</para>
      
      <para>If you want to simultaneously support both v2 and v3, you can take advantage of the binary compatibility
      support in v3, and have one set of maven artifacts for both (compiled with Java 7), plus an additional
      Maven project just for the generated JCas classes v3-style.  This additional maven project would 
      specify Java 8 and UIMA v3 dependencies, and produce a Jar file with the V3 version, either from migrated Java sources,
      or using the JCasGen maven plugin, generating from the type system description.</para>
      
      <para>
      The using community would see the original output artifacts, plus one new Jar artifact, which, if they were
      wanting to use V3, they would need to place ahead of the original artifacts in the running pipeline's classpath.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section id="uv3.migration.jcas">
    <title>Migrating JCas classes</title>
    
  <para>Some projects are built using Maven, and use the JCasGen Maven plugin as part of the build.
  These builds, when switched to depend on version 3, will automatically generate the new JCas
  class definitions, so nothing special need be done.
  </para>
  
  <para>If you have customized JCasGen classes, these can be migrated by running the migration tool, which is available
	  as a stand-alone command line tool (<code>runV3migrateJCas.sh or ...bat</code>), or 
	  as an Eclipse launch configuration.</para>
	  
  <para>This tool is run against a directory tree, and scans all the files in the tree, looking for 
     JCas cover classes.  It can process either source files, or, if those are not available, compiled
     class files.  It can process these inside directories, as well as inside Jar files within those directories.</para>
                
	<para>Run this tool using a Java 8 JDK (as opposed to a Java JRE) in order to have the Java compiler available.</para>

  <para>The results of the migration include the migrated class files and a set of logs, summarized in the console
    output, detailing anything that might need inspection to verify the migration was done correctly.
  </para>
  
  <blockquote><para>
    If all is OK, the migration will say that it "finished with no unusual conditions", at the end.
  </para></blockquote> 	  

  <para>To complete the migration, update your UIMA application to use these classes in place of the version 2 JCas classes.
  </para>
    
  <para>The migration tool is able to scan multiple directory trees, looking for existing Java
	  source (.java) or class (.class) files, even inside Jars and PEAR archives. If compiled class files
	  are used as input, a Java decompiler is used to decompile these to source.
	  For PEARs and Jars, it replaces the migrated and compiled classes in copies of the PEARs and Jars.
	</para>
	
	<para>  
	  The actual migration step is a source-to-source transformation, done using a Java parse of the source files.
	  The parts in the source which are version 2 specific with the equivalent
	  version 3 code.
	  Only those parts which need updating are modified;
    other code and comments which are part of the source file are left unchanged.  This is intended to preserve
    any user customization that may have been done.  
    Detailed reports detailing any issues encountered are written to log files. 
  </para>
    
<!--    <section id="uv3.migration.automatic">
    <title>Automatic migration</title>
    
    <para>It is sometimes possible to have this migration done automatically, when a pipeline is started up.  Although
      convenient, it has some drawbacks, the main ones being that it may not work correctly for more complex
      customized JCas sources, and it slows down the launch of pipelines.  Ideally, the migration utility would be used
      and the results checked before proceeding, and the migrated classes replaced in the pipeline(s), as a one time
      migration process.</para>
      
    <para>The automatic migration works by detecting version 2 classes, decompiling them, migrating them, compiling
      the migrated version, and then loading them in place of the version 2 classes.</para>
    
    <para>The automatic migration will throw a Runtime Exception 
    if an unusual condition occurs for any reason during this process.
    </para>
  </section>
 --> 
 		 
		 <note><para>The compilation step (done after the source-to-source transformation) requires that a Java compiler is available 
		   (which will be the case if you're running with a Java JDK, not a JRE).
		 </para></note>
		 
		 <note><para>After running the tool, it is important to examining the console output and logs.
       You can confirm that the migration completed without any unusual conditions, or, if something 
       unusual was encountered, you can take corrective action.
		 </para></note>
		  
		<section id="uv3.migration.tool_guide.running">
	    <title>Running the migration tool</title>
	    <para>The tool can be run as a stand-alone command, using the launcher scripts <code>runV3migrateJCas</code>; 
	      there are two versions of this &mdash; one for windows (ending it ".bat") and one for linux / mac (ending in ".sh").
		    If you run this without any arguments, it will show a brief help for the arguments.
		  </para>
		  
		  <para>There are also a pair of Eclipse launch configurations 
        (one for source files, the other for compiled classes), 
        which are available if you have the uimaj-examples project
        (included in the binary distribution of UIMA) in your Eclipse workspace.
      </para>
      
      <section id="uv3.migration.tool_guide.running.eclipse">
      <title>Using Eclipse to run the migration tool</title>
      
        <para>There are two Eclipse launch configurations; one works with source code, the other with compiled classes
          or Jars or PEARs.  The launch configurations are named:
          <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem><para>UIMA Run V3 migrate JCas from sources roots</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>UIMA Run V3 migrate JCas from classes roots</para></listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          When running from classes roots, the classes must not have compile errors, and may contain Jars and PEARs. 
        </para>
      
        <para>
          To use these launchers,
            <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
              <listitem><para>First select the eclipse project; this project's "build path" will supply the 
                classpath used during migration for decompiling and compiling the sources.</para></listitem>
              <listitem><para>run the launcher - it will prompt for two values:
                <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
                  <listitem><para>the root directory to scan recursively looking for JCas sources or classes/Jars/Pears to be converted</para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>an output directory - a writable folder, such as /temp/migrate</para></listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </para></listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
  		  </para>
  	    
  	    <para>No matter how the tool is started, the input to the tool is one or more directory tree roots; 
  	      the tool will scan the file system under these roots (including inside Jars and PEARs when running from
          compiled classes), looking for definitions to migrate.  
  	    </para>
		    
	      <!-- <blockquote><para>It can also be run with a list of specific JCas classes
	      to migrate.</para></blockquote> -->
        
      </section>
		  
      
      <section id="uv3.migration.tool_guide.running.cmd_line">
      <title>Running from the command line</title>
      
  	    <section id="uv3.migration.tool_guide.running.inputs">
  	      <title>Command line: Specifying input sources</title>
  	    
  	    <para>Input is specified using these arguments:
  		    <variablelist>
  	
  		      <varlistentry>
  		        <term><emphasis role="strong">"-sourcesRoots"</emphasis></term>
  		        <listitem>
  		          <para>a list of one or more directories, separated by the
  		            a path separator character (";" for Windows, ":" for others). 
  		          </para>
  		          <para>Migrates each candidate source file found in any of the file tree roots,
  		            skipping over non-JCas classes.</para>
  		        </listitem>
  		      </varlistentry>
  	
  	        <varlistentry>
  	          <term><emphasis role="strong">"-classesRoots"</emphasis></term>
  	          <listitem>
                <para>a list of one or more directories
                  containing class files or Jars or PEARs, separated by the
                  a path separator character (";" for Windows, ":" for others). 
                </para>
  	            <para>Decompiles, then migrates each candidate class file found in any of the file tree roots
  	              (skipping over non-JCas classes).  
  	            </para>	              
  	          </listitem>
  	        </varlistentry>
  	        
  		    </variablelist>  
  	    </para>
        </section>
        	    
  	    <section id="uv3.migration.tool_guide.classpath">
  	      <title>Command line: Specifying a classpath for the migration</title>
  	      <para>A classpath is required for the proper operation of the decompiling and compiling steps of 
  	        the migration.  This is provided using the argument <code>-migrateClasspath</code>.
  	        The Eclipse launcher "UIMA run V3 migrate JCas from classes roots" sets this argument using
  	        the selected Eclipse project's classpath.
  	        When migrating within a PEAR, the migration tool automatically adds the PEAR classes to the 
  	        classpath.
  	      </para>
  	    </section>

      </section>
      	    	    	    
	    <section id="uv3.migration.tool_guide.duplicates">
	      <title>Handling duplicate definitions</title>
	      <para>Sometimes, a classpath or directory tree may contain multiple instances of the same JCas class.
	        These might be identical, or they might be different versions.  The migration utility detects this, 
	        and migrates all non-identical instances, using a convention to store them in the output directory in a manner
	        where different versions can be conveniently compared using tooling such as Eclipse's file compare.
	      </para>
	      <blockquote><para>When there are non-identical duplicate definitions, 
	        the user must manually compare these and decide which version to use.</para></blockquote>
	      
	    </section>
	  </section>  

    <section id="uv3.migration.tool_guide.reports">
      <title>Understanding the reports</title>
      <para>The output directory contains a logs directory with additional information.
        A summary is also written to System.out.
      </para>
        
      <para>Each file translated has both a v2 source and a v3 source.  When the input is ".class" files, 
        the v2 source is the result of the decompilation step, prior to any migration.
      </para>
      
      <blockquote><para>
        These are arranged in parallel directories, allowing Eclipse's multi-file directory "compare" to work on both directory
        collections and conveniently show for all the migrated files the change details.
      </para></blockquote>
        
      <para>In the case of non-identical duplicates, an increasing integer 
        starting with 1 is inserted into the output directory tree
        for each migrated class.</para>
        
      <para>The overall directory output directory tree looks like:
        <programlisting>Directory structure, starting at -outputDirectory
   converted/
     v2/
       x/y/z/javapath/.../Classname.java
       x/y/z/javapath/.../Classname.java
       ...
     v3/
       x/y/z/javapath/.../Classname.java
       x/y/z/javapath/.../Classname.java
       ...
       
       
       1/     &lt;&lt; for non identical duplicates
         x/y/z/javapath/.../Classname.java    
         x/y/z/javapath/.../Classname.java  
         ...                                    
       2/     &lt;&lt; for non identical duplicates
         x/y/z/javapath/.../Classname.java
         x/y/z/javapath/.../Classname.java
         ...
     v3-classes/
         ...    
       
   not-converted/
   logs/
     processed.txt
     failed.txt
     skippedBuiltins.txt
     NonJCasFiles.txt
     workaroundDir.txt
     deletedCheckModified.txt
     manualInspection.txt
     pearsFileUpdates.txt
     jarsFileUpdates.txt
   pears/
     xyz_converted_pear.pear  
     ...
   jars/
     ...</programlisting>
     
        The converted subtree holds all the sources and migrated versions that were successfully migrated.
        The not-converted subtree hold the sources that failed in some way the migration.
        The logs contain many kinds of entries for different issues encountered:
        <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="strong">processed.txt</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>List of successfully processed classes
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="strong">failed.txt</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>List of classes that failed to migrate
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="strong">skippedBuiltins.txt</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>List of classes representing built-ins that were skipped.  These need
                manual inspection to see how to merge with new v3 built-ins.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="strong">NonJCasFiles.txt</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>List of files that were thought to be JCas classes but 
                upon further analysis appear to not be.  These need 
                manual inspection to confirm.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="strong">deletedCheckModified.txt</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>List of class where a version 2 if statement doing the "featOkTst"
                was apparently modified.  In the migrated code, this statement was deleted,
                perhaps incorrectly. These need manual inspection to confirm.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="strong">manualInspection.txt</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>List of files where the migration found a get or set method, where
                the version 2 code was accessing a casFeatCode with the 
                feature name not matching.  These need manual inspection.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="strong">workaroundDir.txt</emphasis></term>
	          <listitem>
	            <para>When running conversions on a windows system for files from a linux system,
	              sometimes there is a clash caused by the fact that Windows doesn't recognize 
	              upper vs lower case in file names.  When this happens, an entry is logged here,
	              and the conflicting name is suffixed with a "_c".
	            </para>
	          </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="strong">jarsFileUpdates.txt</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>List of Jar files and classes which were replace in them.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="strong">pearsFileUpdates.txt</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para>List of Pear files and classes which were replace in them.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>    
      </para>
      
           
    </section>
    
    <section id="uv3.migration.tool_guide.cookbook">
      <title>Examples</title> 
    
      <para>Run the command line tool:
      <programlisting>cd $UIMA_HOME
      
bin/runV3migrateJCas.sh

  -migrateClasspath /home/me/myproj/xyz.jar:$UIMA_HOME/lib/uima-core.jar
    
  -classesRoots /home/me/myproj/xyz.jar:/home/me/myproj/target/classes
  
  -outputDirectory /temp/migratejcas  
</programlisting>
      </para>
      
      <para>Run the Eclipse launcher:</para>
      
      <programlisting>Load Eclipse workspace containing the project to be migrated,
  and the version 3 uimaj-migration project.
      
Select the Java project having the classpath used when running.

Eclipse -&gt; menu -&gt; Run -&gt; Run configurations
  Use the search box to find "Migrate JCas" launcher, and launch that.

In the first prompt, 
  enter the path to the root of the compiled classes or Jar or PEAR
In the second prompt, 
  enter a path to where you want the output, e.g. /temp/migrateJCas
</programlisting>
    
    <para>Please read the console output summarization to see about any 
      conditions found during migration which need manual inspection and fixup.</para>
    </section>
    
  </section>
</chapter>