<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY imgroot "images/uima_v3_users_guide/backwards_compatibility/">
<!ENTITY % uimaents SYSTEM "../../target/docbook-shared/entities.ent">  
%uimaents;
]>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->
<chapter id="uv3.backwards_compatibility">
  <title>Backwards Compatibility</title>
  <titleabbrev>Backwards Compatibility</titleabbrev>
  
  <para>Version 3 is designed to be backwards compatibile, except for needing a new set of JCas classes (if these were
  previously being used).</para>
  
  <section id="uv3.backwards_compatibility.serialization">  
	  <title>Serialization forms</title>
	  
	  <para>
	  The backwards compatibility extends to the serialized forms, so that it should be
	  possible to have a UIMA-AS services working with a client, where the client is a version 3 instance, but the
	  server is still a version 2 (or vice versa).  This compatibility is limited in that if new primitive extensions
	  only available in version 3, these can't be received by a version 2 deserializer.
	  </para>
	  
  </section>
  
  <section id="uv3.backards_compatibility.low_level_apis">
    <title>Low Level APIs</title>
    
    <para>Version 2 had APIs called "low level"; these were designed to be used in situations where high performance
    was needed, at the expense of being much more fragile.  Use of these APIs typically avoided creating Java objects,
    and used, in many cases, untyped (and unchecked) plain <code>ints</code> as handles to Feature Structures.
    </para>
    
    <para>In Version 3 these APIs are still supported, but are no longer higher performance, and should be avoided.
    The APIs remain for backwards compatibility.  An example of this is the Binary Serialization protocol.  This 
    remains, for backward compatibility, and because it's used for the <code>C/C++</code> interoperability layer, 
    but that use requires modelling the exact layout of how Version 2 stored CASs and converting between these two
    forms, so it is not particularly efficient.</para>
    
    <para>One consequence of the move toward storing Feature Structures as 
    Java objects, is that the low level Feature Structure creation APIs (which return an int handle) 
    must create an artificial reference to the Java object to keep it from being Garbage Collected (GC'd).
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="uv3.backards_compatibility.PEARs">
    <title>PEAR support</title>   
    
    <para>Pears are supported in Version 3.  If they use JCas, their JCas classes need to be migrated.
    </para>
  </section>
  
  <section id="uv3.backards_compatibility.typesystem_sharing">
    <title>Type System sharing</title>   
    
    <para>Type System definitions are shared when they are equal.  After type systems 
    have been built up from type definitions, and are committed, a check is made to see if an
    identical type system already exists.  This is often the case when a UIMA application is
    scaling up by adding multiple pipelines, all using the same type system.  
    </para>
    
    <para>If an identical type system is already created, then the commit operation returns 
    the already created one, and the one just built is discarded.  Normally, this is not an issue.
    However, some application code (for example, test cases) may construct type systems
    programmatically, and along the way save references to defined types and features.  These
    references can then become invalid when the type system is created and perhaps replaced with
    an already existing one.</para>
    
    <para>Application code should code around this by reacquiring references to type and feature
    objects, if the type system returned from <code>commit</code> is not identical (==) to the
    one being committed.</para>
  </section>
  </chapter>