<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY imgroot "../images/tools/tools.pear.packager/" >
<!ENTITY % uimaents SYSTEM "../entities.ent" >  
%uimaents;
]>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->
<chapter id="ugr.tools.pear.packager">
  <title>PEAR Packager User&apos;s Guide</title>
  
  <para>A PEAR (Processing Engine ARchive) file is a standard package for UIMA (Unstructured
    Information Management Architecture) components. The PEAR package can be used for
    distribution and reuse by other components or applications. It also allows applications
    and tools to manage UIMA components automatically for verification, deployment,
    invocation, testing, etc. Please refer to <olink targetdoc="&uima_docs_ref;" targetptr="ugr.ref.pear"/>
    for more information about the internal structure of a PEAR file.</para>
  
  <para>This chapter describes how to use the PEAR Eclipse plugin or the PEAR command line packager 
  to create PEAR files for standard UIMA components.</para>
  
  <section id="ugr.tools.pear.packager.using_eclipse_plugin">
    <title>Using the PEAR Eclipse Plugin</title>
    
    <para>The PEAR Eclipse plugin is automatically installed if you followed the directions in
      <olink targetdoc="&uima_docs_overview;" targetptr="ugr.ovv.eclipse_setup"/>. The use of the 
      plugin involves the following two steps:</para>
    
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact"><listitem><para>Add the UIMA nature to your project
      </para></listitem>
      
      <listitem><para>Create a PEAR file using the PEAR generation wizard </para>
        </listitem></itemizedlist>
    
    <section id="ugr.tools.pear.packager.add_uima_nature">
      <title>Add UIMA Nature to your project</title>
      
      <para>First, create a project for your UIMA component:</para>
      
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact"><listitem><para>Create a Java project, which
        would contain all the files and folders needed for your UIMA component.</para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>Create a source folder called <quote>src</quote> in your
          project, and make it the only source folder, by clicking on
          <quote>Properties</quote> in your project&apos;s context menu (right-click),
          then select <quote>Java Build Path</quote>, then add the <quote>src</quote>
          folder to the source folders list, and remove any other folder from the
          list.</para></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>Specify an output folder for your project called bin, by clicking
          on <quote>Properties</quote> in your project&apos;s context menu
          (right-click), then select <quote>Java Build Path</quote>, and specify
          <quote><emphasis>your_project_name</emphasis>/bin</quote> as the default
          output folder. </para></listitem></itemizedlist>
      
      <para>Then, add the UIMA nature to your project by clicking on <quote>Add UIMA
        Nature</quote> in the context menu (right-click) of your project. Click
        <quote>Yes</quote> on the <quote>Adding UIMA custom Nature</quote> dialog box.
        Click <quote>OK</quote> on the confirmation dialog box.
        
        
        <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="5.8in" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;image002.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>Screenshot of Adding the UIMA Nature to your project</phrase>
        </textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot></para>
      
      <para>Adding the UIMA nature to your project creates the PEAR structure in your
        project. The PEAR structure is a structured tree of folders and files, including the
        following elements:
        
        <itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Required
          Elements:</emphasis>
          
          <itemizedlist><listitem><para>The <emphasis role="bold">
            metadata</emphasis> folder which contains the PEAR installation descriptor
            and properties files.</para></listitem>
            
            <listitem><para>The installation descriptor (<emphasis role="bold">
              metadata/install.xml</emphasis>)
              </para></listitem></itemizedlist></para></listitem>
          
          <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Optional Elements:</emphasis>
            
            <itemizedlist><listitem><para>The <emphasis role="bold">
              desc</emphasis> folder to contain descriptor files of analysis engines,
              component analysis engines (all levels), and other component (Collection
              Readers, CAS Consumers, etc).</para></listitem>
              
              <listitem><para>The <emphasis role="bold">src </emphasis>folder to
                contain the source code</para></listitem>
              
              <listitem><para>The <emphasis role="bold">bin</emphasis> folder to
                contain executables, scripts, class files, dlls, shared libraries,
                etc.</para></listitem>
              
              <listitem><para>The <emphasis role="bold">lib</emphasis> folder to
                contain jar files. </para></listitem>
              
              <listitem><para>The <emphasis role="bold">doc </emphasis>folder
                containing documentation materials, preferably accessible through an
                index.html.</para></listitem>
              
              <listitem><para>The <emphasis role="bold">data</emphasis> folder to
                contain data files (e.g. for testing).</para></listitem>
              
              <listitem><para>The <emphasis role="bold">conf</emphasis> folder to
                contain configuration files.</para></listitem>
              
              <listitem><para>The <emphasis role="bold">resources</emphasis> folder
                to contain other resources and dependencies.</para></listitem>
              
              <listitem><para>Other user-defined folders or files are allowed, but
                <emphasis>should be avoided</emphasis>. </para></listitem>
              </itemizedlist> </para></listitem></itemizedlist></para>
      
      <para>For more information about the PEAR structure, please refer to the
        <quote>Processing Engine Archive</quote> section.
        
        <figure id="ugr.tools.pear.packager.fig.pear_structure">
          <title>The Pear Structure</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="3in" format="JPG"
                fileref="&imgroot;image004.jpg"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject><phrase>Pear structure</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure></para>
      
    </section>
    <section id="ugr.tools.pear.packager.using_pear_generation_wizard">
      <title>Using the PEAR Generation Wizard</title>
      
      <para>Before using the PEAR Generation Wizard, add all the files needed to
        run your component including descriptors, jars, external libraries, resources,
        and component analysis engines (in the case of an aggregate analysis engine), etc.
        <emphasis>Do not</emphasis> add Jars for the UIMA framework, however.  Doing so will
        cause class loading problems at run time.</para>
      <para>
        If you're using a Java IDE like Eclipse, instead of using the output folder (usually 
        <literal>bin</literal> as the source of your classes, it&apos;s recommended that 
        you generate a Jar file containing these classes.</para>
      
      <para>Then, click on <quote>Generate PEAR file</quote> from the context menu
        (right-click) of your project, to open the PEAR Generation wizard, and follow the
        instructions on the wizard to generate the PEAR file.</para>
      
      <section id="ugr.tools.pear.packager.wizard.component_information">
        <title>The Component Information page</title>
        
        <para>The first page of the PEAR generation wizard is the component information
          page. Specify in this page a component ID for your PEAR and select the main Analysis
          Engine descriptor. The descriptor must be specified using a pathname relative to
          the project&apos;s root (e.g. <quote>desc/MyAE.xml</quote>). The component id
          is a string that uniquely identifies the component. It should use the JAVA naming
          convention (e.g. org.apache.uima.mycomponent).</para>
        
        <para>Optionally, you can include specific Collection Iterator, CAS Initializer (deprecated
          as of Version 2.1),
          or CAS Consumers. In this case, specify the corresponding descriptors in this
          page.
          
          <figure id="ugr.tools.pear.packager.fig.wizard.component_information">
            <title>The Component Information Page</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="5.8in" format="JPG"
                  fileref="&imgroot;image006.jpg"/>
              </imageobject>
              <textobject><phrase>Pear Wizard - component information page</phrase>
              </textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure></para>
        
      </section>
      
      <section id="ugr.tools.pear.packager.wizard.install_environment">
        <title>The Installation Environment page</title>
        
        <para>The installation environment page is used to specify the following:
          
          <itemizedlist spacing="compact"><listitem><para>Preferred operating
            system</para></listitem>
            
            <listitem><para>Required JDK version, if applicable.</para></listitem>
            
            <listitem><para>Required Environment variable settings.  This is where
              you specify special CLASSPATH paths.  You do not need to specify this for
              any Jar that is listed in the your eclipse project classpath settings; those are automatically
              put into the generated CLASSPATH.  Nor should you include paths to the
              UIMA Framework itself, here.  Doing so may cause class loading problems.
            </para>
              
            <para>CLASSPATH segments are written here using a semicolon ";" as the separator;
              during PEAR installation, these will be adjusted to be the correct character for the
              target Operating System.</para>
            
            <para>In order to specify the UIMA datapath for your component you have to create an environment
            variable with the property name <literal>uima.datapath</literal>. The value of this property 
            must contain the UIMA datapath settings.</para>
              
              </listitem></itemizedlist></para>
        
        <para>Path names should be specified using macros (see below), instead of
          hard-coded absolute paths that might work locally, but probably won&apos;t if the
          PEAR is deployed in a different machine and environment.</para>
        
        <para>Macros are variables such as $main_root, used to represent a string such as the
          full path of a certain directory.</para>
        
        <para>These macros should be defined in the PEAR.properties file using the local
          values. The tools and applications that use and deploy PEAR files should replace
          these macros (in the files included in the conf and desc folders) with the
          corresponding values in the local environment as part of the deployment
          process.</para>
        
        <para>Currently, there are two types of macros:</para>
        
        <itemizedlist><listitem><para>$main_root, which represents the local absolute
          path of the main component root directory after deployment.</para></listitem>
          
          <listitem><para><emphasis>$component_id$root</emphasis>, which
            represents the local absolute path to the root directory of the component which
            has <emphasis>component_id</emphasis> as component ID. This component could
            be, for instance, a delegate component. </para></listitem></itemizedlist>
        
        <figure id="ugr.tools.pear.packager.fig.wizard.install_environment">
          <title>The Installation Environment Page</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="5.8in" format="JPG"
                fileref="&imgroot;image008.jpg"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject><phrase>Pear Wizard - install environment page</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        
      </section>
      
      <section id="ugr.tools.pear.packager.wizard.file_content">
        <title>The PEAR file content page</title>
        
        <para>The last page of the wizard is the <quote>PEAR file Export</quote> page, which
          allows the user to select the files to include in the PEAR file. The metadata folder
          and all its content is mandatory. Make sure you include all the files needed to run
          your component including descriptors, jars, external libraries, resources, and
          component analysis engines (in the case of an aggregate analysis engine), etc.
          It&apos;s recommended to generate a jar file from your code as an alternative to
          building the project and making sure the output folder (bin) contains the required
          class files.</para>
        
        <para>Eclipse compiles your class files into some output directory, often named
        "bin" when you take the usual defaults in Eclipse.  The recommended practice is to
        take all these files and put them into a Jar file, perhaps using the Eclipse Export 
        wizard.  You would place that Jar file into the PEAR <literal>lib</literal> directory.</para>
        
        <note><para>If you are relying on the class files generated in the output folder
          (usually called bin) to run your code, then make sure the project is built properly,
          and all the required class files are generated without errors, and then put the
          output folder (e.g. $main_root/bin) in the classpath using the option to set
          environment variables, by setting the CLASSPATH variable to include this folder (see the
          <quote>Installation Environment</quote> page.
          Beware that using a Java output folder named "bin" in this case is a poor practice, 
            because the PEAR installation
          tools will presume this folder contains binary executable files, and will adds this folder to 
          the PATH environment variable.
          </para>          
          <figure id="ugr.tools.pear.packager.fig.wizard.export">
            <title>The PEAR File Export Page</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="5.8in" format="JPG"
                  fileref="&imgroot;image010.jpg"/>
              </imageobject>
              <textobject><phrase>Pear Wizard - File Export Page</phrase>
              </textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
          
          </note>
        
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section id="ugr.tools.pear.packager.using_command_line">
    <title>Using the PEAR command line packager</title>
     <para>The PEAR command line packager takes some PEAR package parameter settings on the command line to create an 
     UIMA PEAR file.</para>
     
     <para>To run the PEAR command line packager you can use the provided runPearPackager (.bat for Windows, and .sh for Unix) 
     scripts. The packager can be used in three different modes.</para>
     <para><itemizedlist>
     <listitem> 
     	<para>Mode 1: creates a complete PEAR package with the provided information (default mode)</para>
     	<para><programlisting>runPearPackager -compID &lt;componentID> 
  -mainCompDesc &lt;mainComponentDesc> [-classpath &lt;classpath>] 
  [-datapath &lt;datapath>] -mainCompDir &lt;mainComponentDir> 
  -targetDir &lt;targetDir> [-envVars &lt;propertiesFilePath>]</programlisting></para>   
     	<para> The created PEAR file has the file name &lt;componentID>.pear and is located in the &lt;targetDir>.</para>
     </listitem>
     
     <listitem> 
     	<para>Mode 2: creates a PEAR installation descriptor without packaging the PEAR file</para>
     	<para><programlisting>runPearPackager -create -compID &lt;componentID> 
  -mainCompDesc &lt;mainComponentDesc> [-classpath &lt;classpath>]
  [-datapath &lt;datapath>] -mainCompDir &lt;mainComponentDir> 
  [-envVars &lt;propertiesFilePath>]</programlisting></para>
     	<para> The PEAR installation descriptor is created in the &lt;mainComponentDir>/metadata directory.</para>
     </listitem>

     <listitem>
     	<para>Mode 3: creates a PEAR package with an existing PEAR installation descriptor</para>
     	<para><programlisting>runPearPackager -package -compID &lt;componentID> 
  -mainCompDir &lt;mainComponentDir> -targetDir &lt;targetDir></programlisting></para>
      	<para> The created PEAR file has the file name &lt;componentID>.pear and is located in the &lt;targetDir>.</para>
     </listitem>
     	 
     </itemizedlist>
     </para>          
     <para>The modes 2 and 3 should be used when you want to manipulate the PEAR installation descriptor before packaging
     the PEAR file. </para>
     
     <para>Some more details about the PearPackager parameters is provided in the list below:</para>
     <para><itemizedlist>
     <listitem> 
     	<simpara><literal>&lt;componentID></literal>: PEAR package component ID.</simpara>
     </listitem>
     
     <listitem> 
     	<simpara><literal>&lt;mainComponentDesc></literal>: Main component descriptor of the PEAR package.</simpara>
     </listitem>

     <listitem>
     	<simpara><literal>&lt;classpath></literal>: PEAR classpath settings. Use $main_root macros to specify
     	path entries. Use <literal>;</literal> to separate the entries.</simpara>
     </listitem>

     <listitem>
     	<simpara><literal>&lt;datapath></literal>: PEAR datapath settings. Use $main_root macros to specify
     	path entries. Use <literal>;</literal> to separate the path entries.</simpara>
     </listitem>

     <listitem>
     	<simpara><literal>&lt;mainComponentDir></literal>: Main component directory that contains the PEAR package content.</simpara>
     </listitem>

     <listitem>
     	<simpara><literal>&lt;targetDir></literal>: Target directory where the created PEAR file is written to.</simpara>
     </listitem>

     <listitem>
     	<simpara><literal>&lt;propertiesFilePath></literal>: Path name to a properties file that contains environment variables that must be
     	set to run the PEAR content.</simpara>
     </listitem>
          	 
     </itemizedlist>
     
     </para>
   </section>
  
</chapter>