<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY imgroot "../images/tools/tools.jcasgen/" >
<!ENTITY % uimaents SYSTEM "../entities.ent" >  
%uimaents;
]>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->
<chapter id="ugr.tools.jcasgen">
  <title>JCasGen User&apos;s Guide</title>
  
  <para>JCasGen reads a descriptor for an application (either an Analysis Engine Descriptor, 
    or a Type System Descriptor), creates the merged type system
    specification by merging all the type system information from all the components
    referred to in the descriptor, and then uses this merged type system to create Java source
    files for classes that enable JCas access to the CAS. Java classes are not produced for the
    built-in types, since these classes are already provided by the UIMA SDK.  (An exception is
    the built-in type <literal>uima.tcas.DocumentAnnotation</literal>, see the warning below.) </para>
  
  <warning><para>If the components comprising the input to the type merging process 
    have different definitions for the same type name,
    JCasGen will show a warning, and in some environments may offer to abort the operation.
    If you continue past this warning, 
    JCasGen will produce correct Java source files representing the merged types 
   (that is, the
    type definition containing all of the features defined on that type by all of the
    components).  It is recommended that you do not use this capability (of having 
    two different definitions for the same type name, with different feature sets) since it can make it 
    difficult to combine/package your annotator with others. See <olink
      targetdoc="&uima_docs_ref;"
      targetptr="ugr.ref.jcas.merging_types_from_other_specs"/> for more information.
  </para>
  
  <para>Also note that if your type system declares a custom version of the 
    <literal>uima.tcas.DocumentAnnotation</literal> 
    built-in type, then JCasGen will generate a Java source file for it.  If you do this, you need to be
    aware of the issues discussed in 
    <olink
       targetdoc="&uima_docs_ref;"
       targetptr="ugr.ref.jcas.documentannotation_issues"/>.</para></warning>
  
  <para>There are several versions of JCasGen. The basic version reads an XML descriptor
    which contains a type system descriptor, and generates the corresponding Java Class
    Models for those types. Variants exist for the Eclipse environment that allow merging the
    newly generated Java source code with previously augmented versions; see <olink
      targetdoc="&uima_docs_ref;"
      targetptr="ugr.ref.jcas.augmenting_generated_code"/> for a discussion of how the
    Java Class Models can be augmented by adding additional methods and fields.</para>
  
  <para>Input to JCasGen needs to be mostly self-contained. In particular, any types that are
    defined to depend on user-defined supertypes must have that supertype defined, if the
    supertype is <literal>uima.tcas.Annotation </literal>or a subtype of it. Any features
    referencing ranges which are subtypes of uima.cas.String must have those subtypes
    included. If this is not followed, a warning message is given stating that the resulting
    generation may be inaccurate.</para>
  
  <para>JCasGen is typically invoked automatically when using the Component Descriptor
    Editor (see <olink targetdoc="&uima_docs_tools;"
      targetptr="ugr.tools.cde.auto_jcasgen"/>), but can also be run using a shell
    script. These scripts can take 0, 1, or 2 arguments. The first argument is the location of
    the file containing the input XML descriptor. The second argument specifies where the
    generated Java source code should go. If it isn&apos;t given, JCasGen generates its
    output into a subfolder called JCas (or sometimes JCasNew &ndash; see below), of the first
    argument&apos;s path.</para>
  
  <para>If no arguments are given to JCasGen, then it launches a GUI to interact with the user
    and ask for the same input. The GUI will remember the arguments you previously used.
    Here&apos;s what it looks like:
    
    
    <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="5.8in" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;image002.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>JCasGen tool showing fields for input arguments</phrase>
        </textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot></para>
  
  <para>When running with automatic merging of the generated Java source with previously
    augmented versions, the output location is where the merge function obtains the source
    for the merge operation.</para>
  
  <para>As is customary for Java, the generated class source files are placed in the
    appropriate subdirectory structure according to Java conventions that correspond to
    the package (name space) name.</para>
  
  <para>The Java classes must be compiled and the resulting class files included in the class
    path of your application; you make these classes available for other annotator writers
    using your types, perhaps packaged as an xxx.jar file. If the xxx.jar file is made to
    contain only the Java Class Models for the CAS types, it can be reused by any users of these
    types.</para>
  
  <section id="ugr.tools.jcasgen.running_without_eclipse">
    <title>Running stand-alone without Eclipse</title>
    
    <para>There is no capability to automatically merge the generated Java source with
      previous versions, unless running with Eclipse. If run without Eclipse, no automatic
      merging of the generated Java source is done with any previous versions. In this case,
      the output is put in a folder called <quote>JCasNew</quote> unless overridden by
      specifying a second argument.</para>
    
    <para>The distribution includes a shell script/bat file to run the stand-alone version,
      called jcasgen.</para>
    
  </section>
  
  <section id="ugr.tools.jcasgen.running_standalone_with_eclipse">
    <title>Running stand-alone with Eclipse</title>
    
    <para>If you have Eclipse and EMF (EMF = Eclipse Modeling Framework; both of these are
      available from <ulink url="http://www.eclipse.org"/>) installed (version 3 or
      later) JCasGen can merge the Java code it generates with previous versions, picking up
      changes you might have inserted by hand. The output (and source of the merge input) is in a
      folder <quote>JCas</quote> under the same path as the input XML file, unless
      overridden by specifying a second argument.</para>
    
    <para>You must install the UIMA plug-ins into Eclipse to enable this function.</para>
    
    <para>The distribution includes a shell script/bat file to run the stand-alone with
      Eclipse version, called jcasgen_merge. This works by starting Eclipse in
      <quote>headless</quote> mode (no GUI) and invoking JCasGen within Eclipse. You will
      need to set the ECLIPSE_HOME environment variable or modify the jcasgen_merge shell
      script to specify where to find Eclipse. The version of Eclipse needed is 3 or higher,
      with the EMF plug-in and the UIMA runtime plug-in installed. A temporary workspace is
      used; the name/location of this is customizable in the shell script.</para>
    
    <para>Log and error messages are written to the UIMA log. This file is called uima.log, and
      is located in the default working directory, which if not overridden, is the startup
      directory of Eclipse.</para>
    
  </section>
  
  <section id="ugr.tools.jcasgen.running_within_eclipse">
    <title>Running within Eclipse</title>
    
    <para>There are two ways to run JCasGen within Eclipse. The first way is to configure an
      Eclipse external tools launcher, and use it to run the stand-alone shell scripts, with
      the arguments filled in. Here&apos;s a picture of a typical launcher configuration
      screen (you get here by navigating from the top menu: Run &ndash;&gt; External Tools
      &ndash;&gt; External tools...).
      
      
      <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="5.8in" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;image004.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>Running JCasGen within Eclipse using the external tool launcher</phrase>
        </textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </screenshot></para>
    
    <para>The second way (which is the normal way it's done) to run within Eclipse is to use the
      Component Descriptor Editor (CDE) (see <olink targetdoc="&uima_docs_tools;"
        targetptr="ugr.tools.cde"/>). This tool can be configured to automatically
      launch JCasGen whenever the type system descriptor is modified. In this release, this
      operation completely regenerates the files, even if just a small thing changed. For
      very large type systems, you probably don&apos;t want to enable this all the time. The
      configurator tool has an option to enable/disable this function.</para>
  </section>
  
</chapter>