<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY imgroot "../images/tutorials_and_users_guides/tug.aae/">
<!ENTITY % uimaents SYSTEM "../entities.ent">  
%uimaents;
]>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one
or more contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file
distributed with this work for additional information
regarding copyright ownership.  The ASF licenses this file
to you under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the
"License"); you may not use this file except in compliance
with the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

   http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing,
software distributed under the License is distributed on an
"AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY
KIND, either express or implied.  See the License for the
specific language governing permissions and limitations
under the License.
-->
<chapter id="ugr.tug.aae">
  <title>Annotator and Analysis Engine Developer&apos;s Guide</title>
  <titleabbrev>Annotator &amp; AE Developer&apos;s Guide</titleabbrev>
  
  <para>This chapter describes how to develop UIMA <emphasis>type systems</emphasis>,
    <emphasis>Annotators</emphasis> and <emphasis>Analysis Engines</emphasis> using
    the UIMA SDK. It is helpful to read the UIMA Conceptual Overview chapter for a review on
    these concepts.</para>
  
  <para>An <emphasis>Analysis Engine (AE)</emphasis> is a program that analyzes artifacts
    (e.g. documents) and infers information from them.</para>
  
  <para>Analysis Engines are constructed from building blocks called
    <emphasis>Annotators</emphasis>. An annotator is a component that contains analysis
    logic. Annotators analyze an artifact (for example, a text document) and create
    additional data (metadata) about that artifact. It is a goal of UIMA that annotators need
    not be concerned with anything other than their analysis logic &ndash; for example the
    details of their deployment or their interaction with other annotators.</para>
  
  <para>An Analysis Engine (AE) may contain a single annotator (this is referred to as a
    <emphasis>Primitive AE)</emphasis>, or it may be a composition of others and therefore
    contain multiple annotators (this is referred to as an <emphasis>Aggregate
    AE</emphasis>). Primitive and aggregate AEs implement the same interface and can be used
    interchangeably by applications.</para>
  
  <para>Annotators produce their analysis results in the form of typed <emphasis>Feature
    Structures</emphasis>, which are simply data structures that have a type and a set of
    (attribute, value) pairs. An <emphasis>annotation</emphasis> is a particular type of
    Feature Structure that is attached to a region of the artifact being analyzed (a span of
    text in a document, for example).</para>
  
  <para>For example, an annotator may produce an Annotation over the span of text
    <literal>President Bush</literal>, where the type of the Annotation is
    <literal>Person</literal> and the attribute <literal>fullName</literal> has the
    value <literal>George W. Bush</literal>, and its position in the artifact is character
    position 12 through character position 26.</para>
  
  <para>It is also possible for annotators to record information associated with the entire
    document rather than a particular span (these are considered Feature Structures but not
    Annotations).</para>
  
  <para>All feature structures, including annotations, are represented in the UIMA
    <emphasis>Common Analysis Structure(CAS)</emphasis>. The CAS is the central data
    structure through which all UIMA components communicate. Included with the UIMA SDK is an
    easy-to-use, native Java interface to the CAS called the <emphasis>JCas</emphasis>.
    The JCas represents each feature structure as a Java object; the example feature
    structure from the previous paragraph would be an instance of a Java class Person with
    getFullName() and setFullName() methods. Though the examples in this guide all use the
    JCas, it is also possible to directly access the underlying CAS system; for more
    information see <olink targetdoc="&uima_docs_ref;" targetptr="ugr.ref.cas"/>
    .</para>
  
  <para>The remainder of this chapter will refer to the analysis of text documents and the
    creation of annotations that are attached to spans of text in those documents. Keep in mind
    that the CAS can represent arbitrary types of feature structures, and feature structures
    can refer to other feature structures. For example, you can use the CAS to represent a parse
    tree for a document. Also, the artifact that you are analyzing need not be a text
    document.</para>
  
  <para>This guide is organized as follows:</para>
  
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="bold-italic"><xref linkend="ugr.tug.aae.getting_started"/></emphasis> is a
        tutorial with step-by-step instructions for how to develop and test a simple UIMA annotator.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="bold-italic"><xref linkend="ugr.tug.aae.configuration_logging"/>
        </emphasis> discusses how to make your UIMA annotator configurable, and how it can write messages to the UIMA
        log file.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para> <emphasis role="bold-italic"><xref linkend="ugr.tug.aae.building_aggregates"/></emphasis>
        describes how annotators can be combined into aggregate analysis engines. It also describes how one
        annotator can make use of the analysis results produced by an annotator that has run previously.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="bold-italic"><xref linkend="ugr.tug.aae.other_examples"/></emphasis>
        describes several other examples you may find interesting, including</para>
      
      <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>SimpleTokenAndSentenceAnnotator
            &ndash; a simple tokenizer and sentence annotator.</para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>PersonTitleDBWriterCasConsumer &ndash; a sample CAS Consumer which populates a relational
            database with some annotations. It uses JDBC and in this example, hooks up with the Open Source Apache
            Derby database. </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="bold-italic"><xref linkend="ugr.tug.aae.additional_topics"/></emphasis>
        describes additional features of the UIMA SDK that may help you in building your own annotators and analysis
        engines.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="bold-italic"><xref linkend="ugr.tug.aae.common_pitfalls"/> </emphasis>
        contains some useful guidelines to help you ensure that your annotators will work correctly in any UIMA
        application.</para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  
  <para>This guide does not discuss how to build UIMA Applications, which are programs that
    use Analysis Engines, along with other components, e.g. a search engine, document store,
    and user interface, to deliver a complete package of functionality to an end-user. For
    information on application development, see <olink
      targetdoc="&uima_docs_tutorial_guides;" targetptr="ugr.tug.application"
       xrefstyle="select: label quotedtitle"/>
    .</para>
  
  <section id="ugr.tug.aae.getting_started">
    <title>Getting Started</title>
    
    <para>This section is a step-by-step tutorial that will get you started developing UIMA
      annotators. All of the files referred to by the examples in this chapter are in the
      <literal>examples</literal> directory of the UIMA SDK. This directory is designed to
      be imported into your Eclipse workspace; see <olink
        targetdoc="&uima_docs_overview;"
        targetptr="ugr.ovv.eclipse_setup.example_code"/> for instructions on how to do
      this. 
      See <olink  targetdoc="&uima_docs_overview;"
        targetptr="ugr.ovv.eclipse_setup.linking_uima_javadocs"/> for how to attach the UIMA 
        Javadocs to the jar files.
      Also you may wish to refer to the UIMA SDK Javadocs located in the <ulink
        url="file:../../api/index.html">docs/api</ulink> directory.</para>
    
        <note><para>In Eclipse 3.1, if you highlight a UIMA class or method defined in the UIMA SDK
    Javadocs, you can conveniently have Eclipse open the corresponding Javadoc for that
    class or method in a browser, by pressing Shift + F2.</para></note>
    <note><para>If you downloaded the source distribution for UIMA, you can attach that as
    well to the library Jar files; for information on how to do this, see
    <olink targetdoc="&uima_docs_ref;" targetptr="ugr.ref.javadocs"/>.</para></note>

    <para>The example annotator that we are going to walk through will detect room numbers for
      rooms where the room numbering scheme follows some simple conventions. In our example,
      there are two kinds of patterns we want to find; here are some examples, together with
      their corresponding regular expression patterns:
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Yorktown patterns:</term>
          <listitem><para>20-001, 31-206, 04-123(Regular Expression Pattern:
            ##-[0-2]##)</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Hawthorne patterns:</term>
          <listitem><para>GN-K35, 1S-L07, 4N-B21 (Regular Expression Pattern:
            [G1-4][NS]-[A-Z]##)</para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist> </para>
    
    <para>There are several steps to develop and test a simple UIMA annotator.</para>
    
    <orderedlist spacing="compact"><listitem><para>Define the CAS types that the
      annotator will use.</para></listitem>
      
      <listitem><para>Generate the Java classes for these types.</para></listitem>
      
      <listitem><para>Write the actual annotator Java code.</para></listitem>
      
      <listitem><para>Create the Analysis Engine descriptor.</para></listitem>
      
      <listitem><para>Test the annotator. </para></listitem></orderedlist>
    
    <para>These steps are discussed in the next sections.</para>
    
    <section id="ugr.tug.aae.defining_types">
      <title>Defining Types</title>
      
      <para>The first step in developing an annotator is to define the CAS Feature Structure
        types that it creates. This is done in an XML file called a <emphasis>Type System
        Descriptor</emphasis>. UIMA defines basic primitive types such as
        Boolean, Byte, Short, Integer, Long, Float, and Double, as well as Arrays of these primitive
        types.  UIMA also defines the built-in types <literal>TOP</literal>, which is the root 
        of the type system, analogous to Object in Java; <literal>FSArray</literal>, which is 
        an array of Feature Structures (i.e. an array of instances of TOP); and
        <literal>Annotation</literal>, which we will discuss in more detail in this section.</para>
      
      <para>UIMA includes an Eclipse plug-in that will help you edit Type System
        Descriptors, so if you are using Eclipse you will not need to worry about the details of
        the XML syntax. See <olink targetdoc="&uima_docs_overview;"
          targetptr="ugr.ovv.eclipse_setup"/> for instructions on setting up Eclipse and
        installing the plugin.</para>
      
      <para>The Type System Descriptor for our annotator is located in the file
        <literal>descriptors/tutorial/ex1/TutorialTypeSystem.xml.</literal> (This
        and all other examples are located in the <literal>examples</literal> directory of
        the installation of the UIMA SDK, which can be imported into an Eclipse project for
        your convenience, as described in <olink targetdoc="&uima_docs_overview;"
          targetptr="ugr.ovv.eclipse_setup.example_code"/>.)</para>
      
      <para>In Eclipse, expand the <literal>uimaj-examples</literal> project in the
        Package Explorer view, and browse to the file
        <literal>descriptors/tutorial/ex1/TutorialTypeSystem.xml</literal>.
        Right-click on the file in the navigator and select Open With &rarr; Component
        Descriptor Editor. Once the editor opens, click on the <quote>Type System</quote>
        tab at the bottom of the editor window. You should see a view such as the
        following:</para>
      
      
      <screenshot>
 <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata scale="100" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;image002.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>Screenshot of editor for Type System Definitions</phrase></textobject>
      </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
      
      <para>Our annotator will need only one type &ndash;
        <literal>org.apache.uima.tutorial.RoomNumber</literal>. (We use the same
        namespace conventions as are used for Java classes.) Just as in Java, types have
        supertypes. The supertype is listed in the second column of the left table. In this
        case our RoomNumber annotation extends from the built-in type
        <literal>uima.tcas.Annotation</literal>.</para>
      
      <para>Descriptions can be included with types and features. In this example, there is a
        description associated with the <literal>building</literal> feature. To see it,
        hover the mouse over the feature.</para>
      
      <para>The bottom tab labeled <quote>Source</quote> will show you the XML source file
        associated with this descriptor.</para>
      
      <para>The built-in Annotation type declares three fields (called
        <emphasis>Features</emphasis> in CAS terminology).  The features <literal>begin</literal>
        and <literal>end</literal> store the character offsets of the span of text to which the 
        annotation refers.  The feature <literal>sofa</literal> (Subject of Analysis) indicates
        which document the begin and end offsets point into.  The <literal>sofa</literal> feature
        can be ignored for now since we assume in this tutorial that the CAS contains only one
        subject of analysis (document).</para>
      <para>Our RoomNumber type will inherit these three features from
        <literal>uima.tcas.Annotation</literal>, its supertype; they are not visible in
        this view because inherited features are not shown. One additional feature,
        <literal>building</literal>, is declared. It takes a String as its value. Instead
        of String, we could have declared the range-type of our feature to be any other CAS type
        (defined or built-in).</para>
      
      <para>If you are not using Eclipse, if you need to edit the type system, do so using any XML
        or text editor, directly. The following is the actual XML representation of the Type
        System displayed above in the editor:</para>
      
      
      <programlisting><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
  <typeSystemDescription xmlns="http://uima.apache.org/resourceSpecifier">
    <name>TutorialTypeSystem</name>
    <description>Type System Definition for the tutorial examples - 
        as of Exercise 1</description>
    <vendor>Apache Software Foundation</vendor>
    <version>1.0</version>
    <types>
      <typeDescription>
        <name>org.apache.uima.tutorial.RoomNumber</name>
        <description></description>
        <supertypeName>uima.tcas.Annotation</supertypeName>
        <features>
          <featureDescription>
            <name>building</name>
            <description>Building containing this room</description>
            <rangeTypeName>uima.cas.String</rangeTypeName>
          </featureDescription>
        </features>
      </typeDescription>
    </types>
  </typeSystemDescription>]]></programlisting>
      
    </section>
    
    <section id="ugr.tug.aae.generating_jcas_sources">
      <title>Generating Java Source Files for CAS Types</title>
      
      <para>When you save a descriptor that you have modified, the Component Descriptor
        Editor will automatically generate Java classes corresponding to the types that are
        defined in that descriptor (unless this has been disabled), using a utility called
        JCasGen. These Java classes will have the same name (including package) as the CAS
        types, and will have get and set methods for each of the features that you have
        defined.</para>
      
      <para>This feature is enabled/disabled using the UIMA menu pulldown (or the Eclipse
        Preferences &rarr; UIMA). If automatic running of JCasGen is not happening, please
        make sure the option is checked:</para>
      
      
      <screenshot>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="5.7in" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;image004.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>Screenshot of enabling automatic running of JCasGen</phrase></textobject>
      </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
      
      <para>The Java class for the example org.apache.uima.tutorial.RoomNumber type can
        be found in <literal>src/org/apache/uima/tutorial/RoomNumber.java</literal>
        . You will see how to use these generated classes in the next section.</para>
      
      <para>If you are not using the Component Descriptor Editor, you will need to generate
        these Java classes by using the <emphasis>JCasGen</emphasis> tool. JCasGen reads a
        Type System Descriptor XML file and generates the corresponding Java classes that
        you can then use in your annotator code. To launch JCasGen, run the jcasgen shell
        script located in the <literal>/bin</literal> directory of the UIMA SDK
        installation. This should launch a GUI that looks something like this:</para>
      
      
      <screenshot>
        <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="5.7in" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;image006.jpg"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject><phrase>Screenshot of JCasGen</phrase></textobject>
      </mediaobject>
</screenshot>
      
      <para>Use the <quote>Browse</quote> buttons to select your input file
        (TutorialTypeSystem.xml) and output directory (the root of the source tree into
        which you want the generated files placed). Then click the <quote>Go</quote>
        button. If the Type System Descriptor has no errors, new Java source files will be
        generated under the specified output directory.</para>
      
      <para>There are some additional options to choose from when running JCasGen; please
        refer to the <olink targetdoc="&uima_docs_tools;"
          targetptr="ugr.tools.jcasgen"/> for details.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="ugr.tug.aae.developing_annotator_code">
      <title>Developing Your Annotator Code</title>
      
      <para>Annotator implementations all implement a standard interface (AnalysisComponent), having several
        methods, the most important of which are:
        
        <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
          <listitem>
            <para><literal>initialize</literal>, </para>
          </listitem>
          
          <listitem>
            <para><literal>process</literal>, and </para>
          </listitem>
          
          <listitem>
            <para><literal>destroy</literal>. </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
      
      <para><literal>initialize</literal> is called by the framework once when it first creates an instance of the
        annotator class. <literal>process</literal> is called once per item being processed.
        <literal>destroy</literal> may be called by the application when it is done using your annotator. There is a 
        default implementation of this interface for annotators using the JCas, called JCasAnnotator_ImplBase, which 
        has implementations of all required methods except for the process method.</para>
      
      <para>Our annotator class extends the JCasAnnotator_ImplBase; most annotators that use the JCas will extend
        from this class, so they only have to implement the process method. This class is not restricted to handling
        just text; see <olink targetdoc="&uima_docs_tutorial_guides;" targetptr="ugr.tug.aas"/>.</para>
      
      <para>Annotators are not required to extend from the JCasAnnotator_ImplBase class; they may instead
        directly implement the AnalysisComponent interface, and provide all method implementations themselves.
        <footnote>
        <para>Note that AnalysisComponent is not specific to JCAS. There is a method getRequiredCasInterface()
          which the user would have to implement to return <literal>JCas.class</literal>. Then in the
          <literal>process(AbstractCas cas)</literal> method, they would need to typecast
          <literal>cas</literal> to type <literal>JCas</literal>.</para></footnote> This allows you to have
        your annotator inherit from some other superclass if necessary. If you would like to do this, see the Javadocs
        for JCasAnnotator for descriptions of the methods you must implement.</para>
      
      <para>Annotator classes need to be public, cannot be declared abstract, and must have public, 0-argument 
        constructors, so that they can be instantiated by the framework. <footnote>
        <para> Although Java classes in which you do not define any constructor will, by default, have a 0-argument
          constructor that doesn&apos;t do anything, a class in which you have defined at least one constructor does
          not get a default 0-argument constructor.</para> </footnote> .</para>
      
      <para>The class definition for our RoomNumberAnnotator implements the process method, and is shown here. You
        can find the source for this in the
        <literal>uimaj-examples/src/org/apache/uima/tutorial/ex1/RoomNumberAnnotator.java</literal> .
        <note>
        <para>In Eclipse, in the <quote>Package Explorer</quote> view, this will appear by default in the project
          <literal>uimaj-examples</literal>, in the folder <literal>src</literal>, in the package
          <literal>org.apache.uima.tutorial.ex1</literal>.</para></note> In Eclipse, open the
        RoomNumberAnnotator.java in the uimaj-examples project, under the src directory.</para>
      
      
      <programlisting>package org.apache.uima.tutorial.ex1;

import java.util.regex.Matcher;
import java.util.regex.Pattern;

import org.apache.uima.analysis_component.JCasAnnotator_ImplBase;
import org.apache.uima.jcas.JCas;
import org.apache.uima.tutorial.RoomNumber;

/**
 * Example annotator that detects room numbers using 
 * Java 1.4 regular expressions.
 */
public class RoomNumberAnnotator extends JCasAnnotator_ImplBase {
  private Pattern mYorktownPattern = 
        Pattern.compile("\\b[0-4]\\d-[0-2]\\d\\d\\b");

  private Pattern mHawthornePattern = 
        Pattern.compile("\\b[G1-4][NS]-[A-Z]\\d\\d\\b");

  public void process(JCas aJCas) {
    // Discussed Later
  }
}</programlisting>
      
      <para>The two Java class fields, mYorktownPattern and mHawthornePattern, hold regular expressions that
        will be used in the process method. Note that these two fields are part of the Java implementation of the
        annotator code, and not a part of the CAS type system. We are using the regular expression facility that is
        built into Java 1.4. It is not critical that you know the details of how this works, but if you are curious the
        details can be found in the Java API docs for the java.util.regex package.</para>
      
      <para>The only method that we are required to implement is <literal>process</literal>. This method is typically 
        called once for each document that is being analyzed. This method takes one argument, which is a JCas instance; 
        this holds the document to be analyzed and all of the analysis results. <footnote>
        <para>Version 1 of UIMA specified an additional parameter, the ResultSpecification. This provides a
          specification of which types and features are desired to be computed and "output" from this annotator. Its
          use is optional; many annotators ignore it.</para>
        <para> This parameter has been replaced by specific set/getResultSpecification() methods, which allow
          the annotator to receive a signal (a method call) when the result specification changes.</para>
        </footnote></para>
      
      
      <programlisting>public void process(JCas aJCas) {
  // get document text
  String docText = aJCas.getDocumentText();
  // search for Yorktown room numbers
  Matcher matcher = mYorktownPattern.matcher(docText);
  int pos = 0;
  while (matcher.find(pos)) {
    // found one - create annotation
    RoomNumber annotation = new RoomNumber(aJCas);
    annotation.setBegin(matcher.start());
    annotation.setEnd(matcher.end());
    annotation.setBuilding("Yorktown");
    annotation.addToIndexes();
    pos = matcher.end();
  }
  // search for Hawthorne room numbers
  matcher = mHawthornePattern.matcher(docText);
  pos = 0;
  while (matcher.find(pos)) {
    // found one - create annotation
    RoomNumber annotation = new RoomNumber(aJCas);
    annotation.setBegin(matcher.start());
    annotation.setEnd(matcher.end());
    annotation.setBuilding("Hawthorne");
    annotation.addToIndexes();
    pos = matcher.end();
  }
}</programlisting>
      
      <para>The Matcher class is part of the java.util.regex package and is used to find the room numbers in the
        document text. When we find one, recording the annotation is as simple as creating a new Java object and
        calling some set methods:</para>
      
      
      <programlisting>RoomNumber annotation = new RoomNumber(aJCas);
annotation.setBegin(matcher.start());
annotation.setEnd(matcher.end());
annotation.setBuilding("Yorktown");</programlisting>
      
      <para>The <literal>RoomNumber</literal> class was generated from the type system description by the
        Component Descriptor Editor or the JCasGen tool, as discussed in the previous section.</para>
      
      <para>Finally, we call <literal>annotation.addToIndexes()</literal> to add the new annotation to the
        indexes maintained in the CAS. By default, the CAS implementation used for analysis of text documents keeps
        an index of all annotations in their order from beginning to end of the document. Subsequent annotators or
        applications use the indexes to iterate over the annotations. </para>
      
      <note>
      <para> If you don&apos;t add the instance to the indexes, it cannot be retrieved by down-stream annotators,
        using the indexes. </para></note>
      
      <note>
      <para>You can also call <literal>addToIndexes()</literal> on Feature Structures that are not subtypes of
        <literal>uima.tcas.Annotation</literal>, but these will not be sorted in any particular way. If you want
        to specify a sort order, you can define your own custom indexes in the CAS: see <olink
          targetdoc="&uima_docs_ref;" targetptr="ugr.ref.cas"/> and <olink targetdoc="&uima_docs_ref;"
          targetptr="ugr.ref.xml.component_descriptor.aes.index"/> for details.</para></note>
      
      <para>We&apos;re almost ready to test the RoomNumberAnnotator. There is just one more step
        remaining.</para>
    </section>
    <section id="ugr.tug.aae.creating_xml_descriptor">
      <title>Creating the XML Descriptor</title>
      
      <para>The UIMA architecture requires that descriptive information about an
        annotator be represented in an XML file and provided along with the annotator class
        file(s) to the UIMA framework at run time. This XML file is called an
        <emphasis>Analysis Engine Descriptor</emphasis>. The descriptor includes:
        
        <itemizedlist><listitem><para>Name, description, version, and vendor</para>
          </listitem>
          
          <listitem><para>The annotator&apos;s inputs and outputs, defined in terms of
            the types in a Type System Descriptor</para></listitem>
          
          <listitem><para>Declaration of the configuration parameters that the
            annotator accepts </para></listitem></itemizedlist> </para>
      
      <para>The <emphasis>Component Descriptor Editor</emphasis> plugin, which we
        previously used to edit the Type System descriptor, can also be used to edit Analysis
        Engine Descriptors.</para>
      
      <para>A descriptor for our RoomNumberAnnotator is provided with the UIMA
        distribution under the name
        <literal>descriptors/tutorial/ex1/RoomNumberAnnotator.xml.</literal> To
        edit it in Eclipse, right-click on that file in the navigator and select Open With
        &rarr; Component Descriptor Editor.</para> <tip><para>In Eclipse, you can double
      click on the tab at the top of the Component Descriptor Editor&apos;s window
      identifying the currently selected editor, and the window will
      <quote>Maximize</quote>. Double click it again to restore the original size.</para>
      </tip>
      
      <para>If you are not using Eclipse, you will need to edit Analysis Engine descriptors
        manually. See <xref linkend="ugr.tug.aae.xml_intro_ae_descriptor"/> for an
        introduction to the Analysis Engine descriptor XML syntax. The remainder of this
        section assumes you are using the Component Descriptor Editor plug-in to edit the
        Analysis Engine descriptor.</para>
      
      <para>The Component Descriptor Editor consists of several tabbed pages; we will only
        need to use a few of them here. For more information on using this editor, see <olink
          targetdoc="&uima_docs_tools;" targetptr="ugr.tools.cde"/>.</para>
      
      <para>The initial page of the Component Descriptor Editor is the Overview page, which
        appears as follows:</para>
      
      
      <screenshot>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata width="5.7in" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;image008.jpg"/>
    </imageobject>
    <textobject><phrase>Screenshot of Component Descriptor Editor overview page</phrase>      
    </textobject>
  </mediaobject>
</screenshot>
      
      <para>This presents an overview of the RoomNumberAnnotator Analysis Engine (AE). The
        left side of the page shows that this descriptor is for a
        <emphasis>Primitive</emphasis> AE (meaning it consists of a single annotator),
        and that the annotator code is developed in Java. Also, it specifies the Java class
        that implements our logic (the code which was discussed in the previous section).
        Finally, on the right side of the page are listed some descriptive attributes of our
        annotator.</para>
      
      <para>The other two pages that need to be filled out are the Type System page and the
        Capabilities page. You can switch to these pages using the tabs at the bottom of the
        Component Descriptor Editor. In the tutorial, these are already filled out for
        you.</para>
      
      <para>The RoomNumberAnnotator will be using the TutorialTypeSystem we looked at in
        Section <xref linkend="ugr.tug.aae.defining_types"/>. To specify this, we add
        this type system to the Analysis Engine&apos;s list of Imported Type Systems, using
        the Type System page&apos;s right side panel, as shown here:</para>
      
      
      <screenshot>
   <mediaobject>
     <imageobject>
       <imagedata width="5.7in" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;image010.jpg"/>
     </imageobject>
     <textobject><phrase>Screenshot of CDE Type System page</phrase></textobject>
   </mediaobject>
 </screenshot>
      
      <para>On the Capabilities page, we define our annotator&apos;s inputs and outputs, in
        terms of the types in the type system. The Capabilities page is shown below:</para>
      
      
      <screenshot>
   <mediaobject>
     <imageobject>
       <imagedata width="5.3in" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;image012.jpg"/>
     </imageobject>
     <textobject><phrase>Screenshot of CDE Capabilities page</phrase></textobject>
   </mediaobject>
 </screenshot>
      
      <para>Although capabilities come in sets, having multiple sets is deprecated; here
        we&apos;re just using one set. The RoomNumberAnnotator is very simple. It requires
        no input types, as it operates directly on the document text -- which is supplied as a
        part of the CAS initialization (and which is always assumed to be present). It
        produces only one output type (RoomNumber), and it sets the value of the
        <literal>building</literal> feature on that type. This is all represented on the
        Capabilities page.</para>
      
      <para>The Capabilities page has two other parts for specifying languages and Sofas.
        The languages section allows you to specify which languages your Analysis Engine
        supports. The RoomNumberAnnotator happens to be language-independent, so we can
        leave this blank. The Sofas section allows you to specify the names of additional
        subjects of analysis. This capability and the Sofa Mappings at the bottom are
        advanced topics, described in <olink targetdoc="&uima_docs_tutorial_guides;"
          targetptr="ugr.tug.aas"/>. </para>
      
      <para>This is all of the information we need to provide for a simple annotator. If you
        want to peek at the XML that this tool saves you from having to write, click on the
        <quote>Source</quote> tab at the bottom to view the generated XML.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="ugr.tug.aae.testing_your_annotator">
      <title>Testing Your Annotator</title>
      
      <para>Having developed an annotator, we need a way to try it out on some example
        documents. The UIMA SDK includes a tool called the Document Analyzer that will allow
        us to do this. To run the Document Analyzer, execute the documentAnalyzer shell
        script that is in the <literal>bin</literal> directory of your UIMA SDK
        installation, or, if you are using the example Eclipse project, execute the
        <quote>UIMA Document Analyzer</quote> run configuration supplied with that
        project. (To do this, click on the menu bar Run &rarr; Run ... &rarr; and under Java
        Applications in the left box, click on UIMA Document Analyzer.)</para>
      
      <para>You should see a screen that looks like this:</para>
      
      
      <screenshot>
   <mediaobject>
     <imageobject>
       <imagedata width="5.7in" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;image014.jpg"/>
     </imageobject>
     <textobject><phrase>Screenshot of UIMA Document Analyzer GUI</phrase></textobject>
   </mediaobject>       
      </screenshot>
      
      <para>There are six options on this screen:</para>
      
      <orderedlist><listitem><para>Directory containing documents to analyze</para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>Directory where analysis results will be written</para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>The XML descriptor for the Analysis Engine (AE) you want to
          run</para></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>(Optional) an XML tag, within the input documents, that contains
          the text to be analyzed. For example, the value TEXT would cause the AE to only
          analyze the portion of the document enclosed within
          &lt;TEXT&gt;...&lt;/TEXT&gt; tags.</para></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>Language of the document </para></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>Character encoding </para></listitem></orderedlist>
      
      <para>Use the Browse button next to the third item to set the <quote>Location of AE XML
        Descriptor</quote> field to the descriptor we&apos;ve just been discussing
        &mdash;
        <literal>&lt;where-you-installed-uima-e.g.UIMA_HOME&gt; 
          /examples/descriptors/tutorial/ex1/RoomNumberAnnotator.xml</literal>
        . Set the other fields to the values shown in the screen shot above (which should be the
        default values if this is the first time you&apos;ve run the Document Analyzer). Then
        click the <quote>Run</quote> button to start processing.</para>
      
      <para>When processing completes, an <quote>Analysis Results</quote> window should
        appear.</para>
      
      
      <screenshot>
   <mediaobject>
     <imageobject>
       <imagedata width="3.5in" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;image016.jpg"/>
     </imageobject>
     <textobject><phrase>Screenshot of UIMA Document Analyzer Results GUI</phrase></textobject>
   </mediaobject>       
      </screenshot>
      
      <para>Make sure <quote>Java Viewer</quote> is selected as the Results Display
        Format, and <emphasis role="bold">double-click</emphasis> on the document
        UIMASummerSchool2003.txt to view the annotations that were discovered. The view
        should look something like this:</para>
      
      
      <screenshot>
   <mediaobject>
     <imageobject>
       <imagedata width="5.7in" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;image018.jpg"/>
     </imageobject>
     <textobject><phrase>Screenshot of UIMA CAS Annotation Viewer GUI</phrase></textobject>
   </mediaobject>       
      </screenshot>
      
      <para>You can click the mouse on one of the highlighted annotations to see a list of all
        its features in the frame on the right.</para> <note><para>The legend will only show
      those types which have at least one instance in the CAS, and are declared as outputs in the
      capabilities section of the descriptor (see <xref
        linkend="ugr.tug.aae.creating_xml_descriptor"/>. </para></note>
      
      <para>You can use the DocumentAnalyzer to test any UIMA annotator
        &mdash; just make sure that the annotator&apos;s classes are in the class
        path.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section id="ugr.tug.aae.configuration_logging">
    <title>Configuration and Logging</title>
    
    <section id="ugr.tug.aae.configuration_parameters">
      <title>Configuration Parameters</title>
      
      <para>The example RoomNumberAnnotator from the previous section used hardcoded
        regular expressions and location names, which is obviously not very flexible. For
        example, you might want to have the patterns of room numbers be supplied by a
        configuration parameter, rather than having to redo the annotator&apos;s Java code
        to add additional patterns. Rather than add a new hardcoded regular expression for a
        new pattern, a better solution is to use configuration parameters.</para>
      
      <para>UIMA allows annotators to declare configuration parameters in their
        descriptors. The descriptor also specifies default values for the parameters,
        though these can be overridden at runtime.</para>
      
      <section id="ugr.tug.aae.declaring_parameters_in_the_descriptor">
        <title>Declaring Parameters in the Descriptor</title>
        
        <para>The example descriptor
          <literal>descriptors/tutorial/ex2/RoomNumberAnnotator.xml</literal> is
          the same as the descriptor from the previous section except that information has
          been filled in for the Parameters and Parameter Settings pages of the Component
          Descriptor Editor.</para>
        
        <para>First, in Eclipse, open example two&apos;s RoomNumberAnnotator in the
          Component Descriptor Editor, and then go to the Parameters page (click on the
          parameters tab at the bottom of the window), which is shown below:</para>
        
        
        <screenshot>
   <mediaobject>
     <imageobject>
       <imagedata width="5.7in" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;image020.jpg"/>
     </imageobject>
     <textobject><phrase>Screenshot of UIMA Component Descriptor Editor (CDE) Parameters page</phrase></textobject>
   </mediaobject>       
      </screenshot>
        
        <para>Two parameters &ndash; Patterns and Locations -- have been declared. In this
          screen shot, the mouse (not shown) is hovering over Patterns to show its
          description in the small popup window. Every parameter has the following
          information associated with it:</para>
        
        <itemizedlist><listitem><para>name &ndash; the name by which the annotator code
          refers to the parameter</para></listitem>
          
          <listitem><para>description &ndash; a natural language description of the
            intent of the parameter</para></listitem>
          
          <listitem><para>type &ndash; the data type of the parameter&apos;s value
            &ndash; must be one of String, Integer, Float, or Boolean.</para></listitem>
          
          <listitem><para>multiValued &ndash; true if the parameter can take
            multiple-values (an array), false if the parameter takes only a single value.
            Shown above as <literal>Multi</literal>.</para></listitem>
          
          <listitem><para>mandatory &ndash; true if a value must be provided for the
            parameter. Shown above as <literal>Req</literal> (for required). </para>
          </listitem></itemizedlist>
        
        <para>Both of our parameters are mandatory and accept an array of Strings as their
          value.</para>
        
        <para>Next, default values are assigned to the parameters on the Parameter Settings
          page:</para>
        
        
        <screenshot>
   <mediaobject>
     <imageobject>
       <imagedata width="5.7in" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;image022.jpg"/>
     </imageobject>
     <textobject><phrase>Screenshot of UIMA Component Descriptor Editor (CDE) Parameter Settings page</phrase></textobject>
   </mediaobject>       
      </screenshot>
        
        <para>Here the <quote>Patterns</quote> parameter is selected, and the right pane
          shows the list of values for this parameter, in this case the regular expressions
          that match particular room numbering conventions. Notice the third pattern is
          new, for matching the style of room numbers in the third building, which has room
          numbers such as <literal>J2-A11</literal>.</para>
      </section>
      <section id="ugr.tug.aae.accessing_parameter_values_from_annotator">
        <title>Accessing Parameter Values from the Annotator Code</title>
        
        <para>The class
          <literal>org.apache.uima.tutorial.ex2.RoomNumberAnnotator</literal> has
          overridden the initialize method. The initialize method is called by the UIMA
          framework when the annotator is instantiated, so it is a good place to read
          configuration parameter values. The default initialize method does nothing with
          configuration parameters, so you have to override it. To see the code in Eclipse,
          switch to the src folder, and open
          <literal>org.apache.uima.tutorial.ex2</literal>. Here is the method
          body:</para>
        
        
        <programlisting>/**
* @see AnalysisComponent#initialize(UimaContext)
*/
public void initialize(UimaContext aContext) 
        throws ResourceInitializationException {
  super.initialize(aContext);
  
  // Get config. parameter values  
  String[] patternStrings = 
        (String[]) aContext.getConfigParameterValue("Patterns");
  mLocations = 
        (String[]) aContext.getConfigParameterValue("Locations");

  // compile regular expressions
  mPatterns = new Pattern[patternStrings.length];
  for (int i = 0; i &lt; patternStrings.length; i++) {
    mPatterns[i] = Pattern.compile(patternStrings[i]);
  }
}</programlisting>
        
        <para>Configuration parameter values are accessed through the UimaContext. As you
          will see in subsequent sections of this chapter, the UimaContext is the
          annotator&apos;s access point for all of the facilities provided by the UIMA
          framework &ndash; for example logging and external resource access.</para>
        
        <para>The UimaContext&apos;s <literal>getConfigParameterValue</literal>
          method takes the name of the parameter as an argument; this must match one of the
          parameters declared in the descriptor. The return value of this method is a Java
          Object, whose type corresponds to the declared type of the parameter. It is up to the
          annotator to cast it to the appropriate type, String[] in this case.</para>
        
        <para>If there is a problem retrieving the parameter values, the framework throws an
          exception. Generally annotators don&apos;t handle these, and just let them
          propagate up.</para>
        
        <para>To see the configuration parameters working, run the Document Analyzer
          application and select the descriptor
          <literal>examples/descriptors/tutorial/ex2/RoomNumberAnnotator.xml</literal>
          . In the example document <literal>WatsonConferenceRooms.txt</literal>, you
          should see some examples of Hawthorne II room numbers that would not have been
          detected by the ex1 version of RoomNumberAnnotator.</para>
      </section>
      
      <section id="ugr.tug.aae.supporting_reconfiguration">
        <title>Supporting Reconfiguration</title>
        
        <para>If you take a look at the Javadocs (located in the <ulink
            url="api/index.html">docs/api</ulink> directory) for
          <literal>org.apache.uima.analysis_component.AnaysisComponent</literal>
          (which our annotator implements indirectly through JCasAnnotator_ImplBase),
          you will see that there is a reconfigure() method, which is called by the containing
          application through the UIMA framework, if the configuration parameter values
          are changed.</para>
        
        <para>The AnalysisComponent_ImplBase class provides a default implementation
          that just calls the annotator&apos;s destroy method followed by its initialize
          method. This works fine for our annotator. The only situation in which you might
          want to override the default reconfigure() is if your annotator has very expensive
          initialization logic, and you don&apos;t want to reinitialize everything if just
          one configuration parameter has changed. In that case, you can provide a more
          intelligent implementation of reconfigure() for your annotator.</para>
        
      </section>
      
      <section id="ugr.tug.aae.configuration_parameter_groups">
        <title>Configuration Parameter Groups</title>
        
        <para>For annotators with many sets of configuration parameters, UIMA supports
          organizing them into groups. It is possible to define a parameter with the same name
          in multiple groups; one common use for this is for annotators that can process
          documents in several languages and which want to have different parameter
          settings for the different languages.</para>
        
        <para>The syntax for defining parameter groups in your descriptor is fairly
          straightforward &ndash; see <olink targetdoc="&uima_docs_ref;"
            targetptr="ugr.ref.xml.component_descriptor"/> for details. Values of
          parameters defined within groups are accessed through the two-argument version
          of <literal>UimaContext.getConfigParameterValue</literal>, which takes
          both the group name and the parameter name as its arguments.</para>
      </section>
    </section>
    
    <section id="ugr.tug.aae.logging">
      <title>Logging</title>
      
      <para>The UIMA SDK provides a logging facility, which is very similar to the
        java.util.logging.Logger class that was introduced in Java 1.4.</para>
      
      <para>In the Java architecture, each logger instance is associated with a name. By
        convention, this name is often the fully qualified class name of the component
        issuing the logging call. The name can be referenced in a configuration file when
        specifying which kinds of log messages to actually log, and where they should
        go.</para>
      
      <para>The UIMA framework supports this convention using the
        <literal>UimaContext</literal> object. If you access a logger instance using
        <literal>getContext().getLogger()</literal> within an Annotator, the logger
        name will be the fully qualified name of the Annotator implementation class.</para>
      
      <para>Here is an example from the process method of
        <literal>org.apache.uima.tutorial.ex2.RoomNumberAnnotator</literal>:
        
        
        <programlisting>getContext().getLogger().log(Level.FINEST,"Found: " + annotation);</programlisting>
        </para>
      
      <para>The first argument to the log method is the level of the log output. Here, a value of
        FINEST indicates that this is a highly-detailed tracing message. While useful for
        debugging, it is likely that real applications will not output log messages at this
        level, in order to improve their performance. Other defined levels, from lowest to
        highest importance, are FINER, FINE, CONFIG, INFO, WARNING, and SEVERE.</para>
      
      <para>If no logging configuration file is provided (see next section), the Java
        Virtual Machine defaults would be used, which typically set the level to INFO and
        higher messages, and direct output to the console.</para>
      
      <para>If you specify the standard UIMA SDK <literal>Logger.properties,</literal>
        the output will be directed to a file named uima.log, in the current working directory
        (often the <quote>project</quote> directory when running from Eclipse, for
        instance).</para> <note><para>When using Eclipse, the uima.log file, if written
      into the Eclipse workspace in the project uimaj-examples, for example, may not appear
      in the Eclipse package explorer view until you right-click the uimaj-examples project
      with the mouse, and select <quote>Refresh</quote>. This operation refreshes the
      Eclipse display to conform to what may have changed on the file system. Also, you can set
      the Eclipse preferences for the workspace to automatically refresh (Window &rarr;
      Preferences &rarr; General &rarr; Workspace, then click the <quote>refresh
      automatically</quote> checkbox.</para></note>
      
      <section id="ugr.tug.aae.logging.configuring">
        <title>Specifying the Logging Configuration</title>
        
        <para>The standard UIMA logger uses the underlying Java 1.4 logging mechanism. You
          can use the APIs that come with that to configure the logging. In addition, the
          standard Java 1.4 logging initialization mechanisms will look for a Java System
          Property named <literal>java.util.logging.config.file</literal> and if
          found, will use the value of this property as the name of a standard
          <quote>properties</quote> file, for setting the logging level. Please refer to
          the Java 1.4. documentation for more information on the format and use of this
          file.</para>
        
        <para>Two sample logging specification property files can be found in the UIMA_HOME
          directory where the UIMA SDK is installed:
          <literal>config/Logger.properties</literal>, and
          <literal>config/FileConsoleLogger.properties</literal>. These specify the same
          logging, except the first logs just to a file, while the second logs both to a file and
          to the console. You can edit these files, or create additional ones, as described
          below, to change the logging behavior.</para>
        
        <para>When running your own Java application, you can specify the location of the
          logging configuration file on your Java command line by setting the Java system
          property <literal>java.util.logging.config.file</literal> to be the logging
          configuration filename. This file specification can be either absolute or
          relative to the working directory. For example:
          
          
          <programlisting><?db-font-size 65% ?>java "-Djava.util.logging.config.file=C:/Program Files/apache-uima/config/Logger.properties"</programlisting>
          <note><para>In a shell script, you can use environment variables such as
          UIMA_HOME if convenient.</para></note> </para>
               
        <para>If you are using Eclipse to launch your application, you can set this property
          in the VM arguments section of the Arguments tab of the run configuration screen. If
          you&apos;ve set an environment variable UIMA_HOME, you could for example, use the
          string:
          <literal>"-Djava.util.logging.config.file=${env_var:UIMA_HOME}/config/Logger.properties".</literal>
          </para>
        
        <para>If you running the .bat or .sh files in the UIMA SDK's <literal>bin</literal> directory, you can specify the location of your
           logger configuration file by setting the <literal>UIMA_LOGGER_CONFIG_FILE</literal> environment variable prior to running the script,
           for example (on Windows): 

           <programlisting><?db-font-size 70% ?>set UIMA_LOGGER_CONFIG_FILE=C:/myapp/MyLogger.properties</programlisting>        
        </para>        
      </section>
      
      <section id="ugr.tug.aae.logging.setting_logging_levels">
        <title>Setting Logging Levels</title>
        
        <para>Within the logging control file, the default global logging level specifies
          which kinds of events are logged across all loggers. For any given facility this
          global level can be overridden by a facility specific level. Multiple handlers are
          supported. This allows messages to be directed to a log file, as well as to a
          <quote>console</quote>. Note that the ConsoleHandler also has a separate level
          setting to limit messages printed to the console. For example: <literal>.level=
          INFO</literal> </para>
        
        <para>The properties file can change where the log is written, as well.</para>
        
        <para>Facility specific properties allow different logging for each class, as
          well. For example, to set the com.xyz.foo logger to only log SEVERE messages:
          <literal>com.xyz.foo.level = SEVERE</literal></para>
        
        <para>If you have a sample annotator in the package
          <literal>org.apache.uima.SampleAnnotator</literal> you can set the log level
          by specifying: <literal>org.apache.uima.SampleAnnotator.level =
          ALL</literal></para>
        
        <para>There are other logging controls; for a full discussion, please read the
          contents of the <literal>Logger.properties</literal> file and the Java
          specification for logging in Java 1.4.</para>
      </section>
      
      <section id="ugr.tug.aae.logging.output_format">
        <title>Format of logging output</title>
        
        <para>The logging output is formatted by handlers specified in the properties file
          for configuring logging, described above. The default formatter that comes with
          the UIMA SDK formats logging output as follows:</para>
        
        <para><literal>Timestamp - threadID: sourceInfo: Message level:
          message</literal></para>
        
        <para> Here&apos;s an example:</para>
        
        <para><literal>7/12/04 2:15:35 PM - 10:
          org.apache.uima.util.TestClass.main(62): INFO: You are not logged
          in!</literal></para>
      </section>
      
      <section id="ugr.tug.aae.logging.meaning_of_severity_levels">
        <title>Meaning of the logging severity levels</title>
        
        <para>These levels are defined by the Java logging framework, which was
          incorporated into Java as of the 1.4 release level. The levels are defined in the
          Javadocs for java.util.logging.Level, and include both logging and tracing
          levels:
          <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
            <listitem><para>OFF is a special level that can be used to turn off
              logging.</para></listitem>
            
            <listitem><para>ALL indicates that all messages should be logged. </para>
            </listitem>
            
            <listitem><para>CONFIG is a message level for configuration messages. These
              would typically occur once (during configuration) in methods like
              <literal>initialize()</literal>. </para></listitem>
            
            <listitem><para>INFO is a message level for informational messages, for
              example, connected to server IP: 192.168.120.12 </para></listitem>
            
            <listitem><para>WARNING is a message level indicating a potential
              problem.</para></listitem>
            
            <listitem><para>SEVERE is a message level indicating a serious
              failure.</para></listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>
        
        <para> Tracing levels, typically used for debugging:
          <itemizedlist>
            
            <listitem><para>FINE is a message level providing tracing information,
              typically at a collection level (messages occurring once per collection).
              </para></listitem>
            
            <listitem><para>FINER indicates a fairly detailed tracing message,
              typically at a document level (once per document).</para></listitem>
            
            <listitem><para>FINEST indicates a highly detailed tracing message. </para>
            </listitem></itemizedlist></para>
      </section>
      
      <section id="ugr.tug.aae.logging.using_outside_of_an_annotator">
        <title>Using the logger outside of an annotator</title>
        
        <para>An application using UIMA may want to log its messages using the same logging
          framework. This can be done by getting a reference to the UIMA logger, as follows:
          
          
          <programlisting>Logger logger = UIMAFramework.getLogger(TestClass.class);</programlisting>
          </para>
        
        <para>The optional class argument allows filtering by class (if the log handler
          supports this). If not specified, the name of the returned logger instance is
          <quote>org.apache.uima</quote>.</para>
      </section>
      
      <section id="ugr.tug.aae.logging.change_logger_implementation">
        <title>Changing the underlying UIMA logging implementation</title>
        
        <para>By default the UIMA framework use, under the hood of the UIMA Logger interface, the Java logging framework 
        to do logging. But it is possible to change the logging implementation that UIMA use from Java logging to 
        an arbitrary logging system when specifying the system property  
          <programlisting>-Dorg.apache.uima.logger.class=&lt;loggerClass></programlisting>
        when the UIMA framework is started.
        </para>
        <para>
          The specified logger class must be available in the classpath and have to implement the 
          <code>org.apache.uima.util.Logger</code> interface. 
        </para>
        
        <para>
          UIMA also provides a logging implementation that use Apache Log4j instead of Java logging. To
          use Log4j you have to provide the Log4j jars in the classpath and your application 
          must specify the logging configuration as shown below. 
          <programlisting><?db-font-size 80% ?>-Dorg.apache.uima.logger.class=&lt;org.apache.uima.util.impl.Log4jLogger_impl></programlisting>
        </para>
      </section>
      
      
    </section>
  </section>  
  <section id="ugr.tug.aae.building_aggregates">
    <title>Building Aggregate Analysis Engines</title>
    
    <section id="ugr.tug.aae.combining_annotators">
      <title>Combining Annotators</title>
      
      <para>The UIMA SDK makes it very easy to combine any sequence of Analysis Engines to
        form an <emphasis>Aggregate Analysis Engine</emphasis>. This is done through an
        XML descriptor; no Java code is required!</para>
      
      <para>If you go to the <literal>examples/descriptors/tutorial/ex3</literal>
        folder (in Eclipse, it&apos;s in your uimaj-examples project, under the
        <literal>descriptors/tutorial/ex3</literal> folder), you will find a
        descriptor for a TutorialDateTime annotator. This annotator detects dates and
        times (and also sentences and words). To see what this annotator can do, try it out
        using the Document Analyzer. If you are curious as to how this annotator works, the
        source code is included, but it is not necessary to understand the code at this
        time.</para>
      
      <para>We are going to combine the TutorialDateTime annotator with the
        RoomNumberAnnotator to create an aggregate Analysis Engine. This is illustrated
        in the following figure:
        
        <figure id="ugr.tug.aae.fig.combining_annotators">
          <title>Combining Annotators to form an Aggregate Analysis Engine</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="5.7in" format="PNG"
                fileref="&imgroot;image024.png"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject> <phrase>Combining Annotators to form an Aggregate Analysis
              Engine</phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure> </para>
      
      <para>The descriptor that does this is named
        <literal>RoomNumberAndDateTime.xml</literal>, which you can open in the
        Component Descriptor Editor plug-in. This is in the uimaj-examples project in the
        folder <literal>descriptors/tutorial/ex3</literal>. </para>
      
      <para>The <quote>Aggregate</quote> page of the Component Descriptor Editor is
        used to define which components make up the aggregate. A screen shot is shown below.
        (If you are not using Eclipse, see <xref
          linkend="ugr.tug.aae.xml_intro_ae_descriptor"/> for the actual XML syntax
        for Aggregate Analysis Engine Descriptors.)</para>
      
      
        <screenshot>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
      <imagedata width="5.7in" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;image026.jpg"/>
    </imageobject>
    <textobject>
      <phrase>Aggregate page of the Component Descriptor Editor (CDE)</phrase>
    </textobject>
  </mediaobject>
</screenshot>
        
      <para>On the left side of the screen is the list of component engines that make up the
        aggregate &ndash; in this case, the TutorialDateTime annotator and the
        RoomNumberAnnotator. To add a component, you can click the <quote>Add</quote>
        button and browse to its descriptor. You can also click the <quote>Find AE</quote>
        button and search for an Analysis Engine in your Eclipse workspace.
        <note><para>The <quote>AddRemote</quote> button is used for adding components
        which run remotely (for example, on another machine using a remote networking
        connection). This capability is described in section <olink
          targetdoc="&uima_docs_tutorial_guides;"
          targetptr="ugr.tug.application.how_to_call_a_uima_service"/>,</para>
        </note> </para>
      
      <para>The order of the components in the left pane does not imply an order of
        execution. The order of execution, or <quote>flow</quote> is determined in the
        <quote>Component Engine Flow</quote> section on the right. UIMA supports
        different types of algorithms (including user-definable) for determining the
        flow. Here we pick the simplest: <literal>FixedFlow</literal>. We have chosen to
        have the RoomNumberAnnotator execute first, although in this case it
        doesn&apos;t really matter, since the RoomNumber and DateTime annotators do not
        have any dependencies on one another.</para>
      
      <para>If you look at the <quote>Type System</quote> page of the Component
        Descriptor Editor, you will see that it displays the type system but is not
        editable. The Type System of an Aggregate Analysis Engine is automatically
        computed by merging the Type Systems of all of its components.</para>
      
      <warning><para>If the components have different definitions for the same type name,
        The Component Descriptor Editor will show a warning.  It is possible to continue past
        this warning, in which case your aggregate's type system will have the correct
        <quote>merged</quote>
        type definition that contains all of the features defined on that type by all of your
        components.  However, it is not recommended to use this feature in conjunction with JCAS,
        since the JCAS Java Class definitions cannot be so easily merged.  See
        <olink
          targetdoc="&uima_docs_ref;"
          targetptr="ugr.ref.jcas.merging_types_from_other_specs"/> for more information.
      </para></warning>
      
      <para>The Capabilities page is where you explicitly declare the aggregate Analysis
        Engine&apos;s inputs and outputs. Sofas and Languages are described later.
        
          
          <screenshot>
     <mediaobject>
       <imageobject>
         <imagedata width="5.7in" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;image028.jpg"/>
       </imageobject>
       <textobject><phrase>Screen shot of the Capabilities page of the Component Descriptor Editor
       </phrase></textobject>
     </mediaobject>
   </screenshot>
          </para>
        <para>Note that it is not automatically assumed that all outputs of each component
          Analysis Engine (AE) are passed through as outputs of the aggregate AE. In this
          case, for example, we have decided to suppress the Word and Sentence annotations
          that are produced by the TutorialDateTime annotator.</para>
        
        <para>You can run this AE using the Document Analyzer in the same way that you run any
          other AE. Just select the <literal>examples/descriptors/tutorial/ex3/
          RoomNumberAndDateTime.xml</literal> descriptor and click the Run button. You
          should see that RoomNumbers, Dates, and Times are all shown but that Words and
          Sentences are not:</para>
        
        
        <screenshot>
     <mediaobject>
       <imageobject>
         <imagedata width="5.7in" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;image030.jpg"/>
       </imageobject>
       <textobject><phrase>Screen shot results of running the Document Analyzer
       </phrase></textobject>
     </mediaobject>
   </screenshot>
        
    </section>
    
    <section id="ugr.tug.aae.aaes_can_contain_cas_consumers">
      <title>AEs can also contain CAS Consumers</title>
      
      <para>In addition to aggregating Analysis Engines, Aggregates can also contain CAS
        Consumers (see <olink targetdoc="&uima_docs_tutorial_guides;"
          targetptr="ugr.tug.cpe"/>, or even a mixture of these components with regular
        Analysis Engines. The UIMA Examples has an example of an Aggregate which contains
        both an analysis engine and a CAS consumer, in
        <literal>examples/descriptors/MixedAggregate.xml.</literal></para>
      
      <para>Analysis Engines support the <literal>collectionProcessComplete</literal>
        method, which is particularly important for many CAS Consumers.  If
        an application (or a Collection Processing Engine) calls 
        <literal>collectionProcessComplete</literal> no an aggregate, the framework
        will deliver that call to all of the components of the aggregate.  If you use
        one of the built-in flow types (fixedFlow or capabilityLanguageFlow), then the
        order specified in that flow will be the same order in which the
        <literal>collectionProcessComplete</literal> calls are made to the components.
        If a custom flow is used, then the calls will be made in arbitrary order.
      </para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="ugr.tug.aae.reading_results_previous_annotators">
      <title>Reading the Results of Previous Annotators</title>
      
      <para>So far, we have been looking at annotators that look directly at the document text. However, annotators
        can also use the results of other annotators. One useful thing we can do at this point is look for the
        co-occurrence of a Date, a RoomNumber, and two Times &ndash; and annotate that as a Meeting.</para>
      
      <para>The CAS maintains <emphasis>indexes</emphasis> of annotations, and from an index you can obtain an
        iterator that allows you to step through all annotations of a particular type. Here&apos;s some example code
        that would iterate over all of the TimeAnnot annotations in the JCas:
        
        
        <programlisting>FSIndex timeIndex = aJCas.getAnnotationIndex(TimeAnnot.type);
Iterator timeIter = timeIndex.iterator();   
while (timeIter.hasNext()) {
  TimeAnnot time = (TimeAnnot)timeIter.next();

  //do something
}</programlisting></para>
      
      <note>
      <para>You can also use the method
        <literal>JCAS.getJFSIndexRepository().getAllIndexedFS(YourClass.type)</literal>, which returns an iterator
        over all instances of <literal>YourClass</literal> in no particular order. This can be useful for types
        that are not subtypes of the built-in Annotation type and which therefore have no default sort order.</para>
        
      <para>Also, if you've defined your own custom index as described in <olink targetdoc="&uima_docs_ref;"
          targetptr="ugr.ref.xml.component_descriptor.aes.index"/>, you can get an iterator over that
        specific index by calling <literal>aJCas.getJFSIndexRepository().getIndex(label)</literal>.
        The <literal>getIndex(...)</literal> method has also a 2 argument form; the second argument, 
      if used, specialized the index to subtype of the type the index was declared to index.  For instance,
      if you defined an index called "allEvents" over the type <literal>Event</literal>, and wanted 
      to get an index over just a particular subtype of event, say, <literal>TimeEvent</literal>,
      you can ask for that index using 
        <literal>aJCas.getJFSIndexRepository().getIndex("allEvents", TimeEvent.type)</literal>.</para></note>
      
      <para>Now that we&apos;ve explained the basics, let&apos;s take a look at the process method for
        <literal>org.apache.uima.tutorial.ex4.MeetingAnnotator</literal>. Since we&apos;re looking for a
        combination of a RoomNumber, a Date, and two Times, there are four nested iterators. (There&apos;s surely a
        better algorithm for doing this, but to keep things simple we&apos;re just going to look at every combination
        of the four items.)</para>
      
      <para>For each combination of the four annotations, we compute the span of text that includes all of them, and
        then we check to see if that span is smaller than a <quote>window</quote> size, a configuration parameter.
        There are also some checks to make sure that we don&apos;t annotate the same span of text multiple times. If all
        the checks pass, we create a Meeting annotation over the whole span. There&apos;s really nothing to
        it!</para>
      
      <para>The XML descriptor, located in
        <literal>examples/descriptors/tutorial/ex4/MeetingAnnotator.xml</literal> , is also very
        straightforward. An important difference from previous descriptors is that this is the first annotator
        we&apos;ve discussed that has input requirements. This can be seen on the <quote>Capabilities</quote>
        page of the Component Descriptor Editor:</para>
      
      
      <screenshot>
     <mediaobject>
       <imageobject>
         <imagedata width="5.7in" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;image032.jpg"/>
       </imageobject>
       <textobject><phrase>Screen shot of Capabilities page of the Component Descriptor Editor
       </phrase></textobject>
     </mediaobject>
   </screenshot>
      
      <para>If we were to run the MeetingAnnotator on its own, it wouldn&apos;t detect anything because it
        wouldn&apos;t have any input annotations to work with. The required input annotations can be produced by the
        RoomNumber and DateTime annotators. So, we create an aggregate Analysis Engine containing these two
        annotators, followed by the Meeting annotator. This aggregate is illustrated in <xref
          linkend="ugr.tug.aae.fig.aggregate_for_meeting_annotator"/>. The descriptor for this is in
        <literal>examples/descriptors/tutorial/ex4/MeetingDetectorAE.xml</literal> . Give it a try in the
        Document Analyzer.
        
        <figure id="ugr.tug.aae.fig.aggregate_for_meeting_annotator">
          <title>An Aggregate Analysis Engine where an internal component uses output from previous
            engines</title>
          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata width="5.7in" format="PNG" fileref="&imgroot;image034.png"/>
            </imageobject>
            <textobject><phrase>An Aggregate Analysis Engine where an internal component uses output from
              previous engines. </phrase>
            </textobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure> </para>
      
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section id="ugr.tug.aae.other_examples">
    <title>Other examples</title>
    
    <para>The UIMA SDK include several other examples you may find interesting,
      including</para>
    
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem><para>SimpleTokenAndSentenceAnnotator &ndash; a simple tokenizer and
        sentence annotator.</para></listitem>
      
      <listitem><para>XmlDetagger &ndash; A multi-sofa annotator that does XML
        detagging. Multiple Sofas (Subjects of Analysis) are described in a later &ndash;
        see <olink targetdoc="&uima_docs_tutorial_guides;"
          targetptr="ugr.tug.mvs"/>.  Reads XML data from the input Sofa
        (named "xmlDocument"); this data can be stored in the CAS as a string or array, or it can
        be a URI to a remote file. The XML is parsed using the JVM's default parser, and the
        plain-text content is written to a new sofa called "plainTextDocument".</para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem><para>PersonTitleDBWriterCasConsumer &ndash; a sample CAS Consumer
        which populates a relational database with some annotations. It uses JDBC and in this
        example, hooks up with the Open Source Apache Derby database. </para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  
  <section id="ugr.tug.aae.additional_topics">
    <title>Additional Topics</title>
    
    <section id="ugr.tug.aae.contract_for_annotator_methods">
      <title>Contract: Annotator Methods Called by the Framework</title>
      <titleabbrev>Annotator Methods</titleabbrev>
      
      <para>The UIMA framework ensures that an Annotator instance is called by only one
        thread at a time.  An instance never has to worry about running some method on one 
        thread, and then asynchronously being called using another thread. This approach 
        simplifies the design of annotators &ndash; they do not have to be designed to support
        multi-threading. When multiple threading is wanted, for performance, multiple
        instances of the Annotator are created, each one running on just one thread.</para>
      
      <para>The following table defines the methods called by the framework, when they are
        called, and the requirements annotator implementations must follow.</para>
      
      <informaltable frame="all">
        <tgroup cols="3" colsep="1" rowsep="1">
          <colspec colname="c1"/>
          <colspec colname="c2"/>
          <colspec colname="c3"/>
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry align="center">Method</entry>
              <entry align="center">When Called by Framework</entry>
              <entry align="center">Requirements</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>initialize</entry>
              <entry>Typically only called once, when instance is created. Can be called
                again if application does a reinitialize call and the default behavior
                isn't overridden (the default behavior for reinitialize is to call
                <literal>destroy</literal> followed by
                <literal>initialize</literal></entry>
              <entry>Normally does one-time initialization, including reading of
                configuration parameters. If the application changes the parameters, it
                can call initialize to have the annotator re-do its
                initialization.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>typeSystemInit</entry>
              <entry>Called before <literal>process</literal> whenever the type system
                in the CAS being passed in differs from what was previously passed in a
                <literal>process</literal> call (and called for the first CAS passed in,
                too). The Type System being passed to an annotator only changes in the case of
                remote annotators that are active as servers, receiving possibly
                different type systems to operate on.</entry>
              <entry>Typically, users of JCas do not implement any method for this. An
                annotator can use this call to read the CAS type system and setup any instance
                variables that make accessing the types and features convenient.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>process</entry>
              <entry>Called once for each CAS. Called by the application if not using
                Collection Processing Manager (CPM); the application calls the process
                method on the analysis engine, which is then delegated by the framework to
                all the annotators in the engine. For Collection Processing application,
                the CPM calls the process method. If the application creates and manages
                your own Collection Processing Engine via API calls (see Javadocs), the
                application calls this on the Collection Processing Engine, and it is
                delegated by the framework to the components.</entry>
              <entry>Process the CAS, adding and/or modifying elements in it</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>destroy</entry>
              <entry>This method can be called by applications, and is also called by the
                Collection Processing Manager framework when the collection processing
                completes. If called by an application on the Engine object, it is
                propagated to all contained annotators.</entry>
              <entry>An annotator should release all resources, close files, close
                database connections, etc., and return to a state where another initialize
                call could be received to restart. Typically, after a destroy call, no
                further calls will be made to an annotator instance.</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>reconfigure</entry>
              <entry><para>This method is never called by the framework, unless an
                application calls it on the Engine object &ndash; in which case it the
                framework propagates it to all annotators contained in the Engine.</para>
                <para>Its purpose is to signal that the configuration parameters have
                  changed.</para></entry>
              <entry>A default implementation of this calls destroy, followed by
                initialize. This is the only case where initialize would be called more than
                once. Users should implement whatever logic is needed to return the
                annotator to an initialized state, including re-reading the
                configuration parameter data.</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </informaltable>
      
    </section>
    
    <section id="ugr.tug.aae.reporting_errors_from_annotators">
      <title>Reporting errors from Annotators</title>
      
      <para>There are two broad classes of errors that can occur: recoverable and
        unrecoverable. Because Annotators are often expected to process very large numbers
        of artifacts (for example, text documents), they should be written to recover where
        possible.</para>
      
      <para>For example, if an upstream annotator created some input for an annotator which
        is invalid, the annotator may want to log this event, ignore the bad input and
        continue. It may include a notification of this event in the CAS, for further
        downstream annotators to consider. Or, it may throw an exception (see next section)
        &ndash; but in this case, it cannot do any further processing on that
        document.</para> <note><para>The choice of what to do can be made configurable,
      using the configuration parameters. </para></note>
      
    </section>
    
    <section id="ugr.tug.aae.throwing_exceptions_from_annotators">
      <title>Throwing Exceptions from Annotators</title>
      
      <para>Let&apos;s say an invalid regular expression was passed as a parameter to the
        RoomNumberAnnotator. Because this is an error related to the overall
        configuration, and not something we could expect to ignore, we should throw an
        appropriate exception, and most Java programmers would expect to do so like
        this:</para>
      
      
      <programlisting>throw new ResourceInitializationException(
    "The regular expression " + x + " is not valid.");</programlisting>
      
      <para>UIMA, however, does not do it this way. All UIMA exceptions are
        <emphasis>internationalized</emphasis>, meaning that they support translation
        into other languages. This is accomplished by eliminating hardcoded message
        strings and instead using external message digests. Message digests are files
        containing (key, value) pairs. The key is used in the Java code instead of the actual
        message string. This allows the message string to be easily translated later by
        modifying the message digest file, not the Java code. Also, message strings in the
        digest can contain parameters that are filled in when the exception is thrown. The
        format of the message digest file is described in the Javadocs for the Java class
        <literal>java.util.PropertyResourceBundle</literal> and in the load method of
        <literal>java.util.Properties</literal>.</para>
      
      <para>The first thing an annotator developer must choose is what Exception class to
        use. There are three to choose from:
        
        <orderedlist><listitem><para>ResourceConfigurationException should be
          thrown from the annotator&apos;s initialize() method if invalid configuration
          parameter values have been specified.</para></listitem>
          
          <listitem><para>ResourceInitializationException should be thrown from the
            annotator&apos;s initialize() method if initialization fails for some other
            reason.</para></listitem>
          
          <listitem><para>AnalysisEngineProcessException should be thrown from the
            annotator&apos;s process() method if the processing of a particular document
            fails for any reason. </para></listitem></orderedlist></para>
      
      <para>Generally you will not need to define your own custom exception classes, but if
        you do they must extend one of these three classes, which are the only types of
        Exceptions that the annotator interface permits annotators to throw.</para>
      
      <para>All of the UIMA Exception classes share common constructor varieties. There are
        four possible arguments:</para>
      
      <para>The name of the message digest to use (optional &ndash; if not specified the
        default UIMA message digest is used).</para>
      
      <para>The key string used to select the message in the message digest.</para>
      
      <para>An object array containing the parameters to include in the message. Messages
        can have substitutable parts. When the message is given, the string representation
        of the objects passed are substituted into the message. The object array is often
        created using the syntax new Object[]{x, y}.</para>
      
      <para>Another exception which is the <quote>cause</quote> of the exception you are
        throwing. This feature is commonly used when you catch another exception and rethrow
        it. (optional)</para>
      
      <para>If you look at source file (folder: src in Eclipse)
        <literal>org.apache.uima.tutorial.ex5.RoomNumberAnnotator</literal>, you
        will see the following code:
        
        
        <programlisting>try {
  mPatterns[i] = Pattern.compile(patternStrings[i]);
} 
catch (PatternSyntaxException e) {
  throw new ResourceInitializationException(
     MESSAGE_DIGEST, "regex_syntax_error",
     new Object[]{patternStrings[i]}, e);
}</programlisting>
        where the MESSAGE_DIGEST constant has the value <literal>
        "org.apache.uima.tutorial.ex5.RoomNumberAnnotator_Messages". </literal>
        </para>
      
      <para>Message digests are specified using a dotted name, just like Java classes. This
        file, with the .properties extension, must be present in the class path. In Eclipse,
        you find this file under the src folder, in the package
        org.apache.uima.tutorial.ex5, with the name
        RoomNumberAnnotator_Messages.properties. Outside of Eclipse, you can find this
        in the <literal>uimaj-examples.jar</literal> with the name
        <literal>org/apache/uima/tutorial/ex5/RoomNumberAnnotator_Messages.properties.</literal>
        If you look in this file you will see the line:
        
        
        <programlisting>regex_syntax_error = {0} is not a valid regular expression.</programlisting>
        which is the error message for the example exception we showed above. The placeholder
        {0} will be filled by the toString() value of the argument passed to the exception
        constructor &ndash; in this case, the regular expression pattern that didn&apos;t
        compile. If there were additional arguments, their locations in the message would be
        indicated as {1}, {2}, and so on.</para>
      
      <para>If a message digest is not specified in the call to the exception constructor, the
        default is <literal>UIMAException.STANDARD_MESSAGE_CATALOG</literal> (whose
        value is <quote><literal>org.apache.uima.UIMAException_Messages</literal>
        </quote> in the current release but may change). This message digest is located in the
        <literal>uima-core.jar</literal> file at
        <literal>org/apache/uima/UIMAException_messages.properties</literal>
        &ndash; you can take a look to see if any of these exception messages are useful to
        use.</para>
      
      <para>To try out the regex_syntax_error exception, just use the Document Analyzer to
        run
        <literal>examples/descriptors/tutorial/ex5/RoomNumberAnnotator.xml</literal>
        , which happens to have an invalid regular expression in its configuration parameter
        settings.</para>
      
      <para>To summarize, here are the steps to take if you want to define your own exception
        message:</para>
      
      <para>Create a file with the .properties extension, where you declare message keys and
        their associated messages, using the same syntax as shown above for the
        regex_syntax_error exception. The properties file syntax is more completely
        described in the Javadocs for the <ulink 
          url="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/docs/api/java/util/Properties.html#load(java.io.InputStream)">
        load</ulink> method of the java.util.Properties class.</para>
      
      <para>Put your properties file somewhere in your class path (it can be in your
        annotator&apos;s .jar file).</para>
      
      <para>Define a String constant (called MESSAGE_DIGEST for example) in your annotator
        code whose value is the dotted name of this properties file. For example, if your
        properties file is inside your jar file at the location
        <literal>org/myorg/myannotator/Messages.properties</literal>, then this
        String constant should have the value
        <literal>org.myorg.myannotator.Messages</literal>. Do not include the
        .properties extension. In Java Internationalization terminology, this is called
        the Resource Bundle name. For more information see the Javadocs for the <ulink
          url="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/docs/api/java/util/PropertyResourceBundle.html">
        PropertyResourceBundle</ulink> class.</para>
      
      <para>In your annotator code, throw an exception like this:
        
        <programlisting>throw new ResourceConfigurationException(
    MESSAGE_DIGEST, "your_message_name",
    new Object[]{param1,param2,...});</programlisting></para>
      
      <para>You may also wish to look at the Javadocs for the UIMAException class.</para>
      
      <para>For more information on Java&apos;s internationalization features, see the 
       <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/docs/guide/intl/index.html">
        Java Internationalization Guide</ulink>.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="ugr.tug.aae.accessing_external_resource_files">
      <title>Accessing External Resource Files</title>
      
      <para>Sometimes you may want an annotator to read from an external file &ndash; for
        example, a long list of keys and values that you are going to build into a HashMap. You
        could, of course, just introduce a configuration parameter that holds the absolute
        path to this resource file, and build the HashMap in your annotator&apos;s
        initialize method. However, this is not the best solution for three reasons:</para>
      
      <orderedlist><listitem><para>Including an absolute path in your descriptor makes
        your annotator difficult for others to use. Each user will need to edit this
        descriptor and set the absolute path to a value appropriate for his or her
        installation.</para></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>You cannot share the HashMap between multiple annotators. Also,
          in some deployment scenarios there may be more than one instance of your annotator,
          and you would like to have the option for them to use the same HashMap
          instance.</para></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>Your annotator would become dependent on a particular data
          representation &ndash; the word list would have to come from a file on the local disk
          and it would have to be in a particular format. It would be better if this were
          decoupled. </para></listitem></orderedlist>
      
      <para>A better way to access external resources is through the ResourceManager
        component. In this section we are going to show an example of how to use the Resource
        Manager.</para>
      
      <para>This example annotator will annotate UIMA acronyms (e.g. UIMA, AE, CAS, JCas)
        and store the acronym&apos;s expanded form as a feature of the annotation. The
        acronyms and their expanded forms are stored in an external file.</para>
      
      <para>First, look at the
        <literal>examples/descriptors/tutorial/ex6/UimaAcronymAnnotator.xml</literal>
        descriptor.
        
        
        <screenshot>
       <mediaobject>
       <imageobject>
         <imagedata width="5.7in" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;image036.jpg"/>
       </imageobject>
       <textobject><phrase>Screen shot of Component Descriptor Editor page for configuring External Resources
       </phrase></textobject>
     </mediaobject>

</screenshot></para>
      
      <para>The values of the rows in the two tables are longer than can be easily shown. You can
        click the small button at the top right to shift the layout from two side-by-side
        tables, to a vertically stacked layout. You can also click the small twisty on the
        <quote>Imports for External Resources and Bindings</quote> to collapse this
        section, because it&apos;s not used here. Then the same screen will appear like this:
        
        
        <screenshot>
       <mediaobject>
       <imageobject>
         <imagedata width="5.7in" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;image038.jpg"/>
       </imageobject>
       <textobject><phrase>Screen shot of Component Descriptor Editor page for configuring External Resources after
         adjusting the layout
       </phrase></textobject>
     </mediaobject>
</screenshot>
        </para>
      
      <para>The top window has a scroll bar allowing you to see the rest of the line.</para>
      
      <section id="ugr.tug.aae.resources.declaring_dependencies">
        <title>Declaring Resource Dependencies</title>
        
        <para>The bottom window is where an annotator declares an external resource
          dependency. The XML for this is as follows:</para>
        
        
        <programlisting><![CDATA[<externalResourceDependency>
  <key>AcronymTable</key> 
  <description>Table of acronyms and their expanded forms.</description> 
  <interfaceName>
    org.apache.uima.tutorial.ex6.StringMapResource
  </interfaceName> 
</externalResourceDependency>
]]></programlisting>
        
        <para>The &lt;key&gt; value (AcronymTable) is the name by which the annotator
          identifies this resource. The key must be unique for all resources that this
          annotator accesses, but the same key could be used by different annotators to mean
          different things. The interface name
          (<literal>org.apache.uima.tutorial.ex6.StringMapResource</literal>) is
          the Java interface through which the annotator accesses the data. Specifying an
          interface name is optional. If you do not specify an interface name, annotators
          will get direct access to the data file.</para>
      </section>
      
      <section id="ugr.tug.aae.resources.accessing_from_uimacontext">
        <title>Accessing the Resource from the UimaContext</title>
        
        <para> If you look at the
          <literal>org.apache.uima.tutorial.ex6.UimaAcronymAnnotator</literal>
          source, you will see that the annotator accesses this resource from the
          UimaContext by calling:
          
          
          <programlisting>StringMapResource mMap = 
  (StringMapResource)getContext().getResourceObject("AcronymTable");</programlisting>
          </para>
        
        <para>The object returned from the <literal>getResourceObject</literal> method
          will implement the interface declared in the
          <literal>&lt;interfaceName&gt;</literal> section of the descriptor,
          <literal>StringMapResource</literal> in this case. The annotator code does not
          need to know the location of the data nor the Java class that is being used to read the
          data and implement the <literal>StringMapResource</literal>
          interface.</para>
        
        <para>Note that if we did not specify a Java interface in our descriptor, our
          annotator could directly access the resource data as follows:
          
          
          <programlisting>InputStream stream = getContext().getResourceAsStream("AcronymTable");</programlisting></para>
        
        <para>If necessary, the annotator could also determine the location of the resource
          file, by calling:
          
          
          <programlisting>URI uri = getContext().getResourceURI("AcronymTable");</programlisting></para>
        
        <para>These last two options are only available in the case where the descriptor does
          not declare a Java interface.</para>
        
        <note><para>The methods for getting access to resources include <literal>getResourceURL</literal>.  That 
        method returns a URL, which may contain spaces encoded as %20.  url.getPath() would
        return the path without decoding these %20 into spaces.  <literal>getResourceURI</literal>
        on the other hand, returns a URI, and the uri.getPath() <emphasis>does</emphasis>
        do the conversion of %20 into spaces.  See also <literal>getResourceFilePath</literal>,
          which does a getResourceURI followed by uri.getPath().</para></note>
        
      </section>
      
      <section id="ugr.tug.aae.resources.declaring_and_bindings">
        <title>Declaring Resources and Bindings</title>
        
        <para>Refer back to the top window in the Resources page of the Component Descriptor
          Editor. This is where we specify the location of the resource data, and the Java
          class used to read the data. For the example, this corresponds to the following
          section of the descriptor:
          
          
          <programlisting><![CDATA[<resourceManagerConfiguration>
  <externalResources>
    <externalResource>
      <name>UimaAcronymTableFile</name> 
      <description>
         A table containing UIMA acronyms and their expanded forms.
      </description> 
      <fileResourceSpecifier>
        <fileUrl>file:org/apache/uima/tutorial/ex6/uimaAcronyms.txt
        </fileUrl> 
      </fileResourceSpecifier>
      <implementationName>
         org.apache.uima.tutorial.ex6.StringMapResource_impl
      </implementationName> 
    </externalResource>
  </externalResources>

  <externalResourceBindings>
    <externalResourceBinding>
      <key>AcronymTable</key>    
      <resourceName>UimaAcronymTableFile</resourceName> 
    </externalResourceBinding>
  </externalResourceBindings>
</resourceManagerConfiguration>
]]></programlisting></para>
        
        <para>The first section of this XML declares an externalResource, the
          <literal>UimaAcronymTableFile</literal>. With this, the fileUrl element
          specifies the path to the data file. This can be an absolute URL (e.g. one that starts
          with file:/ or file:///, or file://my.host.org/), but that is not recommended
          because it makes installation of your component more difficult, as noted earlier.
          Better is a relative URL, which will be looked up within the classpath (and/or
          datapath), as used in this example. In this case, the file
          <literal>org/apache/uima/tutorial/ex6/uimaAcronyms.txt</literal> is
          located in <literal>uimaj-examples.jar</literal>, which is in the classpath.
          If you look in this file you will see the definitions of several UIMA
          acronyms.</para>
        
        <para>The second section of the XML declares an externalResourceBinding, which
          connects the key <literal>AcronymTable</literal>, declared in the
          annotator&apos;s external resource dependency, to the actual resource name
          <literal>UimaAcronymTableFile</literal>. This is rather trivial in this case;
          for more on bindings see the example
          <literal>UimaMeetingDetectorAE.xml</literal> below. There is no global
          repository for external resources; it is up to the user to define each resource
          needed by a particular set of annotators.</para>
        
        <para>In the Component Descriptor Editor, bindings are indicated below the
          external resource. To create a new binding, you select an external resource (which
          must have previously been defined), and an external resource dependency, and then
          click the <literal>Bind</literal> button, which only enables if you have
          selected two things to bind together.</para>
        
        <para>When the Analysis Engine is initialized, it creates a single instance of
          <literal>StringMapResource_impl</literal> and loads it with the contents of
          the data file.  This means that the framework calls the instance's <literal>load</literal>
          method, passing it an instance of DataResource, from which you can obtain 
          a stream or URI/URL of the external resource that was declared in the external resource; 
          for resources where
          loading does not make sense, you can implement a <literal>load</literal> method
          which ignores its argument and just returns.  See the Javadocs for SharedResourceObject for
          details on this. 
          The UimaAcronymAnnotator then accesses the data through the
          <literal>StringMapResource</literal> interface. This single instance could
          be shared among multiple annotators, as will be explained later.
          Because of this, you should insure your implementation is thread-safe, as it 
          could be called multiple times on multiple threads.</para>
        
        <para>Note that all resource implementation classes (e.g.
          StringMapResource_impl in the provided example) must be declared public
          must not be declared abstract, and must have public, 0-argument constructors, so 
          that they can be instantiated by the framework. (Although Java classes in which 
          you do not define any constructor will, by default, have a 0-argument constructor
          that doesn&apos;t do anything, a class in which you have defined at least one
          constructor does not get a default 0-argument constructor.)</para>
        
        <para>This annotator is illustrated in <xref
            linkend="ugr.tug.aae.fig.external_resource_binding"/>. To see it in
          action, just run it using the Document Analyzer. When it finishes, open up the
          UIMA_Seminars document in the processed results window, (double-click it), and
          then left-click on one of the highlighted terms, to see the expandedForm
          feature&apos;s value.
          <figure id="ugr.tug.aae.fig.external_resource_binding">
            <title>External Resource Binding</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="3.7in" format="PNG"
                  fileref="&imgroot;image040.png"/>
              </imageobject>
              <textobject><phrase>External Resource Binding</phrase></textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure> </para>
        
        <para>By designing our annotator in this way, we have gained some flexibility. We can
          freely replace the StringMapResource_impl class with any other implementation
          that implements the simple StringMapResource interface. (For example, for very
          large resources we might not be able to have the entire map in memory.) We have also
          made our external resource dependencies explicit in the descriptor, which will
          help others to deploy our annotator.</para>
      </section>
      <section id="ugr.tug.aae.resources.sharing_among_annotators">
        <title>Sharing Resources among Annotators</title>
        
        <para>Another advantage of the Resource Manager is that it allows our data to be
          shared between annotators. To demonstrate this we have developed another
          annotator that will use the same acronym table. The UimaMeetingAnnotator will
          iterate over Meeting annotations discovered by the Meeting Detector we
          previously developed and attempt to determine whether the topic of the meeting is
          related to UIMA. It will do this by looking for occurrences of UIMA acronyms in close
          proximity to the meeting annotation. We could implement this by using the
          UimaAcronymAnnotator, of course, but for the sake of this example we will have the
          UimaMeetingAnnotator access the acronym map directly.</para>
        
        <para>The Java code for the UimaMeetingAnnotator in example 6 creates a new type,
          UimaMeeting, if it finds a meeting within 50 characters of the UIMA
          acronym.</para>
        
        <para>We combine three analysis engines, the UimaAcronymAnnotator to annotate
          UIMA acronyms, the MeetingDectector from example 4 to find meetings and finally
          the UimaMeetingAnnotator to annotate just meetings about UIMA. Together these
          are assembled to form the new aggregate analysis engine, UimaMeetingDectector.
          This aggregate and the sharing of a common resource are illustrated in <xref
            linkend="ugr.tug.aae.fig.sharing_common_resource"/>.
          <figure id="ugr.tug.aae.fig.sharing_common_resource">
            <title>Component engines of an aggregate share a common resource</title>
            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata width="5.7in" format="PNG"
                  fileref="&imgroot;image042.png"/>
              </imageobject>
              <textobject><phrase>Picture of Component engines of an aggregate sharing a
                common resource</phrase></textobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure> The important thing to notice is in the
          <literal>UimaMeetingDetectorAE.xml</literal> aggregate descriptor. It
          includes both the UimaMeetingAnnotator and the UimaAcronymAnnotator, and
          contains a single declaration of the UimaAcronymTableFile resource. (The actual
          example has the order of the first two annotators reversed versus the above
          picture, which is OK since they do not depend on one another).</para>
        
        <para>It also binds the resources as follows:
          
          
          <screenshot>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata width="5.7in" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;image044.jpg"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject><phrase>UimaMeetingDetectorAE.xml binding a common resource</phrase></textobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
          
          
          <programlisting><![CDATA[<externalResourceBindings>
  <externalResourceBinding>
    <key>UimaAcronymAnnotator/AcronymTable</key> 
    <resourceName>UimaAcronymTableFile</resourceName> 
  </externalResourceBinding>

  <externalResourceBinding>
    <key>UimaMeetingAnnotator/UimaTermTable</key> 
    <resourceName>UimaAcronymTableFile</resourceName> 
  </externalResourceBinding>
</externalResourceBindings>
]]></programlisting>
          </para>
        
        <para>This binds the resource dependencies of both the UimaAcronymAnnotator
          (which uses the name AcronymTable) and UimaMeetingAnnotator (which uses
          UimaTermTable) to the single declared resource named UimaAcronymFile.
          Therefore they will share the same instance. Resource bindings in the aggregate
          descriptor <emphasis role="bold-italic">override</emphasis> any resource
          declarations in individual annotator descriptors.</para>
        
        <para>If we wanted to have the annotators use different acronym tables, we could
          easily do that. We would simply have to change the resourceName elements in the
          bindings so that they referred to two different resources. The Resource Manager
          gives us the flexibility to make this decision at deployment time, without
          changing any Java code.</para>
        
      </section>
      
      <section id="ugr.tug.aae.resources.threading">
        <title>Threading and Shared Resources</title>
        <para>Sharing can also occur when multiple instances of an annotator are 
        created by the framework in response to run-time deployment specifications.
        If an implementation class is specified in the external resource, 
        only one instance of that implementation class  
          is created for a given binding, and is shared among all
        annotators.  Because of this, the implementation of that shared instance must be written to be
        thread-safe - that is, to operate correctly when called at arbitrary times
        by multiple threads.  Writing thread-safe code in Java is addressed in several
        books, such as Brian Goetz's <emphasis>Java Concurrency in Practice</emphasis>.</para>
        
        <para>
          If no implementation class is specified, then the getResource method returns a
          DataResource object, from which each annotator instance can obtain their
          own (non-shared) input stream; so threading is not an issue in this case.
        </para>
        
      </section>
    </section>
    <section id="ugr.tug.aae.result_specification_setting">
      <title>Result Specifications</title>
      
      <para>The Result Specification is passed to the annotator instance by calling its
        setResultSpecificaiton method. When called, the default implementation saves the
        result specification in an instance variable of the Annotator instance, which can be
        accessed by the annotator using the protected
        <literal>getResultSpecification()</literal> method.</para>
      
      <para>A Result Specification is a list of output types and / or type:feature
        names, catagorized by language(s), which are expected to be output from (produced by) the
        annotator. Annotators may use this to optimize their operations, when possible, for
        those cases where only particular outputs are wanted. The interface to the Result
        Specification object (see the Javadocs) allows querying both types and particular
        features of types.</para>
      
      <para>The languages specifications used by Result Specifications are the same that are
      specifiable in Capability Specifications; examples include "en" for English, "en-uk" for
      British English, etc.  There is also a language type, "x-unspecified", which is presumed
      if no language specification(s) are given.</para>
      
      <para>Result Specifications can be queryed by the Annotator code, and the query may 
      include the language.  If it doesn't include the language, it is treated as if the 
      language "x-unspecified" was specified.  Language matching is hierarchically defaulted,
      in one direction: if a query asks about a type T for language "en-uk", it will match
        for languages "en-uk", "en", or "x-unspecified".  However the reverse is not true:
        If the query asks about a type T for language "x-unspecified", then it only 
        matches Result Specifications with no language (or "x-unspecified", which is equivalent).
        </para>
      
      <para>
      The effect of this is that if the Result Specification indicates it wants output
      produced for "en-uk", but the annotator is given a language which is unknown, 
        or one that is known, but isn't "en-uk", then the query (using the language 
        of the document) will 
      return false.   This is true even if the language is "en".  
        However, if the Result Specification indicates it wants output for "en", 
      and the query is for "en-uk" (presumably because that's the language of the document
      and the annotator can handle that especially well), then the query will return true.
    </para> 
      
      
      <para>Sometimes you can specify the Result Specification; othertimes, you cannot
        (for instance, inside a Collection Processing Engine, you cannot). When you cannot
        specify it, or choose not to specify it (for example, using the form of the
        process(...) call on an Analysis Engine that doesn&apos;t include the Result
        Specification), a <quote>Default</quote> Result Specification is used.</para>
          
      <section id="ugr.tug.aae.result_spec.default">
        <title>Default ResultSpecification</title>
        
        <para>The default Result Specification is taken from the Engine&apos;s output
          Capability Specification. Remember that a Capability Specification has both
          inputs and outputs, can specify types and / or features, and there can be more than one
          Capability Set. If there is more than one set, the logical union by language of these sets is used.
          Each set can have a different "language(s)" specified; the default Result Specification 
          will have the outputs by language(s), so that the annotator can query which outputs 
          should be provided for particular languages.  The methods to query the Result Specification
          take a type and (optionally) a feature, and optionally, a language.  If the queried type is
          a subtype of some otherwise matching type in the Result Specification, it will match the query.  
          See the Javadocs for more details on this.
          </para>
        
      </section>
      
      <section id="ugr.tug.aae.result_spec.passing_to_annotators">
        <title>Passing Result Specifications to Annotators</title>
        
        <para>If you are not using a Collection Processing Engine, you can specify a Result
          Specification for your AnalysisEngine(s) by calling the
          <literal>AnalysisEngine.setResultSpecification(ResultSpecification)</literal>
          method.</para>
        <para>It is also possible to pass a Result Specification on each call to
          <literal>AnalysisEngine.process(CAS, ResultSpecification)</literal>. However,
          this is not recommended if your Result Specification will stay constant across
          multiple calls to
          <literal>process</literal>. In that case it will be more efficient to call
          <literal>AnalysisEngine.setResultSpecification(ResultSpecification)</literal>
          only when the Result Specification changes.</para>
        <para> For primitive Analysis Engines, whatever Result Specification you pass in is
          passed along to the annotator's
          <literal>setResultSpecification(ResultSpecification)</literal> method. For
          aggregate Analysis Engines, see below.</para>
      </section>
      
      <section id="ugr.tug.aae.result_spec.aggregates">
        <title>Aggregates</title>
        
        <para>For aggregate engines, the Result Specification passed to the
          <code>AnalysisEngine.setResultSpecification(ResultSpecification)</code>
          method is intended to specify the set of output types/features that the aggregate
          should produce. This is not necessarily equivalent to the set of output
          types/features that each annotator should produce. For example, an annotator may
          need to produce an intermediate type that is then consumed by a downstream annotator,
          even though that intermediate type is not part of the Result Specification.</para>
        <para>To handle this situation, when
          <code>AnalysisEngine.setResultSpecification(ResultSpecification)</code>
          is called on an aggregate, the framework computes the union of the passed Result
          Specification with the set of
          <emphasis>all</emphasis> input types and features of
          <emphasis>all</emphasis> component AnalysisEngines within that aggregate. This forms the
          complete set of types and features that any component of the aggregate might need to
          produce. This derived Result Specification is then passed to the
          <code>AnalysisEngine.setResultSpecification(ResultSpecification)</code>
          of each component AnalysisEngine. In the case of nested aggregates, this procedure
          is applied recursively.</para>
      </section>  
      <section id="ugr.tug.aae.result_spec.aggregates.cpes">
        <title>Collection Proessing Engines</title>
          
        <para>The Default Result Specification is always used for all components of a
          Collection Processing Engine.</para>        
      </section>
    </section>
    
    <section id="ugr.tug.aae.classpath_when_using_jcas">
      <title>Class path setup when using JCas</title>
      
      <para>JCas provides Java classes that correspond to each CAS type in an application.
        These classes are generated by the JCasGen utility (which can be automatically
        invoked from the Component Descriptor Editor).</para>
      
      <para>The Java source classes generated by the JCasGen utility are typically compiled
        and packaged into a JAR file. This JAR file must be present in the classpath of the UIMA
        application.</para>
      
      <para>For more details on issues around setting up this class path, including
        deployment issues where class loaders are being used to isolate multiple UIMA
        applications inside a single running Java Virtual Machine, please see <olink
          targetdoc="&uima_docs_ref;" targetptr="ugr.ref.jcas.class_loaders"/>
        .</para>
      
    </section>
    <section id="ugr.tug.aae.using_shell_scripts">
      <title>Using the Shell Scripts</title>
      
      <para>The SDK includes a <literal>/bin</literal> subdirectory containing shell
        scripts, for Windows (.bat files) and Unix (.sh files). Many of these scripts invoke
        sample Java programs which require a class path; they call a common shell script,
        <literal>setUimaClassPath</literal> to set up the UIMA required files and
        directories on the class path.</para>
      
      <para>If you need to include files on the class path, the scripts will add anything you
        specify in the environment variables CLASSPATH or UIMA_CLASSPATH to the classpath. So, for
        example, if you are running the document analyzer, and wanted it to find a Java class
        file named (on Windows) c:\a\b\c\myProject\myJarFile.jar, you could first issue a
        <literal>set</literal> command to set the UIMA_CLASSPATH to this file, followed by
        the documentAnalyzer script:
        
        
        <programlisting>set UIMA_CLASSPATH=c:\a\b\c\myProject\myJarFile.jar
documentAnalyzer</programlisting>
      </para>
      
      <para>Other environment variables are used by the shell scripts, as follows:
        
        <table frame="all" id="ugr.aae.tbl.env_vars_used_by_shell_scripts">
          <title>Environment variables used by the shell scripts</title>
          <tgroup cols="2" rowsep="1" colsep="1">
            <colspec colname="c1"/>
            <colspec colname="c2"/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry align="center">Environment Variable</entry>
                <entry align="center">Description</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>UIMA_HOME</entry>
                <entry>Path where the UIMA SDK was installed.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>JAVA_HOME</entry>
                <entry>(Optional) Path to a Java Runtime Environment. If not set, the Java
                  JRE that is in your system PATH is used.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>UIMA_CLASSPATH</entry>
                <entry>(Optional) if specified, a path specification to use as the default
                  ClassPath.  You can also set the CLASSPATH variable.  If you set both, they
                  will be concatenated.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>UIMA_DATAPATH</entry>
                <entry>(Optional) if specified, a path specification to use as the default
                  DataPath (see <olink targetdoc="&uima_docs_ref;"
                    targetptr="ugr.ref.xml.component_descriptor.datapath"/>)</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>UIMA_LOGGER_CONFIG_FILE</entry>
                <entry>(Optional) if specified, a path to a Java Logger properties file
                  (see <xref linkend="ugr.tug.aae.configuration_logging"/>)</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>UIMA_JVM_OPTS</entry>
                <entry>(Optional) if specified, the JVM arguments to be used when the Java
                  process is started.  This can be used for example to set the maximum Java
                  heap size or to define system properties.</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>VNS_PORT</entry>
                <entry>(Optional) if specified, the network IP port number of the Vinci
                  Name Server (VNS) (see <olink
                    targetdoc="&uima_docs_tutorial_guides;"
                    targetptr="ugr.tug.application.vns"/>)</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>ECLIPSE_HOME</entry>
                <entry>(Optional) Needs to be set to the root of your Eclipse installation
                  when using shell scripts that invoke Eclipse (e.g.
                  jcasgen_merge)</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
          
        </table> </para>
      
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section id="ugr.tug.aae.common_pitfalls">
    <title>Common Pitfalls</title>
    
    <para>Here are some things to avoid doing in your annotator code:</para>
    
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Retaining references to JCas objects between calls to
      process()</emphasis></para>
    
    <para>The JCas will be cleared between calls to your annotator&apos;s process() method.
      All of the analysis results related to the previous document will be deleted to make way
      for analysis of a new document. Therefore, you should never save a reference to a JCas
      Feature Structure object (i.e. an instance of a class created using JCasGen) and
      attempt to reuse it in a future invocation of the process() method. If you do so, the
      results will be undefined.</para>
    
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Careless use of static data</emphasis></para>
    
    <para>Always keep in mind that an application that uses your annotator may create
      multiple instances of your annotator class. A multithreaded application may attempt
      to use two instances of your annotator to process two different documents
      simultaneously. This will generally not cause any problems as long as your annotator
      instances do not share static data.</para>
    
    <para>In general, you should not use static variables other than static final constants
      of primitive data types (String, int, float, etc). Other types of static variables may
      allow one annotator instance to set a value that affects another annotator instance,
      which can lead to unexpected effects. Also, static references to classes that
      aren&apos;t thread-safe are likely to cause errors in multithreaded
      applications.</para>
    
  </section>
  <section id="ugr.tug.aae.viewing_UIMA_objects_in_eclipse_debugger">
    <title>Viewing UIMA objects in the Eclipse debugger</title>
    <titleabbrev>UIMA Objects in Eclipse Debugger</titleabbrev>
    
    <para>Eclipse (as of version 3.1 or later) has a new feature for viewing Java Logical
      Structures. When enabled, it will permit you to see a view of UIMA objects (such as
      feature structure instances, CAS or JCas instances, etc.) which displays the logical
      subparts. For example, here is a view of a feature structure for the RoomNumber
      annotation, from the tutorial example 1:
      
      
      <screenshot>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata width="5.7in" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;image046.jpg"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject><phrase>Screenshot of Eclipse debugger showing non-logical-structure display of 
      a feature structure</phrase></textobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot></para>
    
    <para>The <quote>annotation</quote> object in Java shows as a 2 element object, not very
      convenient for seeing the features or the part of the input that is being annotatoed. But
      if you turn on the Java Logical Structure mode by pushing this button:
      
      
      <screenshot>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata width="5.6in" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;image048.jpg"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject><phrase>Screenshot of Eclipse debugger showing button to push to 
        enable viewing logical structures</phrase></textobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
      the features of the FeatureStructure instance will be shown:
      
      
      <screenshot>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata width="5.7in" format="JPG" fileref="&imgroot;image050.jpg"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject><phrase>Screenshot of Eclipse debugger showing logical structure display of 
      an annotation</phrase></textobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot></para>
    
  </section>
  
  <section id="ugr.tug.aae.xml_intro_ae_descriptor">
    <title>Introduction to Analysis Engine Descriptor XML Syntax</title>
    <titleabbrev>Analysis Engine XML Descriptor</titleabbrev>
    
    <para>This section is an introduction to the syntax used for Analysis Engine
      Descriptors. Most users do not need to understand these details; they can use the
      Component Descriptor Editor Eclipse plugin to edit Analysis Engine Descriptors
      rather than editing the XML directly.</para>
    
    <para>This section walks through the actual XML descriptor for the RoomNumberAnnotator
      example introduced in section <xref linkend="ugr.tug.aae.getting_started"/>. The
      discussion is divided into several logical sections of the descriptor.</para>
    
    <para>The full specification for Analysis Engine Descriptors is defined in <olink
        targetdoc="&uima_docs_ref;" targetptr="ugr.ref.xml.component_descriptor"/>
      .</para>
    
    <section id="ugr.tug.aae.header_annotator_class_identification">
      <title>Header and Annotator Class Identification</title>
      
      
      <programlisting><?db-font-size 80% ?><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?> 
<!--  Descriptor for the example RoomNumberAnnotator. --> 
<analysisEngineDescription xmlns="http://uima.apache.org/resourceSpecifier">
  <frameworkImplementation>org.apache.uima.java</frameworkImplementation> 
  <primitive>true</primitive> 
  <annotatorImplementationName>
    org.apache.uima.tutorial.ex1.RoomNumberAnnotator
  </annotatorImplementationName>
]]></programlisting>
      
      <para>The document begins with a standard XML header and a comment. The root element of
        the document is named <literal>&lt;analysisEngineDescription&gt;,</literal>
        and must specify the XML namespace
        <literal>http://uima.apache.org/resourceSpecifier</literal>.</para>
      
      <para>The first subelement,
        <literal>&lt;frameworkImplementation&gt;</literal>, must contain the value
        <literal>org.apache.uima.java</literal>. The second subelement,
        <literal>&lt;primitive&gt;</literal>, contains the Boolean value true,
        indicating that this XML document describes a <emphasis>Primitive</emphasis>
        Analysis Engine. A Primitive Analysis Engine is comprised of a single annotator. It
        is also possible to construct XML descriptors for non-primitive or
        <emphasis>Aggregate</emphasis> Analysis Engines; this is covered later.</para>
      
      <para>The next element,
        <literal>&lt;annotatorImplementationName&gt;</literal>, contains the
        fully-qualified class name of our annotator class. This is how the UIMA framework
        determines which annotator class to instantiate.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section id="ugr.tug.aae.xml_intro_simple_metadata_attributes">
      <title>Simple Metadata Attributes</title>
      
      
      <programlisting><![CDATA[<analysisEngineMetaData>
  <name>Room Number Annotator</name> 
  <description>An example annotator that searches for room numbers in
     the IBM Watson research buildings.</description> 
  <version>1.0</version> 
  <vendor>The Apache Software Foundation</vendor></para>
]]></programlisting>
      
      <para>Here are shown four simple metadata fields &ndash; name, description, version,
        and vendor. Providing values for these fields is optional, but recommended.</para>
      
    </section>
    
    <section id="ugr.tug.aae.xml_intro_type_system_definition">
      <title>Type System Definition</title>
      
      
      <programlisting><![CDATA[<typeSystemDescription>
  <imports>
    <import location="TutorialTypeSystem.xml"/>
  </imports>
</typeSystemDescription>
]]></programlisting>
      
      <para>This section of the XML descriptor defines which types the annotator works with.
        The recommended way to do this is to <emphasis>import</emphasis> the type system
        definition from a separate file, as shown here. The location specified here should be
        a relative path, and it will be resolved relative to the location of the aggregate
        descriptor. It is also possible to define types directly in the Analysis Engine
        descriptor, but these types will not be easily shareable by others.</para>
      
    </section>
    
    <section id="ugr.tug.aae.xml_intro_capabilities">
      <title>Capabilities</title>
      
      
      <programlisting><![CDATA[<capabilities>
  <capability>
    <inputs /> 
    <outputs>
      <type>org.apache.uima.tutorial.RoomNumber</type> 
      <feature>org.apache.uima.tutorial.RoomNumber:building</feature> 
    </outputs>
  </capability>
</capabilities>
]]></programlisting>
      
      <para>The last section of the descriptor describes the
        <emphasis>Capabilities</emphasis> of the annotator &ndash; the Types/Features
        it consumes (input) and the Types/Features that it produces (output). These must be
        the names of types and features that exist in the ANALYSIS ENGINE descriptor&apos;s
        type system definition.</para>
      
      <para>Our annotator outputs only one Type, RoomNumber and one feature,
        RoomNumber:building. The fully-qualified names (including namespace) are
        needed.</para>
      
      <para>The building feature is listed separately here, but clearly specifying every
        feature for a complex type would be cumbersome. Therefore, a shortcut syntax exists.
        The &lt;outputs&gt; section above could be replaced with the equivalent section:
        
        
        <programlisting><![CDATA[<outputs>
  <type allAnnotatorFeatures ="true">
     org.apache.uima.tutorial.RoomNumber
  </type> 
</outputs>]]></programlisting></para>
      
    </section>
    
    <section id="ugr.tug.aae.xml_intro.configuration_parameters">
      <title>Configuration Parameters (Optional)</title>
      
      <section id="ugr.tug.aae.xml_intro.configuration_parameters_declarations">
        <title>Configuration Parameter Declarations</title>
        
        
        <programlisting><![CDATA[<configurationParameters>
  <configurationParameter>
    <name>Patterns</name> 
    <description>List of room number regular expression patterns.
    </description> 
    <type>String</type> 
    <multiValued>true</multiValued> 
    <mandatory>true</mandatory> 
  </configurationParameter>
  <configurationParameter>
    <name>Locations</name> 
    <description>List of locations corresponding to the room number
       expressions specified by the Patterns parameter.
    </description> 
    <type>String</type> 
    <multiValued>true</multiValued> 
    <mandatory>true</mandatory> 
  </configurationParameter>
</configurationParameters>]]></programlisting>
        
        <para>The <literal>&lt;configurationParameters&gt;</literal> element
          contains the definitions of the configuration parameters that our annotator
          accepts. We have declared two parameters. For each configuration parameter, the
          following are specified:
          
          <itemizedlist><listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">name</emphasis>
            &ndash; the name that the annotator code uses to refer to the parameter</para>
            </listitem>
            
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">description</emphasis>
              &ndash; a natural language description of the intent of the parameter</para>
            </listitem>
            
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">type</emphasis> &ndash; the data
              type of the parameter&apos;s value &ndash; must be one of String, Integer,
              Float, or Boolean.</para></listitem>
            
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">multiValued</emphasis>
              &ndash; true if the parameter can take multiple-values (an array), false if
              the parameter takes only a single value. </para></listitem>
            
            <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">mandatory</emphasis> &ndash; true
              if a value must be provided for the parameter </para></listitem>
          </itemizedlist></para>
        
        <para>Both of our parameters are mandatory and accept an array of Strings as their
          value.</para>
      </section>
      
      <section id="ugr.tug.aae.xml_intro_configuration_parameter_settings">
        <title>Configuration Parameter Settings</title>
        
        
        <programlisting><![CDATA[<configurationParameterSettings>
  <nameValuePair>
    <name>Patterns</name> 
    <value>
      <array>
        <string>b[0-4]d-[0-2]ddb</string> 
        <string>b[G1-4][NS]-[A-Z]ddb</string> 
        <string>bJ[12]-[A-Z]ddb</string> 
      </array>
    </value>
  </nameValuePair>
  <nameValuePair>
    <name>Locations</name> 
    <value>
      <array>
        <string>Watson - Yorktown</string> 
        <string>Watson - Hawthorne I</string> 
        <string>Watson - Hawthorne II</string> 
      </array>
    </value>
  </nameValuePair>
</configurationParameterSettings>]]></programlisting>
        
      </section>
      
      <section id="ugr.tug.aae.xml_intro.aggregate">
        <title>Aggregate Analysis Engine Descriptor</title>
        
        
        <programlisting><?db-font-size 80% ?><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?> 
<analysisEngineDescription xmlns="http://uima.apache.org/resourceSpecifier">
  <frameworkImplementation>org.apache.uima.java</frameworkImplementation> 
  <primitive>false</primitive> 

  <delegateAnalysisEngineSpecifiers>
    <delegateAnalysisEngine key="RoomNumber">
      <import location="../ex2/RoomNumberAnnotator.xml"/> 
    </delegateAnalysisEngine>
    <delegateAnalysisEngine key="DateTime">
      <import location="TutorialDateTime.xml" /> 
    </delegateAnalysisEngine>
  </delegateAnalysisEngineSpecifiers>]]></programlisting>
        
        <para>The first difference between this descriptor and an individual
          annotator&apos;s descriptor is that the
          <literal>&lt;primitive&gt;</literal> element contains the value
          <literal>false</literal>. This indicates that this Analysis Engine (AE) is an
          aggregate AE rather than a primitive AE.</para>
        
        <para>Then, instead of a single annotator class name, we have a list of
          <literal>delegateAnalysisEngineSpecifiers</literal>. Each specifies one of
          the components that constitute our Aggregate . We refer to each component by the
          relative path from this XML descriptor to the component AE&apos;s XML
          descriptor.</para>
        
        <para>This list of component AEs does not imply an ordering of them in the execution
          pipeline. Ordering is done by another section of the descriptor:
          
          
          <programlisting><![CDATA[<analysisEngineMetaData>
  <name>Aggregate AE - Room Number and DateTime Annotators</name> 
  <description>Detects Room Numbers, Dates, and Times</description> 
  <flowConstraints>
    <fixedFlow>
      <node>RoomNumber</node> 
      <node>DateTime</node> 
    </fixedFlow>
  </flowConstraints>]]></programlisting></para>
        
        <para>Here, a fixedFlow is adequate, and we specify the exact ordering in which the
          AEs will be executed. In this case, it doesn&apos;t really matter, since the
          RoomNumber and DateTime annotators do not have any dependencies on one
          another.</para>
        
        <para>Finally, the descriptor has a capabilities section, which has exactly the
          same syntax as a primitive AE&apos;s capabilities section:
          
          
          <programlisting><![CDATA[<capabilities>
  <capability>
    <inputs /> 
    <outputs>
      <type allAnnotatorFeatures="true">
        org.apache.uima.tutorial.RoomNumber
      </type> 
      <type allAnnotatorFeatures="true">
        org.apache.uima.tutorial.DateAnnot
      </type> 
      <type allAnnotatorFeatures="true">
        org.apache.uima.tutorial.TimeAnnot
      </type> 
    </outputs>
    <languagesSupported>
      <language>en</language> 
    </languagesSupported>
  </capability>
</capabilities>]]></programlisting>
          </para>
        
      </section>
      
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
